<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OXFORD//DTD OXCHAPML//EN" "OxChapML.dtd">
<book id="oso-9780198878230-book-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.001.0001" OSOsubject="physics">
<bookMeta id="oso-9780198878230-bookMeta-1">
<versionInfo>
<versionDate>2023-05-06</versionDate>
<versionDesc>Proofs</versionDesc>
</versionInfo>
<metaItem about="book">
<metaItem about="DTD">
<metaDescribes predicate="DTDname">OxChapML</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
<metaItem about="TCIgroup">
<metaItem about="TCI">
<metaDescribes predicate="TCIname">OUP TCI</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="version">20170301.0</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaItem>
<metaDescribes predicate="product">oso</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="colour-figures-for-online">Yes</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="publishing-group">oso US</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="captured-by">Integra</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</bookMeta>
<mainText id="oso-9780198878230-mainText-1">
<chapter id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003">
<metaInfo id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-metaInfo-1">
<versionInfo>
<versionDate>2023-05-06</versionDate>
<versionDesc>Proofs</versionDesc>
</versionInfo>
<creatorGroup>
<creator class="author" invertedForm="Barry, Frank"><forenames>Frank</forenames><surname>Barry</surname></creator>
</creatorGroup>
<abstract><p>This chapter identifies and details the histories of the notable manufacturing firms in operation in 1922, many of which appear in the pages of James Joyce&#x2019;s <i>Ulysses</i>, which is set in the Dublin of 1904. Many of the company names survive as well-known brands to the present day. No more than eighty manufacturing firms employed 500 or more at any stage up to 1972. Firms of this size are tracked throughout the book. A glimpse of the subsequent histories of others that were well known in 1922 is also provided. Food, drink, and tobacco accounted for almost 50 per cent of manufacturing employment in 1926, the benchmark&#x00A0;year for the first Free State Census of Industrial Production. Textiles, clothing, and footwear accounted for a further 20 per cent. The remainder were distributed across a range of other sectors. Major employers at the time included Guinness, biscuit company W. &#x0026; R. Jacob, the Ford tractor plant in Cork, the railway engineering works at Inchicore and Dundalk, and the massive Condensed Milk Company of Ireland, which would collapse in the early 1920s and whose history serves as a microcosm of the economic and political conflicts of the era. The several dozen breweries and distilleries in operation at the establishment of the state are also identified.</p>
</abstract>
<keySubjectWords>
<keyword>Joycean Dublin</keyword>
<keyword>Irish Free State</keyword>
<keyword>breweries</keyword>
<keyword>distilleries</keyword>
<keyword>Guinness</keyword>
<keyword>Jacobs</keyword>
<keyword>Ford</keyword>
<keyword>Condensed Milk Company of Ireland</keyword>
<keyword>bacon</keyword>
<keyword>creameries</keyword></keySubjectWords>
<disclaimer><p><i>Industry and Policy in Independent Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1972</i>. Frank Barry, Oxford University Press. &#x00A9; Frank Barry (2023). DOI: 10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003</p></disclaimer>
<metaItem about="book">
<metaItem about="DTD">
<metaDescribes predicate="DTDname">OxChapML</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
<metaItem about="TCIgroup">
<metaItem about="TCI">
<metaDescribes predicate="TCIname">OUP TCI</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="version">20170301.0</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaItem>
<metaDescribes predicate="product">oso</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="colour-figures-for-online">Yes</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="publishing-group">oso US</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="captured-by">Integra</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaInfo>
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-1"><title id="C3"><p><page id="37" chapter=""/><enumerator>3</enumerator> Firms of Note in 1922</p></title></titleGroup>
<textMatter id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-textMatter-1">
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div1-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.021.0001" role="prelim">
<p id="C3P1">Though the Irish Free State was predominantly agricultural at its establishment in 1922, several local manufacturing firms had significant international reputations. The Guinness brewery at St James&#x2019;s Gate was reputed to be the largest in the world, and biscuit-maker W. &#x0026; R. Jacob&#x2019;s Dublin factory remained far larger at the time than its recently established branch plant near Liverpool. Bacon curer Henry Denny and tobacco manufacturer P. J. Carroll also had substantial export trades, as did some of the country&#x2019;s textiles producers, distilleries, and other firms in particular niche areas. Very many more firms had significant reputations within the home market of course: manufactured goods (including processed foods) made up 50 per cent of the consumer price index of the 1920s, and in a number of sub-sectors the domestic market was dominated by local producers.</p>
<p id="C3P2">This chapter provides an outline of the histories of the notable manufacturing firms in operation in the Free State at independence, many of which appear in the pages of James Joyce&#x2019;s <i>Ulysses</i>, which is set in the Dublin of 1904. Those that employed a workforce of 500 or more at any stage through to 1972 will surface again in later chapters. Many other company names from the period survive as well-known brands down to the present day.</p>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div1-2" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.021.0002">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-2"><title id="C3S1"><p><enumerator>3.1</enumerator> Food, Drink, and Tobacco</p></title></titleGroup>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0001" role="prelim">
<p id="C3P3">Almost all of the processed products tested for a series of articles in the British medical journal <i>The Lancet</i> in the 1850s had been found to have been adulterated. Notwithstanding the significant legislation that followed, the persistence of careless or fraudulent practices made brand names of particular importance in Food, drink, and tobacco. Irish sectors varied substantially in terms of the quality and consistency of their produce, the factors on which the value of their brands depended. Bacon brands were valuable and guarded jealously; Irish butter was largely unbranded and had a poor reputation. Guinness prosecuted those engaged in adulteration; Irish whiskey brands were less well protected.</p>
<p alignment="centre"></p>
<p id="C3P4"><page id="38" chapter=""/><xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-1">3.1</xref></xrefGrp> shows the distribution of employment across the various sub-sectors of Food, drink, and tobacco in 1926, the first&#x00A0;year for which the Free State Census of Industrial Production was produced. Though employment levels would have been somewhat different in 1922, the numbers provided give a sense of the extent to which the leading firms dominated within each sub-sector. Brewing and bacon curing were highly concentrated, flour milling and bread production much less so. In some industries, the same firms would remain dominant throughout the entire period to European Economic Community (EEC) accession. In others, such as flour milling and tobacco, the largest firms at the end of Cumann na nGaedheal&#x2019;s period in office had been established in the Free State only over the previous decade. The order in which sectors are discussed largely follows that of the census.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-1"?></p>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-1">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0001" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-1" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-3"><title id="C3T1"><p><enumerator>Table 3.1</enumerator> Free State Census of Industrial Production (CIP), 1926: Food, Drink, and Tobacco</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Sector</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Employment, 1926 (excluding out-workers)</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Bacon curing</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,823</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Butter, cheese, condensed milk, and margarine</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>3,261</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Grain milling</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>3,012</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Bread, biscuits, and flour confectionery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>8,129</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Sugar confectionery and jam making</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>2,174</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Brewing</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>4,625</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Malting</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>945</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Distilling of spirits</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>429</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Aerated waters, ciders, cordials, and cognate liquors</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,001</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Tobacco</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>2,096</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-2" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0002">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-4"><title id="C3S2"><p>Bacon Curing</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P5">Bacon curing was concentrated primarily in the dairying regions of Munster, where pigs were raised on the milk that had been skimmed to extract butterfat. The hugely popular &#x2018;Limerick mild cure&#x2019; dated from the 1880s.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-1"><sup>1</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Several firms, including the market leaders Henry Denny &#x0026; Sons and O&#x2019;Mara Bacon, <page id="39" chapter=""/>held patents on aspects of the curing process and Irish produce&#x2014;particularly of Limerick origin&#x2014;sold at a premium on the London and US markets.</p>
<p id="C3P6">By the turn of the century, Limerick had overtaken Waterford as the centre of the bacon export trade. Waterford-based Denny had several plants in each of the cities as well as elsewhere in Munster. The other major Limerick operations&#x2014;O&#x2019;Maras, Mattersons, and Shaws&#x2014;were run by local families. The acquisition by one of the O&#x2019;Maras of the old Liberties firm Donnellys in 1907 gave them control of much of the Dublin trade. By the 1930s, the O&#x2019;Maras&#x2014;whose family firm would be renamed the Bacon Company of Ireland in 1938&#x2014;also had plants in Claremorris and Letterkenny.</p>
<p id="C3P7">The two largest bacon curers identified in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-2">3.2</xref></xrefGrp> were among the earliest Irish multinationals. Denny opened a factory in Chicago in 1882 and E. M. Denny&#x2014;a sister company established by one of the founder&#x2019;s sons who had moved to England to oversee their London agency&#x2014;later took ownership of the largest private bacon company in Denmark. The O&#x2019;Maras bought the rights to the Russian Bacon Company in 1891 and ran the operation, located at a rail junction 400 kilometres southeast of Moscow, for more than a decade. In 1902, they invested in an enterprise in the Balkans to which they brought over several of their Limerick staff to train the local workers in how to produce the types of bacon most highly prized on the London market.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-2"><sup>2</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-2"?></p>
<p id="C3P8">The individual bacon factories typically employed in the region of 100&#x2013;200 workers. Denny employed around 500 across its various plants in peacetime and perhaps substantially more during the First World War when E. M. Denny was official supplier to the war office. Control passed to the London sister company on the death of Charles Edward Denny in 1927. It would be among those derided as &#x2018;pseudo-Irish&#x2019; by National Farmers&#x2019; Association president Rikard Deasy in 1966.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-3"><sup>3</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Most of its operations had <page id="40" chapter=""/>transferred to Northern Ireland by then to avail of easier access to the British market.</p>
<p id="C3P9">While bacon curers and farmers battled over pig prices, there were instances of cooperation on product quality.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-4"><sup>4</sup></xref></xrefGrp> There were linkages, too, beyond the immediate sector. Daniel Denny, a younger brother of Henry, established a factory in Waterford to produce wrapping materials for the bacon trade, as J. &#x0026; L.F. Goodbody also did at Clara. Gouldings opened plants in Waterford and Limerick to source dried blood from the bacon factories for use as an organic fertilizer.</p>
<p id="C3P10">By the time of EEC accession, many of the older firms had been acquired and newer, larger, more diversified food producers had come to dominate the sector. The oldest surviving bacon factory in the country, the Denny facility near Gracedieu in Waterford City, closed in 1972.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-1" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>1</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-1" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Shaw, Alexander" partTitle="The Irish Bacon-Curing Industry" date="1902" title="Ireland: Industrial and Agricultural" page="254" place="Dublin" publisher="Brown and Nolan" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Alexander" mainName="Shaw" role="partAuthor">Alexander Shaw</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Irish Bacon-Curing Industry&#x2019;, in <i>Ireland: Industrial and Agricultural</i>, ed. <nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Department of Agriculture">Department of Agriculture</nameGrp> and <nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Technical Instruction">Technical Instruction</nameGrp> (Dublin: Brown and Nolan, 1902), 254.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-2" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>2</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-2" class="book" author="Lavelle, Patricia" date="1961" title="James O&#x2019;Mara: A Staunch Sinn F&#x00E9;iner, 1873&#x2013;1948" place="Dublin" publisher="Clonmore and Reynolds" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Patricia" mainName="Lavelle" role="author">Patricia Lavelle</nameGrp>, <i>James O&#x2019;Mara: A Staunch Sinn F&#x00E9;iner, 1873&#x2013;1948</i> (Dublin: Clonmore and Reynolds, 1961).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-3" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>3</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 28 June 1966. Others included Lunham Bros, which had been sold to a UK concern in 1928, and the Castlebar Bacon Company, which was British-owned from its establishment in 1917.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-4" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>4</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-3" class="book" author="Riordan, Edward J." date="1920" title="Modern Irish Trade and Industry" page="80" place="London, New York" publisher="Metheuen, E. P. Dutton" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Edward J." mainName="Riordan" role="author">Edward J. Riordan</nameGrp>, <i>Modern Irish Trade and Industry</i> (London, New York: Metheuen, E. P. Dutton, 1920), 80.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-2">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-2" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0002" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-2" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-5"><title id="C3T2"><p><enumerator>Table 3.2</enumerator> Employment in major bacon-curing firms</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Henry Denny &#x0026; Sons (1820)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>500 (1900), 400 (1931), 500 (1935, 1960), 700 (1968), <i>c</i>. 400 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>O&#x2019;Maras (1839)/Bacon Company of Ireland (1938)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 400 (1920s&#x2013;1930s), 500 (1960), 300 (1971)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-3" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0003">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-6"><title id="C3S3"><p>Dairy Products and Margarine</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P11">The highly variable quality of Irish farmhouse butter had caused it to be looked upon in Britain &#x2018;as only a very second-rate article&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-5"><sup>5</sup></xref></xrefGrp> These problems persisted into the creamery era initiated by the invention of the mechanical separator by Swedish engineer Gustav de Laval in 1878. Denmark&#x2019;s cooperatives produced butter to a consistently high standard and almost all of it was marketed from the early 1900s under a national trade mark, the &#x2018;Lurbrand&#x2019;. In Ireland, &#x2018;production methods were still primitive, and the marketing system, if such it could be called, was deplorable&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-6"><sup>6</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Over the fifty&#x00A0;years to 1910, Irish butter lost much of its share of the British market to Denmark.</p>
<p id="C3P12">At home, private and cooperative creameries battled for control of the sector. The &#x2018;war of attrition&#x2019; began around 1900 when two-thirds of creameries were in private ownership, many of them branches of British enterprises.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-7"><sup>7</sup></xref></xrefGrp> By 1920, two-thirds were cooperatives.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-8"><sup>8</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The remaining privately owned monolith was the Condensed Milk Company of Ireland. At its collapse in the <page id="41" chapter=""/>early 1920s, it employed a workforce of 3,000 across Munster, including 500 at its Lansdowne headquarters in Limerick City.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-9"><sup>9</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The individual cooperatives were tiny by comparison. Even by the 1930s, Mitchelstown&#x2019;s workforce remained below 200. The majority employed fewer than ten people.</p>
<p id="C3P13">The history of the Condensed Milk Company serves as a microcosm of the political and economic conflicts of the era. It was owned by the Quebec-born Cleeve brothers, the eldest of whom had come to Limerick as a young man to work for his mother&#x2019;s family. Condensed milk had grown in popularity following its use as an army ration during the American civil war. The Cleeves began to manufacture the product at Lansdowne in 1883, along with the tin cans in which it was sold. The company earned massive profits from army contracts during the Boer War and other major conflicts. Condensed milk exports came to fully half the value of Irish brewery exports in 1918.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-10"><sup>10</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The Cleeves, meanwhile, had expanded into butter, cream, cheese, and toffee, and had established scores of creameries, separating stations, and other operations in Limerick, Tipperary, and adjoining counties. They were more successful than the cooperatives in their quality control processes. While most Irish cheese disappeared from British shelves with the re-emergence of foreign supplies from the end of the First World War in 1918, theirs continued to sell &#x2018;for the simple reason that [its quality] was able to challenge comparison with cheese made anywhere&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-11"><sup>11</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C3P14">The war of attrition involved plants being located overly close to each other to capture local milk supplies. These could not then be operated to sufficient capacity during the winter months. Enemies of the Cleeves complained of their practice of &#x2018;sending carts miles away right into suppliers&#x2019; doors for milk <i>and paying fancy prices</i>&#x2019; (italics added).<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-12"><sup>12</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C3P15">That the Cleeves were unionist did not spare their creameries from British military reprisals against the rural population during the war of independence.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-13"><sup>13</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Their large industrial labour force also rendered them vulnerable to the wave of &#x2018;soviet&#x2019; or &#x2018;red flag&#x2019; agitation that swept the country in the wake of the Russian Revolution. A major cause of the bitter industrial relations environment was the deflation of the&#x00A0;years following the end of the First World War, to which businesses responded by attempting to impose wage cuts. For the Condensed Milk Company, the problem was even more acute: the large amounts of produce it held in stock had collapsed in value with the <page id="42" chapter=""/>end of the agricultural boom in 1920. Ill will between workers and farmers led to the destruction of plant and equipment during the factory occupations, and further damage was inflicted by the Irregulars during the civil war.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-14"><sup>14</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The company&#x2019;s collapse in 1923 would lead eventually to the establishment of the Dairy Disposal Company, one of the first state-sponsored bodies of the Free State era.</p>
<p id="C3P16">Though milk distribution is not included in the Census of Industrial Production, the major Dublin distributors&#x2014;Hughes Brothers of Rathfarnham, Merville Dairies of Finglas, and Tel-el-Kebir of Monkstown&#x2014;began to pasteurize and bottle their milk supplies in the early 1920s.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-15"><sup>15</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The H. B. brand of ice cream first appeared on the market in 1926. By the 1960s, the milk distributors had become major employers. Premier Dairies&#x2014;formed from the amalgamation of Merville, Tel-el-Kebir, and a later entrant, Dublin Dairies&#x2014;had a workforce of 1,500 at its establishment in 1966. The largest milk distributors are included among the major dairy firms identified in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-3">3.3</xref></xrefGrp>.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-3"?></p>
<p id="C3P17">There were also in the 1920s two well-known Irish margarine producers. Margarine had been developed by a French chemist in 1869 and Limerick butter merchants W. &#x0026; C. McDonnell and Cork firm Dowdall, O&#x2019;Mahoney &#x0026; Co. had both entered the industry following study visits by the proprietors to Continental Europe. Employment at McDonnells peaked at 400 during the First World War. Its buy-out by the Dutch company J&#x00FC;rgens in 1918 is described in the Unilever archives as &#x2018;the first in a wave of post-war competitor acquisitions&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-16"><sup>16</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Dowdall, O&#x2019;Mahoney &#x0026; Co. remained the smaller of the two. It would be acquired by US firm Kraft Foods in 1969.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-5" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>5</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-4" class="book" date="1892" title="Strattens&#x2019; Dublin, Cork and South of Ireland: A Literary, Commercial and Social Review, with a Description of Leading Mercantile Houses and Commercial Enterprises" page="152" place="London" publisher="Stratten &#x0026; Stratten" purpose="display"><i>Strattens&#x2019; Dublin, Cork and South of Ireland: A Literary, Commercial and Social Review, with a Description of Leading Mercantile Houses and Commercial Enterprises</i> (London: Stratten &#x0026; Stratten, 1892), 152.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-6" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>6</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-5" class="book" author="Bolger, Patrick" date="1977" title="The Irish Co-operative Movement: Its History and Development" page="64" place="Dublin" publisher="Institute of Public Administration" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Patrick" mainName="Bolger" role="author">Patrick Bolger</nameGrp>, <i>The Irish Co-operative Movement: Its History and Development</i> (Dublin: Institute of Public Administration, 1977), 64.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-7" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>7</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-6" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Fox, P. F.|Breathnach, Proinnsias" partTitle="Proprietary Creameries in Ireland" editor="Foynes, Peter|Rynne, Colin|Synnott, Chris" date="2014" title="Butter in Ireland: From Earliest Times to the 21st Century" page="67" pageLast="70" place="Cork" publisher="Cork Butter Museum" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="P. F." mainName="Fox" role="partAuthor">P. F. Fox</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames=" Proinnsias" mainName="Breathnach" role="partAuthor">Proinnsias Breathnach</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Proprietary Creameries in Ireland&#x2019;, in <i>Butter in Ireland: From Earliest Times to the 21st Century</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Peter" mainName="Foynes" role="editor">Peter Foynes</nameGrp>, <nameGrp foreNames="Colin" mainName="Rynne" role="editor">Colin Rynne</nameGrp>, and <nameGrp foreNames="Chris" mainName="Synnott" role="editor">Chris Synnott</nameGrp> (Cork: Cork Butter Museum, 2014), 67&#x2013;70.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-8" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>8</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-7" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Fox, P. F.|Breathnach, Proinnsias" partTitle="Proprietary Creameries in Ireland" editor="Foynes, Peter|Rynne, Colin|Synnott, Chris" date="2014" title="Butter in Ireland: From Earliest Times to the 21st Century" page="67" pageLast="70" place="Cork" publisher="Cork Butter Museum" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-6">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>.; <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-8" class="book" author="Jenkins, William" date="1999" title="Tipp Co-op: Origin and Development of Tipperary Co-operative Creamery Ltd" page="50" place="Dublin" publisher="Geography Publications" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="William" mainName="Jenkins" role="author">William Jenkins</nameGrp>, <i>Tipp Co-op: Origin and Development of Tipperary Co-operative Creamery Ltd</i> (Dublin: Geography Publications, 1999), 50.</bibItem>; Bolger, <i>The Irish Co-operative Movement</i>, 196&#x2013;98.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-9" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>9</sup></enumerator> <i>Cork Examiner</i>, 13 May 1922.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-10" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>10</sup></enumerator> Riordan, <i>Modern Irish Trade and Industry</i>, 157, 91.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-11" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>11</sup></enumerator> Jenkins, <i>Tipp Co-op</i>, 68, 77.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-12" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>12</sup></enumerator> Cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-9" class="book" author="Jenkins, William" date="1999" title="Tipp Co-op: Origin and Development of Tipperary Co-operative Creamery Ltd" page="50" place="Dublin" publisher="Geography Publications" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-8">ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem><i>.</i>, 33, 60.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-13" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>13</sup></enumerator> See e.g. <i>Freemans Journal</i>, 30 September 1920.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-14" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>14</sup></enumerator> Jenkins, <i>Tipp Co-op</i>, 73&#x2013;77.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-15" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>15</sup></enumerator> Tel-el-Kebir, which was founded in 1884, derived its exotic name from a battle in Egypt at which the firm&#x2019;s founder had saved the regimental colours: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-10" class="book" author="Doyle, Pat|P. F. Smith, Louis" date="1989" title="Milk to Market: A History of Dublin Milk Supply" page="96" pageLast="97" place="Dublin" publisher="Leinster Milk Producers&#x2019; Association" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Pat" mainName="Doyle" role="author">Pat Doyle</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Louis" mainName="P. F. Smith" role="author">Louis P. F. Smith</nameGrp>, <i>Milk to Market: A History of Dublin Milk Supply</i> (Dublin: Leinster Milk Producers&#x2019; Association, 1989), 96&#x2013;97.</bibItem> It was owned by the Sutton family, the only Catholic proprietors among the group. Merville was owned by the Craigie brothers.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-16" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>16</sup></enumerator> Unilever archives: Unilever Ireland (Holdings) Ltd and Subsidiary Companies: B1752.IRE/WM, 1858.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-3">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-3" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0003" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-3" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-7"><title id="C3T3"><p><enumerator>Table 3.3</enumerator> Employment in selected firms in the dairy sector</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Condensed Milk Company of Ireland</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>2,000 (1898), 3,000 (1922)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Merville Dairies (pasteurization, bottling, distribution, ice cream production)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>150 (1932), 540 (1960)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Hughes Brothers (as for Merville)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>70 (1935), 110 (1941), 800 (1968)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-4" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0004">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-8"><title id="C3S4"><p><page id="43" chapter=""/>Bread, Grain Milling, and Flour Confectionery</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P18">Bread had displaced the potato as the staple of the Irish diet since the famine of the 1840s. It made up 6 per cent of the consumer price index in the 1920s (ten times its weight in the index for 2022) and an even higher share of wage expenditures.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-17"><sup>17</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The largest of the many hundreds of substantial bakery companies were the four industrial-scale producers mentioned in the previous chapter. Bolands and Johnston, Mooney &#x0026; O&#x2019;Brien also produced the bulk of their own flour: the former since its acquisition of Pim&#x2019;s Mills on Grand Canal Dock in 1873, the latter since its formation in 1889.</p>
<p id="C3P19">By the turn of the century, Bolands had added a further two huge establishments to its original premises on Capel Street: one was in Kingstown (Dun Laoghaire), the other was the massive City of Dublin bakery on Grand Canal Street that would serve as de Valera&#x2019;s headquarters in the 1916 Rising. By 1924, the third largest Dublin producer, Kennedys, had added a further five bakeries to its original establishment on Parnell Street.</p>
<p id="C3P20">Flour milling as a stand-alone activity was dominated by Bannatyne &#x0026; Sons, with Odlums a distant second. Bannatyne controlled a number of mills in Limerick and elsewhere across Munster as well as the Goodbody mills in Clara. The earliest Odlum mills in Maryborough/Portlaoise dated from 1845. Others had been acquired or established across south Leinster over the following decades. By the 1970s, all of the major bread and flour producers were vertically integrated. Odlums and Kennedys had taken their first steps towards integration in 1924 when they participated in the establishment of the Dublin Port Milling Company, part of the milling complex that comprises the only surviving landmark of majesty in the Dublin docklands of today.</p>
<p id="C3P21">Other grain millers of note in the early Free State era included the Shackletons of County Kildare&#x2014;extended family of the famous Antarctic explorer&#x2014;and the Pollexfens of Sligo, maternal family of W. B. Yeats, of whom he wrote with great affection in his various memoirs and his 1914 poem &#x2018;Pardon, Old Fathers&#x2019;. The Pollexfen mills were in Sligo, Mayo, and South Donegal. The Shackleton mills, the most significant of which&#x2014;the Anna Liffey mill in Lucan&#x2014;would remain in operation until the 1990s, were in Carlow, Kildare, and Dublin. Polar explorer Ernest Shackleton&#x2019;s branch of the family operated the Barrow Mills in Carlow. These were bankrupted in 1927 and resurrected as the Barrow Milling Company in 1935.</p>
<p id="C3P22"><page id="44" chapter=""/>&#x2018;Fancy biscuits&#x2019; had grown in popularity with the fall in prices that followed the application of steam power to the production process in the 1840s. Brothers William and Robert Jacob, whose family had been bakers of sea biscuits or &#x2018;hard tack&#x2019; in Waterford, opened a substantial new &#x2018;steam biscuit factory&#x2019; in Dublin in 1853 when their recent entry into the market for fancy biscuits proved a success. The British sector was dominated by Quaker firms, which the public regarded as trustworthy. The Jacobs too were Quakers, as were their future partners, the Bewleys.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-4"?></p>
<p id="C3P23">The company&#x2019;s export trade took off in the 1880s with the launch of the cream cracker, which was developed following a visit by the proprietor to the United States to study the popularity of the American soda biscuit. Two of its other enduring varieties also date from the late Victorian era. Its &#x2018;Mikado&#x2019; capitalized on the wave of orientalism that swept the United Kingdom at the time; its &#x2018;Kimberley&#x2019; was named for the gemstone areas relieved from siege in 1900 during the second Boer War.</p>
<p id="C3P24">Space constraints at the Dublin factory necessitated the use of expensive night-time shift work, and it was reportedly for this reason that a decision was taken to begin construction of a branch plant near Liverpool in 1912. The new factory expanded rapidly due to the &#x2018;enormous demand of the army and navy canteens in every part of the world&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-18"><sup>18</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Fear of punitive taxation led to the operations being split into separate companies in 1922. By 1932 the workforce at Aintree had grown to equal that of the Dublin plant and by 1954 had expanded to 5,000, more than twice the size of its former parent (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-4">3.4</xref></xrefGrp>). Though the Jacobs were regarded as paternalistic employers, this had not saved them from becoming centrally involved in the bitter Dublin industrial dispute of 1913.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-17" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>17</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Independent</i>, 12 May 1928.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-18" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>18</sup></enumerator> The Ambassador of Commerce: supplement to <i>Liverpool Daily Post and Mercury</i>, 7 July 1924, 57.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-4">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-4" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0004" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-4" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-9"><title id="C3T4"><p><enumerator>Table 3.4</enumerator> Employment in selected firms in bread, biscuits, and grain milling</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Jacobs (biscuits)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>3,000 (1911, 1928), 2,000 (1951), &#x003E;2,000 (up to 1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Bolands (bread and flour)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>800 (1888), 420 (1925), 500 (1935), 600 (1939), &#x003E;500 (to 1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Johnston, Mooney &#x0026; O&#x2019;Brien (bread and flour)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>450 (1936), 600 (1941), &#x003E;500 (to 1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Kennedys (bread)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>540 (1948), 400 (1971), closed 1971</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Bannatyne/Goodbody (flour)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 500 (1900), <i>c</i>. 800 (1929); acquired by Ranks (1930)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Odlums (flour)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>300 (1938, 1963), <i>c</i>. 500 (1972), Odlum Group &#x003E;1,000 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-5" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0005">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-10"><title id="C3S5"><p>Sugar Confectionery</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P25"><page id="45" chapter=""/>The structure of the sugar confectionery sector would change dramatically with the Cumann na nGaedheal tariffs of the 1920s. Dublin firm Williams &#x0026; Woods was by far the largest producer of sweets and jams in the Free State in 1922. The other major jam producer was the Quaker firm Lamb Brothers, originators of the Fruitfield label (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-5">3.5</xref></xrefGrp>). Armagh-based Lambs had opened a factory in Inchicore in 1918 and would transfer its headquarters to Dublin in 1944.</p>
<p id="C3P26">Methodist-owned sweet maker Lemons had relocated to the Confectioners&#x2019; Hall on Dublin&#x2019;s Sackville Street (now O&#x2019;Connell Street) in the 1840s. Leopold Bloom, fictional hero of Joyce&#x2019;s <i>Ulysses</i>, muses on its signage as he gazes through the window on his wanderings:</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-displayText-1" class="verse">
<lineGroup>
<line>Lozenge and comfit manufacturer to His Majesty the King.</line>
<line>God. Save. Our. Sitting on his throne sucking red jujubes white.</line>
</lineGroup>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C3P27">Lemons had a management relationship with Savoy Cocoa, another retailer-turned-manufacturer, and would take over a recently developed factory of Savoy&#x2019;s in Drumcondra when trade expanded with the tariffs of the mid-1920s. Toffee maker North Kerry Manufacturing (NKM) transferred production from Listowel to Dublin in 1921. NKM and Savoy Cocoa would both be taken over by major UK confectionery manufacturers within a&#x00A0;year or so of the Cumann na nGaedheal tariffs coming into effect.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-5"?></p>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-5">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-5" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0005" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-5" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-11"><title id="C3T5"><p><enumerator>Table 3.5</enumerator> Employment in selected firms in sugar confectionery</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Williams &#x0026; Woods (1856), Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>200 (1897), 477 (1924), &#x003E;500 (from late 1920s)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Lambs (1918), Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>200 (1936), 375 (1960), 300 (1971)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-6" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0006">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-12"><title id="C3S6"><p>Brewing, Bottling, and Malting</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P28">The Guinness brewery at St James&#x2019;s Gate was referred to in an 1889 guide to the breweries of the United Kingdom as &#x2018;without doubt the largest establishment of its kind in the world&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-19"><sup>19</sup></xref></xrefGrp> A supplement to the <i>Manchester Guardian</i> in <page id="46" chapter=""/>1923 noted that its output was considerably greater than the joint output of the next two largest breweries of the time.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-20"><sup>20</sup></xref></xrefGrp> From the 1820s, with the establishment of a steamer service to Liverpool and the expansion of the British railway network, its growth had been primarily export-driven. Indeed, it was, for a long time, better known in England than in parts of the west of Ireland.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-21"><sup>21</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C3P29">Having abandoned ale brewing at an early stage in its history, the company by the 1920s was producing three basic varieties of stout and porter. Its porter was sold only in Ireland at this stage and was typically consumed on draught. Its main product, Extra Stout, was sold across Britain and Ireland and bottled by specialist firms or by the publicans to whom it was delivered, while Foreign Extra Stout was produced for warmer climatic conditions and exported to more distant locations.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-22"><sup>22</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Product consistency had been achieved by 1821 by the adoption of a standard procedure for the production of Extra Stout (then known as Extra Superior).<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-23"><sup>23</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Leaving bottling to others was cost-effective but raised the possibility of adulteration, which Guinness countered by appointing travelling investigators and a qualified chemist to support its pursuit of transgressors through the courts.</p>
<p id="C3P30">Employment at St James&#x2019;s Gate exceeded 1,000 by the mid-1800s and had reached 3,500 by the early twentieth century. All of the other Irish breweries were tiny by comparison. Those in operation in the Free State in 1922 are listed in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-6">3.6</xref></xrefGrp>.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-24"><sup>24</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Three had closed by 1926. Around half of the remainder had closed by 1972. Many of the others had changed hands over the previous two decades.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-25"><sup>25</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-6"?></p>
<p id="C3P31">The fortunes of the bottling and malting industries were closely related to those of Guinness and the distilleries. By 1892, E. &#x0026; J. Burke had operations in New York and Liverpool as well as in Dublin, and was &#x2018;the largest shipper in the world of Guinness&#x2019;s extra foreign stout, and the most extensive exporter <page id="47" chapter=""/><page id="48" chapter=""/>of cased whiskey in Dublin&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-26"><sup>26</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Burke employed 150 at its bottling plant and bonded warehouses off Dublin&#x2019;s Bachelors Walk in 1913. The company also owned the Hibernian Glass Bottle Works in Ringsend.</p>
<p id="C3P32">The scores of malthouses dotted across the country represented the main source of demand for Irish barley. Though farmers railed against what they saw as Guinness&#x2019;s exploitation of its near-monopoly position, by 1913 the company was purchasing more than twice as much of the crop as it had done thirty&#x00A0;years previously. In addition, thanks to the experimental programmes it conducted with maltsters John H. Bennett &#x0026; Co., and with the Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction, &#x2018;a much larger proportion of the crop was of malting quality, commanding a higher price&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-27"><sup>27</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Other brewers, to the same end, imported selected seeds, which they supplied to farmers at cost price.</p>
<p id="C3P33">Minch Norton would become the largest stand-alone malt producer following the merger of the two Midlands-based family businesses in 1921. It employed 150 across its ten establishments in the 1930s. Beamish &#x0026; Crawford produced much of its own malt, as did the Tullamore distillery of D. E. Williams, which had partner maltings in Banagher, Birr and other neighbouring areas.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-19" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>19</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-11" class="book" date="1889" title="The Noted Breweries of Great Britain and Ireland" vol="3" place="London" publisher="Joseph Causton &#x0026; Sons" purpose="display">Alfred Barnard, <i>The Noted Breweries of Great Britain and Ireland</i>, Vol. 3 (London: Joseph Causton &#x0026; Sons, 1889), 3, 6</bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-20" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>20</sup></enumerator> <i>Manchester Guardian Commercial</i>, 26 July 1923.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-21" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>21</sup></enumerator> Cormac &#x00D3; Gr&#x00E1;da, &#x2018;Triocha bliain ag f&#x00E1;s: Some Reflections on a Classic&#x2019;. Contribution to a conference marking the thirtieth anniversary of the publication of J. J. Lee&#x2019;s <i>Ireland: Politics and Society</i>, Royal Irish Academy, 24 April 2019.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-22" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>22</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-12" class="book" author="Dublin Port and Docks Board" date="1926" title="Dublin Port Yearbook" page="53" place="Dublin" publisher="Dublin Port and Docks Board" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Dublin Port and Docks Board">Dublin Port and Docks Board</nameGrp>, <i>Dublin Port Yearbook</i> (Dublin: Dublin Port and Docks Board, 1926), 53.</bibItem> Guinness began to brew draught stout in 1959. Porter production ceased in 1973.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-23" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>23</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-13" class="book" author="Lynch, Patrick|Vaizey, John" date="1960" title="Guinness&#x2019;s Brewery in the Irish Economy 1759&#x2013;1876" page="160" place="Cambridge" publisher="Cambridge University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Patrick" mainName="Lynch" role="author">Patrick Lynch</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="John" mainName="Vaizey" role="author">John Vaizey</nameGrp>, <i>Guinness&#x2019;s Brewery in the Irish Economy 1759&#x2013;1876</i> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1960), 160.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-24" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>24</sup></enumerator> The table is compiled from a report in the <i>Freemans Journal</i> of 7 March 1917 and from Riordan, <i>Modern Irish Trade and Industry</i>, 159&#x2013;60. A number of others mentioned in these sources had closed by 1922.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-25" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>25</sup></enumerator> Accurate dating is complicated by the fact that the breweries and the brewery companies that operated them are not synonymous. In the case of Watkins, Riordan provides a date of 1736, the company&#x2019;s advertisements referred to its &#x2018;celebrated beer and porter, best in 1789, best today&#x2019;, while the company name was adopted only in 1905 when Joseph Watson &#x0026; Co. merged with Jameson &#x0026; Pim. As in the case of Guinness, new breweries were frequently constructed on the foundations of existing ones. Beer is said to have been brewed at the Watkins site in Dublin&#x2019;s Liberties since before the dissolution of the monasteries: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-14" class="book" date="1912" title="Whitaker&#x2019;s Red Book of Commerce, or Who&#x2019;s Who in Business" place="London" publisher="J. Whitaker and Sons" purpose="display"><i>Whitaker&#x2019;s Red Book of Commerce, or Who&#x2019;s Who in Business</i> (London: J. Whitaker and Sons, 1912).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-26" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>26</sup></enumerator> <i>Strattens&#x2019; Dublin, Cork and South of Ireland: A Literary, Commercial and Social Review</i>, 36. The Liverpool house also bottled Bass for export across the world.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-27" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>27</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-15" class="book" author="Dennison, Stanley R.|MacDonagh, Oliver" date="1998" title="Guinness 1886&#x2013;1939: From Incorporation to the Second World War" page="102" place="Cork" publisher="Cork University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Stanley R." mainName="Dennison" role="author">Stanley R. Dennison</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Oliver" mainName="Macdonagh" role="author">Oliver MacDonagh</nameGrp>, <i>Guinness 1886&#x2013;1939: From Incorporation to the Second World War</i> (Cork: Cork University Press, 1998), 102.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-6">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-6" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0006" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-6" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-13"><title id="C3T6"><p><enumerator>Table 3.6</enumerator> Free State breweries in operation in 1922</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Company, location, and date of establishment</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Developments to 1972</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Selected employment</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Arthur Guinness, St James&#x2019;s Gate, Dublin (1759)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Remains in operation</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>3,000 (1923), remains generally &#x003E;3,000 up to 1972</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Beamish &#x0026; Crawford (1792)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Acquired by Canadian Breweries 1962</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>&#x003E;100 (1907), 150 (1936), 170 (1962), 350 (1970)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Cairnes:</p>
<p>(i)&#x00A0;Castlebellingham, County Louth (early eighteenth century); (ii) Drogheda, County Louth (1825)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>(i)&#x00A0;Castlebellingham brewery closed 1923;</p>
<p>(ii) Drogheda brewery acquired by Guinness 1959; closed 1961</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>(i)&#x00A0;53 (1923)</p>
<p>(ii) 207 (1939)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Cherry Bros, Creywell Brewery, New Ross, County Wexford (<i>c</i>. 1830)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Acquired by Guinness 1952; brewery closed 1955 and production moved to Strangman in Waterford</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>60 (1936)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>John D&#x2019;Arcy and Son, Anchor Brewery, Usher Street, Dublin (1818)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Brewery closed 1926; production moved to Watkins, Jameson &#x0026; Pim</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>&#x2013;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Deasy and Co., Clonakilty, County Cork (1780)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Brewing ceased <i>c</i>. 1940.</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>30 (1941)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>P. &#x0026; H. Egan, Tullamore, County Offaly (1852)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Brewing ceased <i>c</i>. 1924.</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>&#x2013;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Great Northern Brewery, Dundalk, County Louth (1897)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Acquired by Smithwicks 1953; sold to Guinness 1960; converted to production of Harp Lager</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>24 (1941, 1960), 130 (1971)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>P. Kiely and Sons, St Stephen&#x2019;s Brewery, Waterford (1835)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Brewing ceased 1947</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>20 (1935)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>George H. Lett, Mill Park Brewery, Enniscorthy, County Wexford (1810)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Brewing ceased 1956</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>&#x2013;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Macardle, Moore and Co., Dundalk (1863)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Acquired by Irish Ale Breweries &#x0026; Guinness, 1962</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>90 (1958), 150 (1968)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Mountjoy Brewery (Findlater&#x2019;s), Russell Street, Dublin (1852)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Closed 1956</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>60 (1935)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>James J. Murphy and Co., Lady&#x2019;s Well Brewery, Cork (1856)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Acquired by Watney Mann 1967</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>216 (1914), 170 (1935), 200 (1960)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Thomas Murphy and Co., Clonmel, County Tipperary (1838)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Closed <i>c</i>. 1928</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>100 (1910s)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Robert Perry and Sons, Rathdowney, County Laois (1831)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Acquired by Guinness 1957; closed 1966</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>80 (1935), 50 (1962), 40 (1966)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>E. Smithwick and Sons, St Francis Abbey Brewery, Kilkenny (1710)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Acquired by Irish Ale Breweries &#x0026; Guinness 1964</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>110 (1935), 200 (1960)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Strangman, Davis and Co., Waterford (1792)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Closed 1946; acquired and reopened by Guinness 1954</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>60 (1936)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Watkins, Jameson and Pim, Ardee Street, Dublin (1789)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Closed 1937</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>100 (1937)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-7" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0007">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-14"><title id="C3S7"><p><page id="49" chapter=""/>Distilling</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P34">Though Dublin had been &#x2018;the whiskey powerhouse of the world&#x2019; for much of the nineteenth century, output of Scotch had grown to double that of Irish whiskey by the early 1900s.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-28"><sup>28</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The sector contracted further with the imposition of First World War restrictions and Prohibition in America. By 1926, Free State area spirit production had declined to one-fifth of its 1912 level.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-29"><sup>29</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C3P35">The Scottish and Irish distillers had responded differently to the major innovation of the age&#x2014;the development of the &#x2018;patent&#x2019; or &#x2018;Coffey&#x2019; still (named for its inventor, Irishman Aeneas Coffey). The traditional pot still, whose use was largely retained in Ireland, produced pure malt whiskey from home-grown corn. The new type of still employed a different process to produce what was frequently referred to as &#x2018;silent spirit&#x2019;. This could be made from cheaper imported cereals and blended with a small proportion of traditional pot-still whiskey to provide flavour.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-30"><sup>30</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The new method was substantially more economical and produced more malleable blends.</p>
<p id="C3P36">The Irish industry also lost out to its Scottish competitor in the market for traditional pot still whiskey however.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-31"><sup>31</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Irish whiskey</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-displayText-2" class="other">
<p>was sold in barrels to publicans and merchants who bottled it, or more frequently blended it and sold it under their own label. [Many] bought whiskey blended by a merchant without any awareness of whether they were consumers of Power&#x2019;s, John Jameson or some other product. Ceding blending and bottling to outsiders also opened up possibilities for [mis-labelling] or dilution with inferior spirits.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-32"><sup>32</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C3P37">The structure of the Scottish industry was far more favourable to collective marketing and promotion. By 1922, the Distillers Company Ltd (DCL) owned all but one of the Scottish patent-still distilleries and had a close collaborative agreement with the remaining one, while also controlling most of the patent distilleries in England and Ireland.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-33"><sup>33</sup></xref></xrefGrp> This quasi-monopolistic structure facilitated development of the export trade.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-7"?></p>
<p id="C3P38"><page id="50" chapter=""/><xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-7">3.7</xref></xrefGrp> provides a list of distilleries in operation in the Free State area in 1920. Around half of these closed over the following decade, while those that remained open ceased production for large parts of the year.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-34"><sup>34</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C3P39"><page id="51" chapter=""/>Employment figures for the distilleries in the decade or so prior to 1922 suggest an aggregate workforce of around 1,500.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-35"><sup>35</sup></xref></xrefGrp> By 1926, the figure for distilling reported in the Census of Population stood at around 900, and that reported by the Census of Industrial Production at around 500, confirming the sharp contraction suggested by the data on spirit production.</p>
<p id="C3P40">Scotland&#x2019;s DCL closed its distilleries in Chapelizod and Dundalk in the early 1920s and all three of the companies that had merged to form the Dublin Distillers&#x2019; Company in 1889 ceased production over the course of the decade.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-36"><sup>36</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The George Roe distillery had been the largest in Dublin in the Victorian era. Its directors identified the lack of brand recognition as the source of its failure. The Dublin firms with stronger brand recognition, Jameson and Powers, survived.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-37"><sup>37</sup></xref></xrefGrp> There was a further contraction in employment between 1926 and 1929, at which point the industry appeared to be on the verge of extinction.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-28" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>28</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-16" class="book" author="Townsend, Brian" date="1997" title="The Lost Distilleries of Ireland" page="3" place="Glasgow" publisher="Neil Wilson Publishing" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Brian" mainName="Townsend" role="author">Brian Townsend</nameGrp>, <i>The Lost Distilleries of Ireland</i> (Glasgow: Neil Wilson Publishing, 1997), 3</bibItem>; <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-17" class="book" author="Bielenberg, Andy" date="2009" title="Ireland and the Industrial Revolution: The Impact of the Industrial Revolution on Irish Industry, 1801&#x2013;1922" page="97" place="London, New York" publisher="Routledge" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Andy" mainName="Bielenberg" role="author">Andy Bielenberg</nameGrp>, <i>Ireland and the Industrial Revolution: The Impact of the Industrial Revolution on Irish Industry, 1801&#x2013;1922</i> (London, New York: Routledge, 2009), 97</bibItem>; see Table 5.2.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-29" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>29</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-18" class="book" author="Bielenberg, Andy" date="2009" title="Ireland and the Industrial Revolution: The Impact of the Industrial Revolution on Irish Industry, 1801&#x2013;1922" page="97" place="London, New York" publisher="Routledge" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-17">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>, 97, Table 5.2.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-30" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>30</sup></enumerator> The Irish industry argued that use of the term &#x2018;whisky&#x2019; or &#x2018;whiskey&#x2019; should be restricted to the traditional product. A Royal Commission of 1909 determined otherwise: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-19" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Adams, Robin J. C." partTitle="The &#x201C;Made in Ireland&#x201D; Trademark and the Delineation of National Identity" editor="Higgins, David|Glover, Nikolas" date="2023" title="National Brands and Global Markets: An Historical Perspective" place="Abingdon" publisher="Routledge" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Robin J. C." mainName="Adams" role="partAuthor">Robin J. C. Adams</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The &#x201C;Made in Ireland&#x201D; Trademark and the Delineation of National Identity&#x2019;, in <i>National Brands and Global Markets: An Historical Perspective</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="David" mainName="Higgins" role="editor">David Higgins</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Nikolas" mainName="Glover" role="editor">Nikolas Glover</nameGrp> (Abingdon: Routledge, 2023): 46&#x2013;66.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-31" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>31</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-20" class="book" author="Gr&#x00E1;da, Cormac &#x00D3;" date="1994" title="Ireland: A New Economic History 1780&#x2013;1939" page="301" place="Oxford" publisher="Clarendon Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Cormac &#x00D3;" mainName="Gr&#x00e1;da" role="author">Cormac &#x00D3; Gr&#x00E1;da</nameGrp>, <i>Ireland: A New Economic History 1780&#x2013;1939</i> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1994), 301;</bibItem> Bielenberg, <i>Ireland and the Industrial Revolution</i>, 94.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-32" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>32</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-21" class="book" author="Daly, Mary E." date="1984" title="Dublin: The Deposed Capital, 1860&#x2013;1914" page="29" place="Cork" publisher="Cork University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Mary E." mainName="Daly" role="author">Mary E. Daly</nameGrp>, <i>Dublin: The Deposed Capital, 1860&#x2013;1914</i> (Cork: Cork University Press, 1984), 29.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-33" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>33</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-22" class="journalArticle" author="Weir, Ron B." date="1980" journalIssue="1" title="In and Out of Ireland: The Distillers Company Ltd. and the Irish Whiskey Trade 1900&#x2013;39" journalName="Irish Economic and Social History" vol="7" page="52" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Ron B." mainName="Weir" role="author">Ron B. Weir</nameGrp>, &#x2018;In and Out of Ireland: The Distillers Company Ltd. and the Irish Whiskey Trade 1900&#x2013;39&#x2019;. <i>Irish Economic and Social History</i> 7, 1 (1980): 52</bibItem>; <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-23" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Weir, Ron B." partTitle="The Patent Still Distillers and the Role of Competition" editor="Cullen, Louis M.|Smout, T. Christopher" date="1975" title="Comparative Aspects of Irish and Scottish Economic and Social Development, 1660&#x2013;1900" page="142" place="Edinburgh" publisher="John Donald" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Ron B." mainName="Weir" role="partAuthor">Ron B. Weir</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Patent Still Distillers and the Role of Competition&#x2019;, in <i>Comparative Aspects of Irish and Scottish Economic and Social Development, 1660&#x2013;1900</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Louis M." mainName="Cullen" role="editor">Louis M. Cullen</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="T. Christopher" mainName="Smout" role="editor">T. Christopher Smout</nameGrp> (Edinburgh: John Donald, 1975), 142.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-34" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>34</sup></enumerator> The same caveats as to the dates of establishment and decommissioning as discussed in the case of brewing apply. Dundalk distillery had been in operation as Malcolm Brown &#x0026; Co. since the early 1800s but was acquired by Scottish DCL in 1912. Similarly, the distillery at Marrowbone Lane in Dublin pre-dated its acquisition by John Jameson&#x2019;s nephew, William.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-35" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>35</sup></enumerator> Jameson, Powers, and each of the establishments operated by Cork Distilleries and Scotland&#x2019;s DCL employed in the region of 150 to 300 people. Tullamore and the ailing Dublin Distillers Company each employed around 100, and the more localized distilleries employed fewer than 50.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-36" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>36</sup></enumerator> On the closure of the DCL distilleries, see Weir, &#x2018;In and Out of Ireland: The Distillers Company Ltd. and the Irish Whiskey Trade&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-37" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>37</sup></enumerator> Townsend, <i>The Lost Distilleries of Ireland</i>, 95.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-7">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-7" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0007" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-7" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-15"><title id="C3T7"><p><enumerator>Table 3.7</enumerator> Free State area distilleries in operation in 1920</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Distiller</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Distillery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Distillery developments to <i>c</i>. 1972</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>John Jameson (1810)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Bow Street Distillery, Dublin (1780)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Closed 1971; production transferred to Powers and later to Midleton</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>John Power</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>John&#x2019;s Lane, Dublin (1791)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Closed 1974; production transferred to Midleton</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Dublin Distillers (1889)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>George Roe, Thomas Street (1757)</p>
<p>William Jameson, Marrowbone Lane (1752)</p>
<p>Dublin Whisky Distillery, Jones&#x2019; Road (1872)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>George Roe and William Jameson closed in 1923, Jones&#x2019;s Road in 1926</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Cork Distilleries<sup>*</sup> (1867)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Murphy&#x2019;s, Midleton (1825)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Production transferred to new Irish Distillers complex 1975</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Wise&#x2019;s, North Mall, Cork City (1779)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Closed 1920</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Distillers Company Ltd (DCL)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Phoenix Park, Dublin (1878)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Closed early 1920s</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Dundalk, County Louth (pre-1800)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Cassidy&#x2019;s</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Monasterevin, County Kildare (1784)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Closed 1921</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>B. Daly/D. E. Williams</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Tullamore, County Offaly (1829)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Closed 1954</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>John Locke</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Kilbeggan, County Westmeath (1757)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Closed 1953; reopened in the 1990s</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Allman &#x0026; Co.</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Bandon, County Cork (1825)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Closed 1930s</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Glen Distillery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Kilnap, County Cork (1882)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Closed 1920s</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Note</i>: <sup>*</sup>CDC&#x2019;s Watercourse distillery was dormant in the 1920s but operated intermittently since then.</p>
<p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-8" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0008">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-16"><title id="C3S8"><p>Aerated Waters</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P41">There were two significant producers of soft drinks or &#x2018;aerated waters&#x2019; in Dublin in the early twentieth century, with &#x2018;smaller ones to be found in nearly every fair-sized town throughout the country&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-38"><sup>38</sup></xref></xrefGrp> A. &#x0026; R. Thwaite, founded by a father-and-son team of apothecaries, had been producing soda water in Dublin since the late 1700s. Belfast firm Cantrell &#x0026; Cochrane&#x2019;s Dublin factory was larger than Thwaite&#x2019;s, though it employed no more than a couple of hundred in 1929. It had been opened on Nassau Place at the rear of the Cochrane family townhouse on Kildare Street in 1868, where it would remain for the next 100 years.</p>
<p id="C3P42">The early success of Cantrell &#x0026; Cochrane&#x2019;s ginger ale owed much to the temperance movement. It was described in advertisements as</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-displayText-3" class="other">
<p>sparkling like champagne, agreeable to the taste as that much lauded and very costly wine, but not leaving [repentance] and self-reproach as a heritage of the morrow.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-39"><sup>39</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C3P43"><page id="52" chapter=""/>Paradoxically, having concentrated its efforts on the export market, the company suffered a decline in sales when Prohibition led to the emergence of a large number of US competitors. From 1927, Thwaites, Cantrell &#x0026; Cochrane and E. &#x0026; J. Burke were linked through a complicated pattern of cross-ownership, which was reflected in the formation of a new company, Mineral Water Distributors. From the initial letters of the new company would emerge the soft drinks brand <i>MiWadi</i>.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-38" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>38</sup></enumerator> Riordan, <i>Modern Irish Trade and Industry</i>, 164. Thirty-one of the soft-drinks producers from beyond Dublin are listed in an <i>Irish Times</i> article of 10 September 1928.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-39" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>39</sup></enumerator> Cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-24" class="book" author="Greer, Desmond S.|Nicolson, James W." date="2003" title="The Factory Acts in Ireland, 1802&#x2013;1914" vol="12" page="272" place="Dublin" publisher="Four Courts Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Desmond S." mainName="Greer" role="author">Desmond S. Greer</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="James W." mainName="Nicolson" role="author">James W. Nicolson</nameGrp>, <i>The Factory Acts in Ireland, 1802&#x2013;1914</i>, Vol. 12 (Dublin: Four Courts Press, 2003), 272.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-9" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0009">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-17"><title id="C3S9"><p>Tobacco</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P44">Irish and British tobacco consumption were on a par in the early twentieth century, though pipe tobacco retained a stronger hold in Ireland. Prior to the establishment of a customs frontier in 1923, cigarette sales were dominated by imports. The market leader, as in Britain, was Bristol firm W. D. &#x0026; H. O. Wills, whose 40 per cent share was largely accounted for by the low-priced and unfiltered Woodbine.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-40"><sup>40</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-8"?></p>
<p id="C3P45">The largest indigenous Free State area manufacturers were P. J. Carroll of Dundalk and T. P. &#x0026; R. Goodbody of Dublin (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-8">3.8</xref></xrefGrp>). Goodbody had relocated to a site off the South Circular Road when its factory in Tullamore was destroyed by fire in the 1880s. Carrolls moved to a modern, purpose-built factory in 1912 when its original premises too were destroyed by fire. Half of its output in 1923 was sold in Britain and Northern Ireland.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-41"><sup>41</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Its dispatch of 30,000 Silk Cut cigarettes to soldiers fighting at the front in the opening phases of the First World War had elicited repeat orders numbering in the millions, and its &#x2018;Sweet Afton&#x2019; brand, introduced in 1919, proved hugely popular in Scotland. It capitalized on the Dundalk connection with <page id="53" chapter=""/>Robert Burns, whose sister had lived in the town and was buried near the factory gates.</p>
<p id="C3P46">There were only 500 employed in tobacco manufacturing in the Free State prior to the erection of the customs frontier.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-42"><sup>42</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The structure of the industry changed considerably thereafter. Goodbodys would exit in 1929, and Carrolls would expand substantially over the following decades. Dublin, Cork, and Limerick also each hosted a number of smaller tobacco manufacturers.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-40" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>40</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-25" class="journalArticle" author="Bielenberg, Andy|Johnson, David" date="1998" journalIssue="1" title="The Production and Consumption of Tobacco in Ireland, 1800&#x2013;1914" journalName="Irish Economic and Social History" vol="25" page="1" pageLast="21" place="Riordan" publisher="Modern Irish Trade and Industry" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Andy" mainName="Bielenberg" role="author">Andy Bielenberg</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="David" mainName="Johnson" role="author">David Johnson</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Production and Consumption of Tobacco in Ireland, 1800&#x2013;1914&#x2019;. <i>Irish Economic and Social History</i> 25, 1 (1998): 1&#x2013;21; Riordan, <i>Modern Irish Trade and Industry</i>, 183.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-41" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>41</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 3 March 1923.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-42" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>42</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-26" class="book" date="1932" title="Saorst&#x00E1;t &#x00C9;ireann: Irish Free State Official Handbook" page="142" place="Dublin" publisher="Talbot Press" purpose="display"><i>Saorst&#x00E1;t &#x00C9;ireann: Irish Free State Official Handbook</i> (Dublin: Talbot Press, 1932), 142.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-8">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-8" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0008" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-8" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-18"><title id="C3T8"><p><enumerator>Table 3.8</enumerator> Largest tobacco manufacturers in the Free State in 1922</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Firm</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Location and period in operation</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Employment</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>P. J. Carroll</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Dundalk (1824&#x2013;2008)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>150 (1907), 400 (1934), &#x2265;500 (from 1953)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>T. P. &#x0026; R. Goodbody</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Dublin (1886&#x2013;1929)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>320 (1908), 200 (1929)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div1-3" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.021.0003">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-19"><title id="C3S10"><p><enumerator>3.2</enumerator> Textiles, Clothing, Footwear, and Leather</p></title></titleGroup>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-10" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0010" role="prelim">
<p id="C3P47">A form of branding of relevance to textiles and clothing was the use of the Irish national trade mark <i>D&#x00E9;anta i n&#x00C9;irinn</i>. In response to the growing manifestation of nationalist sentiment (particularly the &#x2018;Buy Irish&#x2019; campaign initiated by the &#x2018;Irish Ireland&#x2019; newspaper <i>The Leader</i>), some British manufacturers had begun to use Irish place names and terms such as Hibernian, Harp, Shamrock, and Gaelic in their branding. The passage of the Merchandise Marks Act of 1887 had made it a criminal offence to apply misleading descriptions as to where goods had been produced. The Irish national trade mark became legally enforceable in 1907 and by 1920 some 450 firms, mostly in the Free State area, had been licensed to use it.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-43"><sup>43</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Many of the legal actions taken or warnings issued in response to transgressions pertained to textiles and clothing (and also to flour).<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-44"><sup>44</sup></xref></xrefGrp> <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-9">3.9</xref></xrefGrp> shows the composition of the textiles, clothing, and footwear sector in 1926.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-43" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>43</sup></enumerator> Adams, &#x2018;The &#x201C;Made in Ireland&#x201D; Trademark and the Delineation of National Identity&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-44" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>44</sup></enumerator> Riordan, <i>Modern Irish Trade and Industry</i>, Appendix VI.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-11" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0011">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-20"><title id="C3S11"><p>Non-woollen Textiles</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P48">Limerick had been well-known for its lace in the past, as Dublin had been for its poplin, but both industries were on the verge of extinction by 1922.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-45"><sup>45</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Linen went into decline with the change in tastes and fashions of the First World War era, but production had been sustained over the war&#x00A0;years by the demand for aeroplane cloth. Cork Spinning &#x0026; Weaving closed in 1928. Greenmount Weaving of Harold&#x2019;s Cross in Dublin closed in 1922, though it reopened shortly afterwards upon being acquired by Boyne Weaving of <page id="54" chapter=""/>Drogheda. The merged firm, Greenmount &#x0026; Boyne, would remain for many decades one of the leading manufacturers in the state. It remained primarily export-oriented in the 1920s. From the 1940s, it would begin to diversify into rayon and cotton.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-9"?></p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-10"?></p>
<p id="C3P49">Jute had become a popular sacking material when hemp supplies from Russia were disrupted by the Crimean War and cotton supplies from the southern United States were cut off by the American civil war of the following decade. The Clara factory of J. &#x0026; L. F. Goodbody was one of the earliest jute plants in Europe outside the vast Dundee cluster. Established in 1865, it remained strongly export-oriented until well into the Free State era. It would remain a substantial employer through to 1972 (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-10">3.10</xref></xrefGrp>). By the time of EEC accession it had largely transitioned into polypropylene.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-46"><sup>46</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-45" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>45</sup></enumerator> The only substantial factory-style lace operation, which was located in Limerick department store Cannocks, closed in the 1920s. The main surviving Dublin poplin maker was the 100-year-old Richard Atkinson &#x0026; Co.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-46" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>46</sup></enumerator> Though the implied size of these major non-woollen textiles firms alone exceeds the figure for total employment reported in the Census of Industrial Production, not all of their activities would necessarily have been allocated to the sector. The census notes for example that the cooperage departments of large breweries were included under timber rather than brewing.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-9">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-9" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0009" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-9" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-21"><title id="C3T9"><p><enumerator>Table 3.9</enumerator> Free State CIP, 1926: Textiles, clothing, and footwear</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Sector</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Employment, 1926: CIP, table 1</p>
<p>(excluding out-workers)</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Linen, cotton, hemp, jute, and canvas</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,658</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Woollen and worsted (including blanket making)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>2,332</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Clothing</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>4,001</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Boots and shoes</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>967</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Hosiery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>849</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-10" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0010" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-10" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-22"><title id="C3T10"><p><enumerator>Table 3.10</enumerator> Leading firms in non-woollen textiles</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Company name and location</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Employment</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Cork Spinning &#x0026; Weaving (1889), Cork</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,000 (1919); closed 1928</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Greenmount Weaving (1808), Harold&#x2019;s Cross, Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>550 (1922); merges into Greenmount &#x0026; Boyne</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Boyne Weaving (1865), Drogheda</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>900 (1910), 600 (1923); merges into Greenmount &#x0026; Boyne</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Greenmount &#x0026; Boyne (1925), Dublin and Drogheda</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>590 (1929), 800 (1936), 800 (1960), 200 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>J. &#x0026; L. F. Goodbody (1865), Clara, County Offaly (and Waterford from the 1930s)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>700 (1912), 800 (1920), remains &#x003E;500 (up to 1972)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-12" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0012">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-23"><title id="C3S12"><p><page id="55" chapter=""/>Woollen and Worsted Textiles</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P50">By the late 1800s, Cork had emerged as the centre of the mechanized woollen industry in Ireland.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-47"><sup>47</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Proximity to the port was of importance as Irish wool is too coarse for the production of finer cloths. The area&#x2019;s main advantage according to Bielenberg however was the lead set by Martin Mahony &#x0026; Brothers, whose technical and organizational innovations were copied by other local producers.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-48"><sup>48</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The family had been involved in the woollen industry since 1750 but the reputation of the firm dated largely from the opening of the Blarney Woollen Mills in 1824. It would remain the largest enterprise in the sector throughout the period to 1972 (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-11">3.11</xref></xrefGrp>).</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-11"?></p>
<p id="C3P51">The other major Cork mills were in nearby Douglas. The O&#x2019;Brien Brothers&#x2019; woollen mills, St Patrick&#x2019;s, dated from 1882. The Morrogh Brothers&#x2019; Mills were established several&#x00A0;years later with money made from the South African mining industry, where John Morrogh had been a director of De Beers. Other significant manufacturers included the Athlone Woollen Mills, F. &#x0026; J. Clayton of Navan, Convoy in Donegal, the Providence Mills at Foxford in Mayo, Mulcahy, Redmond &#x0026; Co. in Ardfinnan, County Tipperary, and Hill &#x0026; Sons of Lucan. The Athlone Mills, the oldest of the group, had been set up in 1858 by an English-based Irish doctor at the prompting of his Lancashire industrialist brother-in-law. Providence, the most recent, had been established in 1892 by Sister Agnes Morrogh-Bernard of the Sisters of Charity to provide employment for the impoverished local population. Most of the woollen mills were in Catholic ownership. Hill &#x0026; Sons was a Quaker enterprise.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-49"><sup>49</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Other than Blarney, even the largest of the others generally employed a maximum of 200&#x2013;300 workers.</p>
<p id="C3P52"><page id="56" chapter=""/>The woollen and worsted sector had &#x2018;expanded at an unprecedented rate during the course of the 1914&#x2013;18 War&#x2019; but lost considerable ground thereafter.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-50"><sup>50</sup></xref></xrefGrp> From the 1920s, it would be protected by tariffs. The Navan and Athlone Mills closed in the 1960s, Morrogh in 1971, Ardfinnan in 1973. Convoy, Providence and Hill &#x0026; Sons remained in operation beyond EEC accession, as did Blarney and St Patrick&#x2019;s.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-47" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>47</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-27" class="book" author="Bielenberg, Andy" date="1991" title="Cork&#x2019;s Industrial Revolution 1780&#x2013;1880" place="Cork" publisher="Cork University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Andy" mainName="Bielenberg" role="author">Andy Bielenberg</nameGrp>, <i>Cork&#x2019;s Industrial Revolution 1780&#x2013;1880</i> (Cork: Cork University Press, 1991), 31, 39</bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-48" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>48</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-28" class="book" author="Bielenberg, Andy" date="1991" title="Cork&#x2019;s Industrial Revolution 1780&#x2013;1880" place="Cork" publisher="Cork University Press" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-27">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 40.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-49" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>49</sup></enumerator> The small Kilkenny Woollen Mill was established by the Countess of Desart and her brother-in-law in 1903. Lady Desart, upon her appointment to the senate in 1922, would be the first person of Jewish faith to serve in the parliament of the new state. The Kilkenny mill would be acquired in the 1920s by Business Party TD Andrew O&#x2019;Shaughnessy, whose family also owned the Dripsey and Sallybrook Mills in County Cork.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-50" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>50</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-29" class="book" author="Committee on Industrial Organisation" date="1965" title="Report on Survey of the Woollen and Worsted Industry" page="44" place="Dublin" publisher="Stationery Office" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Committee on Industrial Organisation">Committee on Industrial Organisation</nameGrp>, <i>Report on Survey of the Woollen and Worsted Industry</i> (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1965), 44.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-10">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-11" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0011" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-11" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-24"><title id="C3T11"><p><enumerator>Table 3.11</enumerator> Leading firm in woollens and worsteds: Blarney Woollen Mills</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Firm, date of establishment, location</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Employment</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Blarney Woollen Mills (1824)/Martin Mahony &#x0026; Brothers (1750)<b>,</b> Blarney</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>750 (1892), 600 (1919), &#x003E; 500 (up to 1972)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-13" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0013">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-25"><title id="C3S13"><p>Clothing, Hosiery, and Knitwear</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P53">The clothing sector, though sizeable, consisted for the most part of relatively small establishments. One of the few large employers was the Cork City firm Dwyer and Co. (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-12">3.12</xref></xrefGrp>). Established as a drapery and general-purpose wholesaler in the 1820s, by 1918 it was producing a broad range of clothing and footwear and had a workforce of 700, 70 of whom were employed in the firm&#x2019;s boot factory. Members of the extended Dwyer family would go on to establish Sunbeam and Seafield, two of the largest textiles companies of the protectionist era. The original Dwyer business traded largely under the Lee brand: by the 1960s, manufacturing accounted for only a small share of its activities.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-12"?></p>
<p id="C3P54">The Limerick Clothing Factory had a particularly rich history. Founded by Scottish immigrant Peter Tait in 1850, it employed the recently invented mechanical sewing machine to produce ready-made clothing, particularly military uniforms, and was for a time the largest such concern in the world. It employed close to 2,000 at its peak in the nineteenth century. Tait went bankrupt when a consignment of Alabama cotton bartered for Confederate <page id="57" chapter=""/>army uniforms was seized by Union forces during the American civil war and the company was bought out by a conglomerate of Limerick businessmen. Employment stood at 600 in 1919 but declined to below 500 by 1929 at the latest. It would be acquired by UK company Aquascutum in 1969 and closed in 1974.</p>
<p id="C3P55">The largest and most famous hosiery firm in 1922 was Smyth &#x0026; Co. of Balbriggan, which dated from 1768. Many of its employees up to the 1950s were out-workers. The Oxford English Dictionary records that &#x2018;Balbriggan&#x2019; came to be used in the late nineteenth century as a term for a knitted cotton fabric, used for stockings and underwear, &#x2018;named after the town of Balbriggan in Ireland where it was originally made&#x2019;. The company survived until 1980. The Templecrone Co-operative Society in Donegal reduced its reliance on outworkers with the opening of its &#x2018;machine knitting factory&#x2019; in Dungloe in 1919. <xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-51"><sup>51</sup></xref></xrefGrp> This factory too remained in operation into the EEC era.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-51" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>51</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Independent</i>, 31 October 1919.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-11">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-12" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0012" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-12" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-26"><title id="C3T12"><p><enumerator>Table 3.12</enumerator> Leading firms in clothing, hosiery, and knitwear</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Employment</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Dwyer &#x0026; Co.</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Cork</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>700 (1918), 800 (1939). Excluding footwear: 310 (1960), 450 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Limerick Clothing Factory</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Limerick</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>800 (1899), 400 (1911), 600 (1919), 320 (1936), 350 (1962), 270 (1968)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Smyth &#x0026; Co.</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Balbriggan, County Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Including out-workers: 460 (1898), 450 (1929), 470 (1936). Factory hands: 250 (1962)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-14" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0014">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-27"><title id="C3S14"><p>Department Stores</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P56">Though not included in the Census of Industrial Production, the department stores of the period were significant producers of clothing, furniture, and furnishings. The emergence of the &#x2018;monster houses&#x2019; in the mid-1800s had been vigorously opposed by smaller traders who argued that their importation of &#x2018;slop productions&#x2019; from Britain was ruining entire classes of Irish tradespeople.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-52"><sup>52</sup></xref></xrefGrp> By the turn of the century, in-house production of a range of the items sold on their premises had become standard.</p>
<p id="C3P57">There were seven major department stores in Dublin at the foundation of the state as well as several in Cork, Limerick, and Waterford.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-53"><sup>53</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Ownership of many passed through the hands of the same group of businesspeople. These included Limerickman Michael J. Clery and Scottish expatriates John Arnott, George Cannock, and William Todd. By the 1930s, Pim Brothers had been surpassed in size by several of the other Dublin stores. <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-13">3.13</xref></xrefGrp> tracks the evolution of employment in the major Dublin stores up to the 1930s and 1940s, beyond which their relative significance as manufacturers declined.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-13"?></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-52" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>52</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-30" class="journalArticle" author="Rains, Stephanie" date="2008" journalIssue="4" title="Here Be Monsters: The Irish Industrial Exhibition of 1853 and the Growth of Dublin Department Stores" journalName="Irish Studies Review" vol="16" page="493" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Stephanie" mainName="Rains" role="author">Stephanie Rains</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Here Be Monsters: The Irish Industrial Exhibition of 1853 and the Growth of Dublin Department Stores&#x2019;. <i>Irish Studies Review</i> 16, 4 (2008): 493.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-53" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>53</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-31" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Barry, Frank" partTitle="The Life and Death of Protestant Businesses in Independent Ireland" editor="d&#x2019;Alton, Ian|Milne, Ida" date="2019" title="Protestant and Irish: The Minority&#x2019;s Accommodation with Independent Ireland" page="155" pageLast="170" place="Cork" publisher="Cork University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="partAuthor">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Life and Death of Protestant Businesses in Independent Ireland&#x2019;, in <i>Protestant and Irish: The Minority&#x2019;s Accommodation with Independent Ireland</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Ian" mainName="D&#x2019;alton" role="editor">Ian d&#x2019;Alton</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Ida" mainName="Milne" role="editor">Ida Milne</nameGrp> (Cork: Cork University Press, 2019), 155&#x2013;70.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-12">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-13" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0013" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-13" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-28"><title id="C3T13"><p><enumerator>Table 3.13</enumerator> Selected Dublin department stores in operation in 1922</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Department store</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Employment, selected years</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Todd, Burns &#x0026; Co., Mary Street</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>400&#x2013;500 (1905), 620 (1935), 725 (1941)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Clery&#x2019;s, O&#x2019;Connell Street</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>600 (1941)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Arnott&#x2019;s, Henry Street</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>200 (<i>c</i>. 1900), 400&#x2013;450 (1918), 500 (1931)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Switzers, Grafton Street</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>250 (<i>c</i>. 1900), 425 (1935), 300&#x2013;400 (1947)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Pim Brothers, South Great George&#x2019;s Street</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>600 (1894), 300 (1934)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-15" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0015">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-29"><title id="C3S15"><p><page id="58" chapter=""/>Footwear and Leather</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P58">By the late 1880s, more than 80 per cent of the footwear sold in Ireland was imported, and the Irish sector was largely specialized in the less-skilled agricultural boot segment.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-54"><sup>54</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The five footwear firms in operation in 1924 supplied only 6 per cent of the state&#x2019;s requirements, and most of the 359 workers in the industry were employed on a part-time basis.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-55"><sup>55</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Leather production too was moribund. Riordan estimated that there were only around 500 employed across all of the twelve tanneries in operation in 1920, of which the largest by far was O&#x2019;Callaghan&#x2019;s City Tannery in Limerick.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-56"><sup>56</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Its workforce over the entire period up to its demise in 1967 did not rise much above the 160 employed there during the First World War.</p>
<p id="C3P59">The oldest of the footwear firms still in operation in 1922 was James Winstanley of Dublin, which dated from 1852. Though Hilliard &#x0026; Sons of Killarney and Lee Boot of Cork would both expand with the introduction of protection, neither would attain the scale of the UK firms that entered as a consequence of the tariffs. Hilliard would team up with a British partner to become Hilliard &#x0026; Palmer in 1936 and would become a subsidiary of UK firm G. B. Britton in 1965. Lee Boot was a Dwyer family company. Its survival, Bielenberg notes, was due to its ability to update the plant periodically and to keep abreast of technological and organizational changes in England, which may have been a result of the resources available to it from within the Dwyer group.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-57"><sup>57</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-54" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>54</sup></enumerator> Bielenberg, <i>Cork&#x2019;s Industrial Revolution 1780&#x2013;1880</i>, 83.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-55" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>55</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-32" class="book" author="Commission, Tariff" date="1931" title="Report on the Application for a Tariff on Leather" page="22" place="Dublin" publisher="Stationery Office" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Tariff" mainName="Commission" role="author">Tariff Commission</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Report on the Application for a Tariff on Leather&#x2019;. Report no. 11 (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1931), 22;</bibItem> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-33" class="journalArticle" author="Dwyer, D. J." date="1961" journalIssue="3" title="The Leather Industries of the Irish Republic, 1922&#x2013;55: A Study in Industrial Development and Location" journalName="Irish Geography" vol="4" page="175" pageLast="189" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="D. J." mainName="Dwyer" role="author">D. J. Dwyer</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Leather Industries of the Irish Republic, 1922&#x2013;55: A Study in Industrial Development and Location&#x2019;. <i>Irish Geography</i> 4, 3 (1961): 175&#x2013;89.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-56" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>56</sup></enumerator> Riordan, <i>Modern Irish Trade and Industry</i>, 178.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-57" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>57</sup></enumerator> Bielenberg, <i>Cork&#x2019;s Industrial Revolution 1780&#x2013;1880</i>, 84.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div1-4" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.021.0004">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-30"><title id="C3S16"><p><page id="59" chapter=""/><enumerator>3.3</enumerator> Other Manufacturing Industries</p></title></titleGroup>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-16" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0016" role="prelim">
<p id="C3P60">Sectors other than the ones surveyed above made up the remaining one-third of manufacturing employment in 1926. They are grouped here into broader categories than those employed in the Census of Industrial Production. Certain industrial segments were included in a separate &#x2018;miscellaneous&#x2019; category in order to maintain the confidentiality of the firm-level data submitted to the census authorities. In the 1926 Census of Industrial Production, these included poplin, leather, brush making, ship and boat building, tobacco pipes, and roofing felt.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-58"><sup>58</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-58" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>58</sup></enumerator> The major brush maker was I. S. Varian &#x0026; Co., which dated from 1798. The most significant producer of tobacco pipes was Kapp &#x0026; Peterson, which was established in the mid-1890s. The leading firms in the other miscellaneous segments are mentioned elsewhere in the text.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-17" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0017">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-31"><title id="C3S17"><p>Metals and Engineering</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P61">The metals and engineering sector of the 1920s consisted of agricultural machinery and transport equipment fabrication and the diverse activities of the numerous general foundries then still in existence. Transport companies were treated separately in the census so the many thousands employed in the railway engineering yards where many of the state&#x2019;s mechanical craft workers served their apprenticeships are not included in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-14">3.14</xref></xrefGrp>. The largest of the railyards were the Inchicore and Dundalk engineering works of the Great Southern &#x0026; Western and Great Northern railway companies (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-15">3.15</xref></xrefGrp>).</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-14"?></p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-15"?></p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-16"?></p>
<p id="C3P62">Most of the Dublin engineering work would transfer to Inchicore with the railway amalgamations of the mid-1920s and the formation of Great Southern Rail (GSR). Latterly part of the state transport company CI&#x00C9;, these works would remain a major employer through to 1972 and beyond. The liquidation of the Great Northern in the mid-1950s would put the livelihoods of the more than 1,000 then employed in Dundalk at risk. The Industrial Engineering Company would be established by the state to provide employment for the displaced workers. Its fortunes are discussed in a later chapter.</p>
<p id="C3P63">The other rail yards in operation in 1922 were at Broadstone, headquarters of the Midland Great Western, and the much smaller ones at Grand Canal Street, close to the Westland Row terminus of the Dublin &#x0026; South Eastern Railway Company. Some rail work continued at Broadstone until it was decommissioned as a terminus in the 1930s. Most of the bus fabrication work then being conducted at the site transferred to the bus and tram facility of the Dublin United Transport Company (DUTC) when the latter merged with the <page id="60" chapter=""/>Great Southern to form CI&#x00C9; in 1945. Some 300&#x2013;400 people were employed at the former DUTC facility in Inchicore up to 1972. The Grand Canal Street railyards, where the first locomotive engine manufactured in Ireland had been built, closed in 1925.</p>
<p alignment="centre"></p>
<p id="C3P64">Shipbuilding and ship repair went into sharp decline in the&#x00A0;years following the end of the First World War. The British Admiralty shipyards at <page id="61" chapter=""/>Haulbowline had employed 3,000 in 1917, and 1,000 were still on the books when it was announced in 1921 that they were to close. By the end of the decade, only a skeleton staff remained. The nearby shipyards at Rushbrooke and Passage West suffered collateral damage from the reduction in naval traffic. Owned at the time by UK company Furness &#x0026; Withy, they closed in 1930. Rushbrooke would be reopened in 1941 and would be taken over by the Dutch company Verolme in 1959.</p>
<p id="C3P65">The Dublin Dockyard Company also employed around 1,000 in the&#x00A0;years immediately prior to its closure in the early 1920s. The dockyard was reopened by UK company Vickers in 1924 but remained paralysed by industrial conflict throughout the 1920s. Its ownership changed several times over subsequent decades, with employment fluctuating between 250 and 600 depending on the state of the order book (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-16">3.16</xref></xrefGrp>).</p>
<p alignment="centre"></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C3P66">Struck by the poverty of the country during a brief visit in 1912, American industrialist Henry Ford had resolved to build a tractor plant in Cork&#x2014;the county of his father&#x2019;s birth&#x2014;as a contribution to Ireland&#x2019;s industrial development. Production of cars and trucks would be most efficiently located close to major clusters of consumer demand; for tractors, for which the market was dispersed, a peripheral location would be less disadvantageous. Construction of the &#x2018;Fordson&#x2019; tractor plant commenced in 1917. The project began as a private family venture but would be integrated into the Ford Motor Company in the early 1920s. At its peak later in the decade, it would be by far the largest manufacturing employer in the state.</p>
<p id="C3P67">The tractor market collapsed with the international agricultural depression of the early 1920s however and the Cork foundry was put to use producing car parts for the Ford assembly plant in Manchester. Plans to build an integrated <page id="62" chapter=""/>production facility in Britain would come to fruition with the opening of the Dagenham plant in 1931. The Cork factory would be repurposed several&#x00A0;years later to assemble primarily for the protected local market. It would remain a significant employer until its closure in 1984.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-59"><sup>59</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p alignment="centre"></p>
<p id="C3P68">Ireland&#x2019;s general foundries had become increasingly vulnerable to specialist machinery imports from Britain over the course of the nineteenth century. Those that survived, apart from Philip Pierce &#x0026; Co. in Wexford, tended to concentrate on &#x2018;less sophisticated iron and wrought-iron goods like manhole covers, gates, street lamps, bollards, pumps, railings and other street furniture&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-60"><sup>60</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Though most had passed their peak by the time of independence, their legacy remains apparent on the urban streetscapes of today. The Drogheda Iron Works had, in its time, built ships, bridges, barges, and steam locomotives as well as the diving bell that now stands as a remnant of industrial archaeology on the south bank of the Liffey in Dublin. Established by Thomas Grendon in 1835, it survived until 1970. The Dundalk Iron Works, which dated from 1788, would be liquidated in 1928. The Hive Iron Works and Merrick Engineering in Cork also survived in a much diminished state into the Free State era. The former closed in the 1930s; the latter struggled on into the 1960s. Two of the three surviving Limerick foundries closed in the 1920s. The Shannon Foundry survived beyond 1972.</p>
<p id="C3P69">From its establishment in the mid-1800s, Pierce &#x0026; Co. of Wexford had developed a significant reputation as a producer of agricultural machinery. It was also in the 1920s one of only a handful of bicycle manufacturers in the state.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-61"><sup>61</sup></xref></xrefGrp> It remained in operation until 1980. Wexford town, which benefited from good transport links and proximity to the crop-growing regions of the country, hosted three foundries in total. The Selskar Ironworks closed in the 1930s. The Wexford Engineering Company would be converted in the 1960s into an assembly plant for Renault cars.</p>
<p id="C3P70">Dublin&#x2019;s size afforded the best opportunities for survival, though four foundries had disappeared from the vicinity of Hammond Lane within living memory when the foundry of that name was revived by Scotsman David Frame in 1902. Hammond Holdings would become a major industrial group, <page id="63" chapter=""/>and Frame would go on to establish Irish Steel. The foundry itself, which moved in 1911 to Great Brunswick Street/Pearse Street, employed a similar workforce to the Smith &#x0026; Pearson ironworks in East Wall. The foundry of former shipbuilders Ross &#x0026; Walpole of North Wall closed in the 1920s; William Spence &#x0026; Son of Cork St. closed in 1930; Sharkeys of Church Street closed in the 1940s. Art metalworkers J. &#x0026; C. McGloughlin would merge with Tonge &#x0026; Taggart to form the TMG Group in 1954. Other than the diversified Hammond Lane Group, the foundry companies only rarely employed a workforce of 500 or more (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-17">3.17</xref></xrefGrp>).</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-17"?></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-59" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>59</sup></enumerator> Much of the material on Ford comes from <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-34" class="unclassified" author="Grimes, Thomas" date="2008" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Thomas" mainName="Grimes" role="author">Thomas Grimes</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Starting Ireland on the Road to Industry: Henry Ford in Cork&#x2019;. Unpublished Ph.D. thesis, National University of Ireland, Maynooth, 2008.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-60" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>60</sup></enumerator> Bielenberg, <i>Cork&#x2019;s Industrial Revolution 1780&#x2013;1880</i>, 113.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-61" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>61</sup></enumerator> The Fiscal Inquiry Committee of 1923 reported that 100 of its 350 workers of the time were engaged in the manufacture of bicycles: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-35" class="book" author="Fiscal Inquiry Committee" date="1923" title="Final Report" page="21" place="Dublin" publisher="Stationery Office" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Fiscal Inquiry Committee">Fiscal Inquiry Committee</nameGrp>, Final Report (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1923), 21.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-13">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-14" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0014" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-14" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-32"><title id="C3T14"><p><enumerator>Table 3.14</enumerator> Free State CIP, 1926: Other manufacturing industries</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Sector</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Employment, 1926: Irish Free State CIP, table 1</p>
<p>(excluding out-workers)</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Metals and engineering</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Coach, wagon, and motor body building and construction of motor vehicles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,447</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Metals (excluding engineering)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,276</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Engineering and implements</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,081</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Other</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Bricks, glass, and monumental masonry</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>782</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Timber</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>2,776</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Wood furniture and upholstery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,555</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Paper making and manufactured stationery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>611</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Printing, publishing, bookbinding, and engraving</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>5,128</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Soap and candles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>410</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Fertilizers, chemicals, drugs, and paints</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,102</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Miscellaneous industries</p>
<p>(sugar, polishes, brush making, ship and boat building, poplin, leather, vegetable oils, smoking pipes, roofing felt, other miscellaneous)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>3,065</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: CIP.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-15" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0015" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-15" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-33"><title id="C3T15"><p><enumerator>Table 3.15</enumerator> Railway engineering works</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Facility</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Company</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Employment (year)</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Inchicore Railway Works, Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Great Southern &#x0026; Western/Great Southern Railways/CI&#x00C9;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>1,600 (1917), 1,500 (1922), 1,400 (1954), 1,420 (1964), 2,000 (1975)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Dundalk Rail Yards</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Great Northern Rail</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>1,000 (1914), 800 (1925), 700 (1934), 1,100 (1956)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Broadstone</p>
<p>Rail Yards, Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Midland Great Western</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>600 (1917)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Note</i>: Not included under manufacturing in the CIP for 1926.</p>
<p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-16" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0016" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-16" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-34"><title id="C3T16"><p><enumerator>Table 3.16</enumerator> Ship and boat building and repair</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Facility</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Location</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Employment</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>British Admiralty Yard, Haulbowline</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Cork</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>3,000 (1917), 1,000 (1921), 89 (1928)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Rushbrooke</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Cork</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>800 (1917), 600 (1923), 400 (1946), 200 (1955), Verolme from 1959</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Dublin Dockyard Company/Liffey Dockyard</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>450&#x2013;500 (1912), 750&#x2013;1,000 (1920), 300 (1930), 550 (1936), 500 (1943), 450 (1952), 600 (1960), 250 (1968)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-17" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0017" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-17" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-35"><title id="C3T17"><p><enumerator>Table 3.17</enumerator> Metals and engineering other than rail, ships, and boats</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Ford, Cork city (1919)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,429 (1920), 1,800 (1923), major employer through to 1972</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Philip Pierce &#x0026; Co., Wexford (1839)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>450 (1914), 350 (1923), 220 (1926), 500 (1941), 450 (1960), 260 (1969), 200 (1974)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Hammond Lane Foundry, Dublin (1902)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Foundry only: 150 (1913), 200 (1947), 230 (1962), 160 (1971), Hammond Holdings &#x003E;500 (from 1930s)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Newcomen Ironworks (Smith &#x0026; Pearson), Dublin (1901)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>200 (1922), 300 (1939), 370 (1960), 420 (1966)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-18" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0018">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-36"><title id="C3S18"><p>Building Materials, Glass, and Furniture</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P71">Builders&#x2019; providers are not tracked closely through to the 1970s as only a segment of their activities fall within the definition of manufacturing. The major enterprises in the sector at independence included Dublin firms Brooks Thomas, Dockrells, and T. &#x0026; C. Martin; Francis Spaight and James McMahon of Limerick; Robert McCowen of Tralee; Haughtons of Cork; and Graves &#x0026; Co. of Waterford and New Ross (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-18">3.18</xref></xrefGrp>). Brooks Thomas remained the largest employer in 1972, followed by Dockrells, Concrete Products of Ireland (Chadwicks), and Heitons, which had transitioned from its earlier incarnation as a coal importer and distributor.</p>
<p id="C3P72">T. &#x0026; C. Martin, Spaight, and McMahon were primarily engaged in the timber trade. Graves &#x0026; Co., like Spaight, had originated as a shipping company. It encountered the fire-resistant roofing materials it would later produce at New Ross while engaged in business in Denmark in the 1870s. Its Waterford operation dealt primarily in timber. Graves &#x0026; Co. would merge with Dockrells in 1971. Haughtons would merge with Brooks Thomas in 1969.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-18"?></p>
<p id="C3P73"><page id="64" chapter=""/>Though 70&#x2013;80 per cent of the furniture sold in the 1920s was produced domestically, furniture establishments employed an average of only fifteen workers.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-62"><sup>62</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Among the largest of the furniture firms was the mattress, furniture, and furnishings manufacturer Michael O&#x2019;Dea of Dublin. O&#x2019;Dea&#x2019;s workforce would expand to 250&#x2013;300 in the 1920s with the imposition of a tariff on furniture. It would be acquired by UK company Bond Worth in 1969.</p>
<p id="C3P74">Glass bottle production had been concentrated in Ringsend since the late eighteenth century when it was banished from inner-city Dublin for environmental reasons. All three of the Ringsend bottle works collapsed in the 1910s and 1920s in the face of competition from the recently automated British industry. The Irish Glass Bottle Company would be resurrected under tariff protection in the early 1930s and would remain a significant employer in 1972.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-62" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>62</sup></enumerator> The proportion of sales produced domestically in 1926, 1929, and 1931 is reported in the 1931 Census of Industrial Production, xiv.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-14">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-18" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0018" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-18" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-37"><title id="C3T18"><p><enumerator>Table 3.18</enumerator> Selected building materials firms</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Firm</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Employment</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Brooks Thomas (1865), Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>200 (1933), 750 (1968), 1,180 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Thomas Dockrell (1822), Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>&#x2018;Several hundred&#x2019; (1912), 500 (1960), 670 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-19" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0019">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-38"><title id="C3S19"><p>Paper, Print, and Packaging</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P75">Paper making had largely died out in Ireland, other than in Dublin, by the mid-1800s.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-63"><sup>63</sup></xref></xrefGrp> By 1920, even the five paper mills on the rivers west of the city were inactive for long periods of time. There were only forty-one employed in the sector in 1928. Paper making, too, would be resurrected under tariff protection. Printing and production of stationery and packaging materials, by contrast, were shielded from import competition by the requirements for customized service, and these segments hosted around a dozen firms with workforces of 200&#x2013;300 at the foundation of the state. The largest employers were the Dublin firms Alexander Thom &#x0026; Co. and Helys (<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-19">3.19</xref></xrefGrp>), both of which feature in Joyce&#x2019;s <i>Ulysses</i> as former employers of Leopold Bloom. Thom &#x0026; Co. had been established by a young Scottish immigrant in 1825 and had been appointed official government printer for Ireland in 1876. Helys <page id="65" chapter=""/>operated a substantial retail premises on Dame Street and a large printing plant, the Acme Works, on nearby Dame Court.</p>
<p id="C3P76">Most of the firms in the sector were Protestant-owned, though Browne &#x0026; Nolan had expanded by catering to the captive market for Catholic and nationalist publications.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-64"><sup>64</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Unusually, Cahill &#x0026; Co., a large-scale printer of popular paperbacks, produced primarily for the export market.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-65"><sup>65</sup></xref></xrefGrp> By 1972, many of the firms had been acquired as part of the decade-long battle between the Smurfit and Clondalkin Paper Groups for control of the sector.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-19"?></p>
<p id="C3P77">The largest national newspapers also each employed around 300 in the lead-up to independence. The <i>Freeman&#x2019;s Journal</i> had been the most prominent Catholic/nationalist paper in the late nineteenth century but was rapidly eclipsed by William Martin Murphy&#x2019;s <i>Irish Independent</i> from its launch in 1905. By 1921, the <i>Independent</i> had a circulation of 134,000 copies a day.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-66"><sup>66</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The <i>Journal</i>&#x2019;s circulation had remained stagnant at around 35,000.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-67"><sup>67</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Until the 1980s, the <i>Independent</i>&#x2019;s masthead proclaimed its incorporation of its former rival, which it acquired upon the latter&#x2019;s demise in 1924. Its workforce would double to 600 over the following decade and would double again by 1966. It would remain the largest-circulation Irish newspaper in 1972.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-63" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>63</sup></enumerator> Bielenberg, <i>Cork&#x2019;s Industrial Revolution 1780&#x2013;1880</i>, 79.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-64" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>64</sup></enumerator> Daly, <i>Dublin: The Deposed Capital, 1860&#x2013;1914</i>, 46.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-65" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>65</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 16 September 1927.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-66" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>66</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-36" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Kenneally, Ian" partTitle="Nationalist in the Broadest Sense: The Irish Independent and the Irish Revolution" editor="O&#x2019;Brien, Mark|Rafter, Kevin" date="2012" title="Independent Newspapers A History" page="39" pageLast="51" place="Dublin" publisher="Four Courts Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Ian" mainName="Kenneally" role="partAuthor">Ian Kenneally</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Nationalist in the Broadest Sense: The Irish Independent and the Irish Revolution&#x2019;, in <i>Independent Newspapers A History</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Mark" mainName="O&#x2019;brien" role="editor">Mark O&#x2019;Brien</nameGrp> and ; <nameGrp foreNames="Kevin" mainName="Rafter" role="editor">Kevin Rafter</nameGrp> (Dublin: Four Courts Press, 2012): 39&#x2013;51.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-67" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>67</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-bibItem-37" class="journalArticle" author="Larkin, Felix M." date="2006" title="A Great Daily Organ&#x201D;: The Freeman&#x2019;s Journal, 1763&#x2013;1924" journalName="History Ireland" page="44" pageLast="49" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Felix M." mainName="Larkin" role="author">Felix M. Larkin</nameGrp>, &#x2018;&#x201C;A Great Daily Organ&#x201D;: The Freeman&#x2019;s Journal, 1763&#x2013;1924&#x2019;. <i>History Ireland</i> (2006): 44&#x2013;49.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-15">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-19" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0019" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-19" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-39"><title id="C3T19"><p><enumerator>Table 3.19</enumerator> Selected printing, stationery, and packaging firms</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Firm</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Employment</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Firm</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Employment</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Helys (1896)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>500 (1916), 400&#x2013;500 (1933), 450 (1960)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p><i>Freeman&#x2019;s Journal</i> (1763)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>300 (1924)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Alexander Thom (1825)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>500 (1912)</p>
<p>700 (1916), 400 (1921), 500 (1948, 1960)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p><i>Irish Independent</i> (1905)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>300 (1911), 500 (1926), 600 (1935), 800 (1950), 900 (1960), 1,200 (1966)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-div2-20" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.022.0020">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-40"><title id="C3S20"><p>Chemicals</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C3P78">The chemicals sector of the early Free State era was dominated by fertilizers, of which the most significant producer by far was W. &#x0026; H. M. Goulding <page id="66" chapter=""/>(<xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-20">3.20</xref></xrefGrp>). Established in Cork in 1856, Gouldings held a number of scientific patents and was another of the country&#x2019;s earliest indigenous multinationals, though both of its foreign operations &#x2013; in France and the United States &#x2013; were short-lived.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-68"><sup>68</sup></xref></xrefGrp> By 1922, it had plants in Dublin, Cork and Waterford, and a further three in Northern Ireland. It also owned or controlled three other Free State firms, including the Dublin docklands company Morgan Mooney &#x0026; Co.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-20"?></p>
<p id="C3P79">Though there were firms of note in both soap and candle making, there were only 230 employed in these sectors prior to the introduction of tariffs in the 1920s. The Rathbornes had been producing candles in Dublin since 1488. The family firm, John G. Rathborne, was taken over by the Dublin Quaker soap manufacturer John Barrington &#x0026; Sons in 1914. Barringtons was acquired by Lever Brothers several&#x00A0;years earlier. Lever would dispose of its candle-making interests to Shell in 1923 and would build a major new soap factory on Dublin&#x2019;s Sheriff Street in 1927. The largest producer of paints and varnishes was the Shandon Chemical Works, established by Stanley (later Sir Stanley) Harrington and his brothers in 1885. It merged with its main British supplier to become Harrington-Goodlass Wall in 1922. The new firm would be awarded the contract to supply the Free State Post Office with paint of &#x2018;Saorst&#x00E1;t green&#x2019; and would later, in collaboration with ICI, act as paint supplier to Ford.</p>
<p id="C3P80">One further chemicals firm of note was the phosphorescent match producer Paterson, whose factory at Hammond Lane was acquired by the Liverpool firm Maguire &#x0026; Miller in 1919. The principal of the latter, Alexander Maguire, was of Liverpool-Irish stock and had been knighted for his promotion of a safer form of phosphorus than the variety then in common usage. He would later also be honoured by the Pope for his sponsorship of the Catholic Social Action movement. The Dublin enterprise was renamed Maguire &#x0026; Paterson in 1922. It employed a workforce of 200&#x2013;300 throughout the period to 1972.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-note-68" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>68</sup></enumerator> It had opened a plant in France in the 1870s to source raw materials for the local market, and established a factory in Florida in the 1890s to economize on shipping costs from Ireland. Both operations closed within a few years.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-floatGroup-16">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-tableGroup-20" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0003.007.0020" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-table-20" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3-titleGroup-41"><title id="C3T20"><p><enumerator>Table 3.20</enumerator> Leading chemicals firm: Goulding Fertilizers</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Gouldings (1856)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Fertilizers</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>800&#x2013;1,000 (1912), major employer through to 1972</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
</div1>
</textMatter>
</chapter>
</mainText>
</book>