<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OXFORD//DTD OXCHAPML//EN" "OxChapML.dtd">
<book id="oso-9780198878230-book-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.001.0001" OSOsubject="physics">
<bookMeta id="oso-9780198878230-bookMeta-1">
<versionInfo>
<versionDate>2023-05-06</versionDate>
<versionDesc>Proofs</versionDesc>
</versionInfo>
<metaItem about="book">
<metaItem about="DTD">
<metaDescribes predicate="DTDname">OxChapML</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
<metaItem about="TCIgroup">
<metaItem about="TCI">
<metaDescribes predicate="TCIname">OUP TCI</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="version">20170301.0</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaItem>
<metaDescribes predicate="product">oso</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="colour-figures-for-online">Yes</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="publishing-group">oso US</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="captured-by">Integra</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</bookMeta>
<mainText id="oso-9780198878230-mainText-1">
<chapter id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004">
<metaInfo id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-metaInfo-1">
<versionInfo>
<versionDate>2023-05-06</versionDate>
<versionDesc>Proofs</versionDesc>
</versionInfo>
<creatorGroup>
<creator class="author" invertedForm="Barry, Frank"><forenames>Frank</forenames><surname>Barry</surname></creator>
</creatorGroup>
<abstract>
<p>Official data on economic conditions in the Irish Free State are available only from 1926: analyses that take this as their starting point are likely to understate significantly the industrial expansion that occurred over the first decade of independence. Much of the criticism of the economic policies adopted at the time is argued to have been misplaced. Because the Free State had emerged from a victorious rather than a defeated empire, its major export market remained intact. Pressures to create new jobs were also far weaker than in the newly established &#x2018;successor states&#x2019; on Europe&#x2019;s eastern peripheries: land redistribution in Ireland was much further advanced, there were fewer landless labourers, and emigration options remained more easily accessible. The stability-oriented monetary and fiscal policies of the time would yield benefits both then and into the future. Nor did the governments of the 1920s adhere as closely to laissez-faire principles as is generally imagined. The modest &#x2018;experimental&#x2019; tariffs adopted created considerable numbers of jobs, which would have been included in the official data for 1926. The chapter also identifies the largest manufacturing employers in operation in the state on the eve of the Great Depression. Even by 1929, four of the five largest employers were foreign-owned. The foreign share of employment across all of industry is likely to have been around 15 per cent in 1922. It had grown to around 20 per cent by the end of the decade.</p>
</abstract>
<keySubjectWords>
<keyword>state formation</keyword>
<keyword>selective protection</keyword>
<keyword>inter-war states</keyword>
<keyword>Sterling link</keyword>
<keyword>tariff factories</keyword>
<keyword>tariff-jumping FDI</keyword></keySubjectWords>
<disclaimer><p><i>Industry and Policy in Independent Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1972</i>. Frank Barry, Oxford University Press. &#x00A9; Frank Barry (2023). DOI: 10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004</p></disclaimer>
<metaItem about="book">
<metaItem about="DTD">
<metaDescribes predicate="DTDname">OxChapML</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
<metaItem about="TCIgroup">
<metaItem about="TCI">
<metaDescribes predicate="TCIname">OUP TCI</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="version">20170301.0</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaItem>
<metaDescribes predicate="product">oso</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="colour-figures-for-online">Yes</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="publishing-group">oso US</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="captured-by">Integra</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaInfo>
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-titleGroup-1"><title id="C4"><p><page id="67" chapter=""/><enumerator>4</enumerator> The Irish Free State of the 1920s</p></title></titleGroup>
<textMatter id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-textMatter-1">
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-div1-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004.021.0001" role="prelim">
<p id="C4P1">Official data on industrial conditions in the Irish Free State are available only from 1926. Analyses that take this as their starting point are likely to understate significantly the expansion that occurred over the first decade of independence. The economy was in the midst of a severe downturn in 1922. The UK recession of the previous two&#x00A0;years had been the worst in living memory and the agricultural boom of the First World War period, which had been of particular significance to rural Ireland, had just collapsed. Industry too was under severe pressure. Wartime demand for Irish manufacturing output had been sustained by the absence of competing imports on the British market as well as in Ireland. Import competition had rebounded to intense levels by the early 1920s.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-1"><sup>1</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P2">These difficulties were compounded by the bitter industrial relations environment of the time and the death, destruction, and economic disruption of the eleven-month civil war which broke out in mid-1922.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-2"><sup>2</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The number of days lost through industrial disputes over the four years 1922&#x2013;1925 would not be reached again until the late 1960s.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-3"><sup>3</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The civil war resulted in several thousand deaths, with destruction of property and infrastructure estimated to have amounted to some 30 per cent of national income.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-4"><sup>4</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The costs of the disruption to trade and economic activity have not been quantified.</p>
<p id="C4P3">Free State industry, and the economy more generally, is likely have been in recovery by 1926.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-5"><sup>5</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The earliest of the Cumann na nGaedheal tariffs were also beginning to have an effect. The economic rebound was facilitated by the successful management of the Free State public finances, which contrasted <page id="68" chapter=""/>with the early experiences of the newly established states on Europe&#x2019;s eastern peripheries. Unable to raise revenues by conventional means, these other new states were forced into extreme measures &#x2018;to cope with relief and reconstruction and to ease the pressure of political and social disorders&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-6"><sup>6</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The inflationary and currency chaos that ensued would adversely impact on their policy choices into the future.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-7"><sup>7</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-1" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>1</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-1" class="book" author="Johnson, David" date="1989" title="The Interwar Economy in Ireland" page="3" pageLast="5" place="Dundalk" publisher="Dundalgan Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="David" mainName="Johnson" role="author">David Johnson</nameGrp>, <i>The Interwar Economy in Ireland</i> (Dundalk: Dundalgan Press, 1989), 3&#x2013;5</bibItem>; <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-2" class="book" author="Riordan, Edward J." date="1920" title="Modern Irish Trade and Industry" place="London, New York" publisher="Metheuen, E. P. Dutton" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Edward J." mainName="Riordan" role="author">Edward J. Riordan</nameGrp>, <i>Modern Irish Trade and Industry</i> (London, New York: Metheuen, E. P. Dutton, 1920).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-2" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>2</sup></enumerator> The civil war was fought over the acceptability of the constitutional limitations on independence upon which Britain had insisted, given the potential for a more widespread unravelling of the bonds of empire. Under the terms of the Anglo-Irish Treaty of 1921 the Irish Free State was established as a Commonwealth dominion with a status equivalent specifically to that of Canada.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-3" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>3</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-3" class="journalArticle" author="Brannick, Teresa|Devine, Francis|Kelly, Aidan" date="2000" title="Social Statistics for Labour Historians: Strike Statistics, 1922&#x2013;99" journalName="Saothar" vol="25" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Teresa" mainName="Brannick" role="author">Teresa Brannick</nameGrp>, <nameGrp foreNames="Francis" mainName="Devine" role="author">Francis Devine</nameGrp>, and <nameGrp foreNames="Aidan" mainName="Kelly" role="author">Aidan Kelly</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Social Statistics for Labour Historians: Strike Statistics, 1922&#x2013;99&#x2019;. <i>Saothar</i> 25 (2000): 114&#x2013;20.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-4" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>4</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-4" class="journalArticle" author="Kenny, Se&#x00E1;n|McLaughlin, Eoin" date="2022" journalIssue="1" title="The Political Economy of Secession: Lessons from the Early&#x00A0;Years of the Irish Free State" journalName="National Institute Economic Review" vol="261" page="48" pageLast="78" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Se&#x00E1;N" mainName="Kenny" role="author">Se&#x00E1;n Kenny</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Eoin" mainName="Mclaughlin" role="author">Eoin McLaughlin</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Political Economy of Secession: Lessons from the Early&#x00A0;Years of the Irish Free State&#x2019;. <i>National Institute Economic Review</i> 261, 1 (2022): 48&#x2013;78.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-5" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>5</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-5" class="journalArticle" author="Geary, R. C." date="1951" journalIssue="160" title="Irish Economic Development since the Treaty" journalName="Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review" vol="40" page="404" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="R. C." mainName="Geary" role="author">R. C. Geary</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Irish Economic Development since the Treaty&#x2019;. <i>Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review</i> 40, 160 (1951): 404.</bibItem> The trough across Europe generally was reached in 1925: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-6" class="book" author="Pollard, Sidney" date="1981" title="Peaceful Conquest: The Industrialization of Europe, 1760&#x2013;1970" page="278" place="Oxford" publisher="Oxford University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Sidney" mainName="Pollard" role="author">Sidney Pollard</nameGrp>, <i>Peaceful Conquest: The Industrialization of Europe, 1760&#x2013;1970</i> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1981), 278.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-6" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>6</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-7" class="book" author="Aldcroft, Derek H." date="2006" title="Europe&#x2019;s Third World: The European Periphery in the Interwar Years" place="Aldershot" publisher="Ashgate" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Derek H." mainName="Aldcroft" role="author">Derek H. Aldcroft</nameGrp>, <i>Europe&#x2019;s Third World: The European Periphery in the Interwar Years</i> (Aldershot: Ashgate, 2006).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-7" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>7</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-8" class="journalArticle" author="Eichengreen, Barry|Irwin, Douglas A" date="2010" journalIssue="4" title="The Slide to Protectionism in the Great Depression: Who Succumbed and Why?" journalName="Journal of Economic History" vol="70" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Barry" mainName="Eichengreen" role="author">Barry Eichengreen</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Douglas A" mainName="Irwin" role="author">Douglas A Irwin</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Slide to Protectionism in the Great Depression: Who Succumbed and Why?&#x2019; <i>Journal of Economic History</i> 70, 4 (2010): 871&#x2013;97.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-div1-2" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004.021.0002">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-titleGroup-2"><title id="C4S1"><p><enumerator>4.1</enumerator> Establishment of the State</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C4P4">The first proclamation issued by the Provisional Government in January 1922 directed that all law courts, civil and public servants, and others hitherto under the authority of the British government &#x2018;shall continue to carry out their functions unless and until otherwise ordered by us&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-8"><sup>8</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The legal system was largely maintained intact. The case of the civil service was more complicated.</p>
<p id="C4P5">Nationalists had been bitterly hostile to the &#x2018;Dublin Castle&#x2019; bureaucracy that had administered the country in conjunction with Whitehall under British rule. An underground civil service had been created during the war of independence, but the split over the terms of the Treaty meant that the loyalty of the body in its entirety could not be relied upon. Plans to construct a completely new apparatus were abandoned and &#x2018;the civil service of the D&#x00E1;il was assimilated into the old Castle administration rather than the other way round&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-9"><sup>9</sup></xref></xrefGrp> From 1924, all new civil servants would be recruited by open competitive examinations.</p>
<p id="C4P6">The large-scale transfer of officials from the previous administration would leave a legacy of mistrust of the new civil service which, though particularly prevalent on the anti-Treaty side, was evident across all political parties. Suspicions pertained particularly to the Department of Finance and its two most senior figures, Joseph Brennan and J. J. McElligott. Claims that they were &#x2018;unalterably and fanatically attached to the English interest&#x2019; were definitively without foundation.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-10"><sup>10</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Brennan had served in a variety of administrative <page id="69" chapter=""/>positions since 1912 but&#x2014;as he would reveal for the first time more than fifty&#x00A0;years later&#x2014;had provided detailed financial advice to Collins and the Treaty negotiating team on strict condition of anonymity and at great personal risk.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-11"><sup>11</sup></xref></xrefGrp> McElligott too had served in the Crown service but had been dismissed and jailed for his participation in the 1916 Rising. He was recruited by Brennan from London, where he had risen to become managing editor of the British financial weekly, the <i>Statist</i>.</p>
<p id="C4P7">Suspicions of Brennan and McElligott reflected a mix of frustration at the British Treasury system in which they had been schooled&#x2014;and which was adopted at their behest&#x2014;and at their adherence to Treasury thinking on the benefits of free trade and the importance of balanced budgets and low taxation. Their personal histories contrasted with those of some of the senior officials of the new Department of Industry and Commerce, whose promotion of a more interventionist agenda appears to have inured them from suspicion. The appointment of Gordon Campbell, son of Lord Glenavy, as Secretary of Industry and Commerce was said to have delighted Irish unionists.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-12"><sup>12</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Campbell too had been a member of the Crown bureaucracy, as had R. C. Ferguson, an Ulster Presbyterian who would become Assistant Secretary of the department in 1927.</p>
<p id="C4P8">The failure of the new state to live up to the economic expectations of the nationalist movement has been blamed, even by many modern historians, on the conservative principles that the senior figures in the Department of Finance espoused. An alternative perspective is provided by Se&#x00E1;n Cromien, who served as Secretary of the Department in the 1980s and 1990s. &#x2018;It was very important&#x2019;, Cromien asserts, &#x2018;that the new state should proceed prudently in its budgetary and financial affairs&#x2019;:</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-displayText-1" class="prosequote">
<p>The fact that it soon established a reputation for being a well-run country where British and other businessmen and investors could do business was largely the result of the policy advice of Brennan and McElligott. [This served as] a useful corrective to the unreasonable expectations of the young and inexperienced politicians who took office in 1922 and those who succeeded them in 1932.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-13"><sup>13</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C4P9">The Treasury system that generated such hostility accorded the Department of Finance a central role in controlling the expenditure of other government departments. As T. K. Whitaker would explain to a sceptical audience <page id="70" chapter=""/>of senior officials of these other departments in 1953, the Department of Finance position &#x2018;must inevitably be conditioned not only by the merits of the proposals themselves&#x2014;not always as apparent to others as to the sponsors&#x2014;but also by their implications, in conjunction with everything else, for the national finances and the national economy&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-14"><sup>14</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The resilience of the system is reflected in the fact that it remains in operation to this day.</p>
<p id="C4P10">That Whitaker too was a proponent of free trade and low taxation demonstrates the strong line of continuity in Department of Finance thinking over the decades. The stance of the Department of Industry and Commerce has frequently been portrayed as &#x2018;developmentalist&#x2019;, while that of the Department of Finance has been criticized as negative and obstructionist.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-15"><sup>15</sup></xref></xrefGrp> There was a similar continuity in the Industry and Commerce position advanced by Campbell and his successors John Leydon and J. C. B. McCarthy, with whom Whitaker would cross swords in the 1950s. Though Leydon had served in the Department of Finance from 1923, he would become a trusted advisor to Lemass upon becoming Secretary of Industry and Commerce in 1932 and would remain so even after his retirement from the civil service in 1955.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-16"><sup>16</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P11">The Department of Finance, even under Cumann na nGaedheal, did not win every significant policy battle between the two departments. Neither would prove to have a monopoly of wisdom on economic and industrial development strategy. Whitaker would point out in 2005 that the Department of Finance approach forced others &#x2018;to punch hard to get their point across&#x2019;, to which Garret FitzGerald responded: &#x2018;It is a very important role and it&#x2019;s not always as negative as it seems.&#x2019;<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-17"><sup>17</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-8" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>8</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-9" class="book" author="Maguire, Martin" date="2013" title="The Civil Service and the Revolution in Ireland, 1912&#x2013;38: &#x2018;Shaking the Blood-Stained Hand of Mr. Collins" page="128" place="Manchester" publisher="Manchester University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Martin" mainName="Maguire" role="author">Martin Maguire</nameGrp>, <i>The Civil Service and the Revolution in Ireland, 1912&#x2013;38: &#x2018;Shaking the Blood-Stained Hand of Mr. Collins</i><i>&#x2019;</i> (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2013), 128.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-9" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>9</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-10" class="book" author="Maguire, Martin" date="2013" title="The Civil Service and the Revolution in Ireland, 1912&#x2013;38: &#x2018;Shaking the Blood-Stained Hand of Mr. Collins" page="128" place="Manchester" publisher="Manchester University Press" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-9">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 138.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-10" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>10</sup></enumerator> The claim was made by Se&#x00E1;n McEntee, cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-11" class="book" author="Maguire, Martin" date="2013" title="The Civil Service and the Revolution in Ireland, 1912&#x2013;38: &#x2018;Shaking the Blood-Stained Hand of Mr. Collins" page="128" place="Manchester" publisher="Manchester University Press" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-9">ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 207. De Valera appears to have been more fair-minded: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-12" class="journalArticle" author="Devlin, Anna|Barry, Frank" date="2019" journalIssue="1" title="Protection versus Free Trade in the Free State Era: The Finance Attitude" journalName="Irish Economic and Social History" vol="46" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Anna" mainName="Devlin" role="author">Anna Devlin</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Protection versus Free Trade in the Free State Era: The Finance Attitude&#x2019;. <i>Irish Economic and Social History</i> 46, 1 (2019): 3&#x2013;21</bibItem>: fn 118; Maguire, <i>The Civil Service and the Revolution in Ireland&#x2019;</i>, 220.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-11" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>11</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-13" class="journalArticle" author="O&#x2019;Broin, Leon" date="1977" journalIssue="261" title="Joseph Brennan, Civil Servant Extraordinary" journalName="Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review" vol="66" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Leon" mainName="O&#x2019;broin" role="author">Leon O&#x2019;Broin</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Joseph Brennan, Civil Servant Extraordinary&#x2019;. <i>Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review</i> 66, 261 (1977): 25&#x2013;37.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-12" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>12</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-14" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="J. Dempsey, Pauric" partTitle="Campbell, Charles Gordon" date="2009" title="Dictionary of Irish Biography" place="Cambridge" publisher="Cambridge University Press" url="https://www.dib.ie/" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Pauric" mainName="J. Dempsey" role="partAuthor">Pauric J. Dempsey</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Campbell, Charles Gordon&#x2019;, in <i>Dictionary of Irish Biography</i>, <url webUrl="https://www.dib.ie/">https://www.dib.ie/</url> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-13" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>13</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-15" class="book" author="Cromien, Se&#x00E1;n|Brennan, Joseph" date="2009" title="Dictionary of Irish Biography" place="Cambridge" publisher="Cambridge University Press" url="https://www.dib.ie/" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Se&#x00E1;N" mainName="Cromien" role="author">Se&#x00E1;n Cromien</nameGrp>, &#x2018;<nameGrp foreNames="Joseph" mainName="Brennan" role="author">Brennan, Joseph</nameGrp>&#x2019;, in <i>Dictionary of Irish Biography</i> <url webUrl="https://www.dib.ie/">https://www.dib.ie/</url> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009)</bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-14" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>14</sup></enumerator> Cited in Devlin and Barry, &#x2018;Protection versus Free Trade in the Free State Era: The Finance Attitude&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-15" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>15</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-16" class="book" author="Lee, John Joseph" date="1989" title="Ireland 1912&#x2013;1985: Politics and Society" place="Cambridge" publisher="Cambridge University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John Joseph" mainName="Lee" role="author">John Joseph Lee</nameGrp>, <i>Ireland 1912&#x2013;1985: Politics and Society</i> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989);</bibItem> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-17" class="book" author="Girvin, Brian" date="1989" title="Between Two Worlds: Politics and Economy in Independent Ireland" place="Dublin" publisher="Rowman &#x0026; Littlefield" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Brian" mainName="Girvin" role="author">Brian Girvin</nameGrp>, <i>Between Two Worlds: Politics and Economy in Independent Ireland</i> (Dublin: Rowman &#x0026; Littlefield, 1989);</bibItem> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-18" class="book" author="Murphy, Gary" date="2009" title="In Search of the Promised Land: The Politics of Post-War Ireland" place="Cork" publisher="Mercier Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Gary" mainName="Murphy" role="author">Gary Murphy</nameGrp>, <i>In Search of the Promised Land: The Politics of Post-War Ireland</i> (Cork: Mercier Press, 2009).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-16" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>16</sup></enumerator> Leydon had been offered the position of Secretary of Industry and Commerce upon Campbell&#x2019;s succession to his father&#x2019;s title just before the 1932 general election but delayed accepting the offer until it had been approved by the new government.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-17" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>17</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-19" class="unclassified" author="Whitaker, T. K." date="2005" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="T. K." mainName="Whitaker" role="author">T. K. Whitaker</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Opening Up to the International Economy: Ireland in the 1950s&#x2019;. Witness seminar, Centre for Contemporary Irish History, Trinity College Dublin, 19 January 2005.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-div1-3" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004.021.0003">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-titleGroup-3"><title id="C4S2"><p><enumerator>4.2</enumerator> Economic Policy</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C4P12">In the other newly established states of the interwar period, which stretched from Finland in the north to Yugoslavia in the south,</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-displayText-2" class="prosequote">
<p>Lack of self-determination and the impossibility of an independent economic policy were considered to be the main reasons for previous failures [.&#x00A0;.&#x00A0;.] The <page id="71" chapter=""/>new Zeitgeist of surging nationalism which equated independence with economic self-sufficiency became the cradle of a new modernization philosophy.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-18"><sup>18</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C4P13">It had been presumed that an independent Ireland too would rapidly turn protectionist. The long-established trade relationships of the other new states had been severed however by the collapse of the empires of which they had been a part, while the Irish Free State retained free access to the massive export market on its doorstep. The social and political pressures that it faced to create new jobs were also far weaker: land redistribution in Ireland was much further advanced, there were substantially fewer landless labourers, and emigration options remained more easily accessible.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-19"><sup>19</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Even the livelihoods of the close-to-subsistence farmers of the west of Ireland who would prove the bedrock of early Fianna F&#x00E1;il support were dependent on international trade. They were exporters of pigs and eggs and net consumers of wheat, the main agricultural product on which protectionists proposed to impose tariffs. The price of the young cattle that they sold on to the &#x2018;ranchers&#x2019; of the midlands and east was determined by the price these cattle would ultimately sell for on the British market.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-20"><sup>20</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The constellation of political pressures that determined Irish trade policy &#x2013; and the trade policies of other states across the world &#x2013; would change with the onset of the Great Depression.</p>
<p id="C4P14">The Cumann na nGaedheal governments of the first decade of independence were pragmatists rather than ideologues. Though they did not adhere as closely to laissez-faire principles as is generally imagined, they prioritized stability:</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-displayText-3" class="prosequote">
<p>They had before their eyes the example of financial collapse in many countries. In such circumstance they were naturally reluctant to make experiments. The difficulties of managing a system to which they were unaccustomed in a period of instability both at home and abroad was great enough; to overhaul that system was out of the question.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-21"><sup>21</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C4P15">The fiscal position of the state in its early&#x00A0;years was extremely precarious. Compensation for property losses and expenditure on the army absorbed <page id="72" chapter=""/>almost three-quarters of government revenue in 1924.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-22"><sup>22</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The share of the UK national debt for which the state was potentially liable under the terms of the Treaty amounted to 80 per cent of national income: this would be written off only as part of the Boundary Commission settlement of 1925.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-23"><sup>23</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P16">The pensions issue had been central to earlier discussions of the economics of independence. As a share of national income, Irish pension expenditures were the highest in Europe.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-24"><sup>24</sup></xref></xrefGrp> To bring them into line with the United Kingdom by this measure would have required a rate cut of between 30 and 50 per cent. The one-shilling cut imposed by Finance Minister Ernest Blythe amounted to a reduction of 10 per cent and was announced as the government prepared for the launch of the first national loan, when establishing the creditworthiness of the state was a key priority.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-25"><sup>25</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Though the 10-shilling rate had been restored by 1928 (subject to a tighter means test), the decision is widely agreed to have been a factor in the governing party&#x2019;s loss of popularity and eventual loss of power.</p>
<p id="C4P17">As for the alternative of raising income tax, here too the government was constrained. Not only had nationalists long argued that Ireland had been overtaxed, but it was also believed that if economics lay at the core of the North&#x2013;South divide, then low taxation might make a united Ireland more attractive to northern unionists.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-26"><sup>26</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Of most immediate concern was the prospect of further capital flight. &#x2018;Some of those who paid large amounts in income tax were out of sympathy with the new regime and transferred their domicile to Great Britain.&#x2019;<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-27"><sup>27</sup></xref></xrefGrp> It was not that large-scale migration would ensue but that adverse changes in relative income tax rates could have serious consequences for the Exchequer, and for the business environment more generally.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-28"><sup>28</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P18"><page id="73" chapter=""/>The double taxation agreement signed with the United Kingdom in 1926 was based on a model advocated by the League of Nations. It necessitated responding even more closely to developments in British taxation and it became customary for this reason to delay the Irish budget until several weeks after the British budget had been announced.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-29"><sup>29</sup></xref></xrefGrp> From 1927, the income tax rate had been brought below that in the United Kingdom and did not subsequently exceed it, even under the more radical administrations of the 1930s.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-30"><sup>30</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Criticism of Cumann na nGaedheal&#x2019;s reliance on indirect taxation overlooks the fact that the much more extensive tariffs of the 1930s and beyond had exactly the same effect on consumer prices.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-31"><sup>31</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P19">Currency policy was another area of controversy in the early Free State. The new currencies launched in the eastern periphery states had depreciated sharply, with severe inflationary&#x2014;and sometimes hyperinflationary&#x2014;consequences. Decisions on currency were less pressing in Ireland. Though there was, for the first number of years, &#x2018;no legal tender in circulation identifiable as such&#x2019;, British currency notes and coins continued to circulate freely and Irish private bank notes remained fully payable in sterling.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-32"><sup>32</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The deflation resulting from Britain&#x2019;s desire to restore the currency to its pre-war Gold Standard exchange rate was dramatically disruptive of industrial peace but was largely over by the time the Free State was established.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-33"><sup>33</sup></xref></xrefGrp> From the early 1920s, &#x2018;hostility towards inflation became the <i>leitmotif</i> of economic policy across Europe&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-34"><sup>34</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P20">A new Irish pound, linked one-to-one with sterling and fully backed by a reserve of sterling and sterling securities, was eventually introduced in 1928. The arrangement ensured that developments in Irish retail prices and interest rates paralleled those in the United Kingdom.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-35"><sup>35</sup></xref></xrefGrp> It also tightly constrained fiscal policy, which could otherwise erode confidence in the currency link.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-36"><sup>36</sup></xref></xrefGrp> <page id="74" chapter=""/>By mutual agreement, the cost of exchanging the currencies was set at zero. The decision was warmly welcomed by the commercial and banking communities. Though the opposition gave the impression of being less than fully convinced of its merits, Fianna F&#x00E1;il, once in power, would prove no more keen than Cumann na nGaedheal had been to change the arrangement.</p>
<p id="C4P21">It has been suggested that Keynes may have had the Free State in mind when discussing the merits of such a &#x2018;currency board&#x2019; system:</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-displayText-4" class="prosequote">
<p>For countries which are small compared with their neighbours, or do not contain independent financial centres of international importance, an Exchange Standard may be ideal. But it does undoubtedly involve some measure of dependence on the country whose money is chosen as the basis of the Exchange Standard, which may be hurtful to the national pride.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-37"><sup>37</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C4P22">The hurt to national pride notwithstanding, Irish economists have been strongly supportive of the policy. Honohan writes that the temptation to abandon sterling for political reasons was resisted &#x2018;and the consequences must overall be considered a success&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-38"><sup>38</sup></xref></xrefGrp> To &#x00D3; Gr&#x00E1;da, &#x2018;the logic of maintaining the link with sterling in the interwar period was compelling&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-39"><sup>39</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p alignment="centre"></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C4P23">Southern unionist concerns that a nationalist government would be fiscally profligate proved unfounded. The annual fiscal deficit rarely exceeded 2 per cent of national income until the 1950s.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-40"><sup>40</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The informal partnership established between William Martin Murphy, Presbyterian Charles Eason, and Quaker George Jacob during the bitter Dublin lock-out of 1913 had helped to stabilize business sentiment.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-41"><sup>41</sup></xref></xrefGrp> So too did the appointment of a number of business leaders to the new Free State Senate. These included the banker and distiller Andrew Jameson; Arthur Jackson, the head of Pollexfen grain millers; Benjamin Haughton, principal of the Cork Timber and Iron Company; and members of the Guinness and Goodbody families. Catholic nationalist appointees included margarine manufacturer James Charles Dowdall, who would later join Fianna F&#x00E1;il. Four members of a loose Business Party <page id="75" chapter=""/>alliance were elected to the lower chamber in 1923. Three of them&#x2014;building contractor John Good, coal distributor William Hewat, and brewer Richard Beamish&#x2014;were former unionists. The fourth was the creamery owner and textile manufacturer Andrew O&#x2019;Shaughnessy. Eager for stability and encouraged by the cautious financial policies of the new government, most business interests threw their support behind the pro-Treaty party.</p>
<p id="C4P24">The old elite did not have everything its own way, however. The land settlement up to this point had &#x2018;involved the transfer of ownership from ten thousand or so landed proprietors, mainly Protestant and Unionist, to half a million or so mainly Catholic and Nationalist landholders&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-42"><sup>42</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Thirty per cent of agricultural land still remained in the hands of the landlord class. These were &#x2018;the hard knots that it had been impossible to disentangle under the system of voluntary purchase&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-43"><sup>43</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Upon being informed that there were multitudes of landless men prepared to enforce their claims &#x2018;with the gun and the torch&#x2019;, William T. Cosgrave advocated that negotiations be concluded rapidly to discourage landlords from making exorbitant demands.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-44"><sup>44</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The vast bulk of the remaining estates had been bought out by the end of the Cumann na nGaedheal era.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-45"><sup>45</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P25">Sir John Keane, a Senator and director of the Bank of Ireland, was sharply critical of what he referred to as the policy of land &#x2018;nationalisation&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-46"><sup>46</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Criticism of the &#x2018;nationalisation&#x2019; of electricity generation and distribution was led by ex-unionist parliamentarians and the <i>Irish Times</i>. Parliamentary criticism of the decision not to follow the United Kingdom in abolishing corporation profits tax in 1924 was led by the ex-unionist John Good TD.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-47"><sup>47</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Hewat and Good were among the principal opponents of the state-led amalgamation of the railways.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-48"><sup>48</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P26">Relations with the financial community had been strained by the Bank of Ireland&#x2019;s unwillingness to participate in the first national loan without a guarantee from the British, which was not forthcoming. The refusal of the <page id="76" chapter=""/>banks to underwrite the loan without a substantial commission incensed the Department of Finance since it meant &#x2018;that [they] declined to make any subscription whatever to the Loan on the terms on which it will be issued to the general public&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-49"><sup>49</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Their practice of depositing their excess liquidity in London would remain a matter of controversy for decades.</p>
<p id="C4P27">Though the 1926 Banking Commission rejected the long-held nationalist view that this deprived the economy of investment capital, it recommended the establishment of a state bank of sorts to meet the credit requirements of smaller farmers and co-operative societies. The problem it identified pertained specifically to agriculture. The unwillingness of local communities to tolerate foreclosures meant that land could not serve as a reliable form of collateral.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-50"><sup>50</sup></xref></xrefGrp> An Agricultural Credit Corporation was duly established in 1927. The Trade Loans (Guarantee) Schemes of the 1920s were a precursor of sorts to the Industrial Credit Company which would be established under Fianna F&#x00E1;il in 1933.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-51"><sup>51</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Only in the late 1960s, when the stability of sterling had come increasingly into question, were the external assets of the Associated Banks &#x2018;repatriated&#x2019; to the Central Bank.</p>
<p id="C4P28">The ex-unionist accounting monopoly was tackled more aggressively. Craig Gardner and Stokes Brothers &#x0026; Pim between them audited the majority of companies quoted on the Stock Exchange. The flow of official business directed to these firms under both Cumann na nGaedheal and subsequent administrations was disproportionately small. The auditing contracts for the first state commercial enterprises established in 1927&#x2014;the Agricultural Credit Corporation, the Electricity Supply Board, and the Dairy Disposal Company&#x2014;went to emerging Catholic firms.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-52"><sup>52</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p alignment="centre"></p>
<p id="C4P29">Even those strongly critical of Cumann na nGaedheal&#x2019;s performance in office recognize the significance of its achievements in the fields of electricity generation and distribution, which were decried as &#x2018;socialist&#x2019; and &#x2018;confiscatory&#x2019; in conservative quarters at the time. Of the 160 electricity undertakings in operation in the Free State area prior to the establishment of the Shannon hydro-electric plant, most&#x2014;apart from those in the hands of local <page id="77" chapter=""/>authorities&#x2014;were tiny. Guinness and a number of other manufacturers produced their own electricity. Industrial concerns outside the major urban areas still largely depended on water, steam power, or internal combustion engines. Electricity consumption per capita was among the lowest in Europe.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-53"><sup>53</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P30">Germany had begun to invest in its hydro-electric resources following the loss of some of its major coal-mining regions in the wake of Versailles. The proposals for a similar scheme at Shannon were developed by an Irish engineer, T. A. McLaughlin, who had been working with Siemens-Schuckert in Germany. McLaughlin had presented his ideas to Patrick McGilligan, the Irish High Commissioner in London, and McGilligan, having developed a mastery of the technical issues involved, promoted the scheme assiduously upon his appointment as Minister for Industry and Commerce in 1924.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-54"><sup>54</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Private-sector interests favoured a smaller hydro-electric station on the Liffey. Shannon, however, was seen as a project of major national significance. It was understood that widespread provision of electricity would raise living standards, enhance industrial and agricultural productivity, facilitate regional development, and reduce the country&#x2019;s dependence on imported coal. The Department of Finance was side-lined to a large extent in the discussions. Brennan was concerned over the massive cost of the scheme though public finance pressures had eased by the time the bulk of the funds had to be raised. McElligott and Finance Minister Ernst Blythe were more favourably disposed to the entire undertaking.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-55"><sup>55</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The ex-unionist establishment was critical of the awarding of the contract to Siemens rather than to a British firm.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-56"><sup>56</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P31">Work on the hydro-electric plant had already begun before the question of how the power was to be distributed was settled. The low population density of the country made it difficult to attract private-sector interest, and it was eventually decided that a single company, the Electricity Supply Board (ESB), would be granted responsibility for both production and distribution on a not-for-profit basis&#x2014;the first such integrated state scheme outside the Soviet Union. Existing electricity undertakings were acquired by compulsory order. Private owners were compensated according to a fixed formula while municipally owned undertakings&#x2014;many of them in the former unionist strongholds of South Dublin&#x2014;were acquired without compensation.</p>
<p id="C4P32"><page id="78" chapter=""/>Sir John Keane was sharply critical of the plan to subject electricity to the same &#x2018;poisonous virus&#x2019; that he had railed against in the case of land purchase.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-57"><sup>57</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Business Party TD William Hewat referred to the ESB&#x2019;s remit as signalling the &#x2018;complete elimination of private enterprise&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-58"><sup>58</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The <i>Irish Times</i> too saw it as part of a pattern of growing state intervention, reflected also in the industrial tariffs then being adopted, and in transport policy, where &#x2018;railways and canals passed to the safe keeping of a government department&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-59"><sup>59</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P33">The establishment of the Dairy Disposal Company (DDC) was another departure from laissez-faire principles. It emerged as a consequence of the collapse of the massive Condensed Milk Company of Ireland. The original company was liquidated in October 1923 with debts totalling half a million pounds. Its assets were bought out by a group of investors led by Andrew O&#x2019;Shaughnessy and re-established as the Condensed Milk Company of Ireland (1924). British wholesaler Lovell and Christmas became the major shareholder, into which O&#x2019;Shaughnessy&#x2019;s Newmarket Dairy Company was absorbed.</p>
<p id="C4P34">The long war of attrition with the proprietary creameries had depleted the cooperative movement of most of its cash and credit. Having been warned by O&#x2019;Shaughnessy that Lovell and Christmas had sufficient resources to crush the cooperatives, the government was notified that it was prepared to sell the Condensed Milk Company to the cooperative body, the Irish Agricultural Organisation Society (IAOS). The offer, however, was &#x2018;an indirect approach to the government, since the company must have been aware that the IAOS lacked the necessary capital&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-60"><sup>60</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P35">There were 580 creameries and separating stations in the Free State at the time, 400 of which were owned cooperatively. The Condensed Milk Company owned 113 of the remaining private concerns. The government seized the opportunity to end the war of attrition. The offer was accepted and the Dairy Disposal Company was established to purchase the Condensed Milk Company and the other proprietary creameries. Over the following years, it closed large numbers of redundant plants, transferred dozens more to new cooperative societies, and developed the creamery industry extensively in West Kerry and County Clare.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-61"><sup>61</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The economies of scale that had allowed the original company to successfully engage in marketing and distribution were <page id="79" chapter=""/>lost however.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-62"><sup>62</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Marketing problems would continue to blight the sector for most of the next half-century. Though clearly intended as an interim solution, the Dairy Disposal Company would be wound up only in the&#x00A0;years following Ireland&#x2019;s accession to the European Economic Community.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-63"><sup>63</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P36">Other agri-food developments of significance included the establishment of the Irish Sugar Manufacturing Company and the rigorous systems of agricultural inspection and control introduced by Minister for Agriculture Patrick Hogan. The acts introduced by Hogan, though considered draconian at the time, enabled Irish produce to recover from the poor reputation it had earned during the First World War. The margin separating the price of Irish and Danish butter on the British market fell by half between 1924 and 1929.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-64"><sup>64</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P37">Sugar beet production had been subsidized in Britain since 1924. An agreement was reached with a consortium of Belgian and Czechoslovak interests to develop the industry in Ireland and a sugar beet factory was opened in Carlow in 1926. The subsidies paid both to the company and to growers were more generous than those on offer in Britain, and the response of Irish growers was substantially stronger than expected. The large profits that accrued to the company proved embarrassing to the government.</p>
<p id="C4P38">By 1931, the factory was supplying one-quarter of national requirements and employing 40&#x2013;50 workers year-round and up to 600 during the three-month busy season. The operation ran into difficulties with the Depression-era collapse in international sugar prices and the strong resistance by growers to the tapered reduction in the subsidy (which had been announced at the initiation of the project). A proposal by the Department of Industry and Commerce in 1931 to build additional factories emphasized that they should be Irish owned and controlled, though the capital cost involved was regarded as beyond the means of Irish investors.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-65"><sup>65</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The Carlow factory would be bought out by the new Fianna F&#x00E1;il government in 1933.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-18" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>18</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-20" class="journalArticle" author="Berend, Ivan T." date="2000" journalIssue="2" title="The Failure of Economic Nationalism: Central and Eastern Europe before World War II" journalName="Revue &#x00E9;conomique" vol="51" page="315" pageLast="322" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Ivan T." mainName="Berend" role="author">Ivan T. Berend</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Failure of Economic Nationalism: Central and Eastern Europe before World War II&#x2019;. <i>Revue &#x00E9;conomique</i> 51, 2 (2000): 315&#x2013;22.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-19" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>19</sup></enumerator> The Common Travel Area Agreement between Ireland and Britain allowed mutual freedom of travel, residence, and work. (Northern Ireland would introduce an employment permit system in 1947.) The US restrictions on immigration introduced in 1924 were also relatively generous to Ireland.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-20" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>20</sup></enumerator> Department of Agriculture, <i>Committee of Inquiry on Post-Emergency Agricultural Policy</i> (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1945), 49.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-21" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>21</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-21" class="unclassified" author="Kepple, Simon" date="1938" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Simon" mainName="Kepple" role="author">Simon Kepple</nameGrp>, &#x2018;A Survey of Taxation and Government Expenditure in the Irish Free State, 1922&#x2013;36&#x2019;. MA thesis, University College Cork, 1938, 74.</bibItem> (I am grateful to Peter Clarke for bringing this document to my attention.)</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-22" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>22</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-22" class="journalArticle" author="FitzGerald, John|Kenny, Se&#x00E1;n" date="2020" journalIssue="4" title="Till Debt Do Us Part&#x201D;: Financial Implications of the Divorce of the Irish Free State from the United Kingdom, 1922&#x2013;1926" journalName="European Review of Economic History" vol="24" page="818" pageLast="842" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John" mainName="Fitzgerald" role="author">John FitzGerald</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Se&#x00E1;N" mainName="Kenny" role="author">Se&#x00E1;n Kenny</nameGrp>, &#x2018;&#x201C;Till Debt Do Us Part&#x201D;: Financial Implications of the Divorce of the Irish Free State from the United Kingdom, 1922&#x2013;1926&#x2019;. <i>European Review of Economic History</i> 24, 4 (2020): 818&#x2013;42.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-23" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>23</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-23" class="journalArticle" author="FitzGerald, John|Kenny, Se&#x00E1;n" date="2020" journalIssue="4" title="Till Debt Do Us Part&#x201D;: Financial Implications of the Divorce of the Irish Free State from the United Kingdom, 1922&#x2013;1926" journalName="European Review of Economic History" vol="24" page="818" pageLast="842" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-22">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-24" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>24</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-24" class="journalArticle" author="Lindert, Peter H." date="1994" journalIssue="1" title="The Rise of Social Spending, 1880&#x2013;1930" journalName="Explorations in Economic History" vol="31" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Peter H." mainName="Lindert" role="author">Peter H. Lindert</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Rise of Social Spending, 1880&#x2013;1930&#x2019;. <i>Explorations in Economic History</i> 31, 1 (1994): 12</bibItem>: table 1C.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-25" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>25</sup></enumerator> Even in the&#x00A0;years following the rate cut, pension payments accounted for more than 10 per cent of government spending: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-25" class="journalArticle" author="&#x00D3; Gr&#x00E1;da, Cormac" date="2002" journalIssue="1" title="The Greatest Blessing of All&#x201D;: The Old Age Pension in Ireland" journalName="Past &#x0026; Present" vol="175" page="124" pageLast="161" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Cormac" mainName="&#x00d3; Gr&#x00e1;da" role="author">Cormac &#x00D3; Gr&#x00E1;da</nameGrp>, &#x2018;&#x201C;The Greatest Blessing of All&#x201D;: The Old Age Pension in Ireland&#x2019;. <i>Past &#x0026; Present</i> 175, 1 (2002): 124&#x2013;61.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-26" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>26</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-26" class="book" author="Regan, John M." date="2001" title="The Irish Counter-Revolution, 1921&#x2013;1936: Treatyite Politics and Settlement in Independent Ireland" page="254" place="Dublin" publisher="Gill and Macmillan" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John M." mainName="Regan" role="author">John M. Regan</nameGrp>, <i>The Irish Counter-Revolution, 1921&#x2013;1936: Treatyite Politics and Settlement in Independent Ireland</i> (Dublin: Gill and Macmillan, 2001), 254;</bibItem> Kevin O&#x2019;Higgins, cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-27" class="unclassified" author="Farrell, Mel" date="2011" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Mel" mainName="Farrell" role="author">Mel Farrell</nameGrp>, &#x2018;&#x201C;Few Supporters and No Organisation&#x201D;? Cumann na nGaedheal Organisation and Policy, 1923&#x2013;33&#x2019;. Ph.D. thesis, National University of Ireland Maynooth, 2011, 103.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-27" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>27</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-28" class="book" author="Meenan, James" date="1970" title="The Irish Economy since 1922" page="246" place="Liverpool" publisher="Liverpool University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="James" mainName="Meenan" role="author">James Meenan</nameGrp>, <i>The Irish Economy since 1922</i> (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 1970), 246.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-28" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>28</sup></enumerator> Lord Iveagh, the main shareholder in Guinness, had five residences in England and three in the Free State at his death in the 1920s. In a court battle over where taxes were to be paid, his estate claimed England as his permanent domicile (<i>Irish Times</i>, 20 October 1928). That relative tax rates were a factor in Anglo-Irish calculations is explicitly mentioned by <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-29" class="book" author="Robertson, Nora" date="1960" title="Crowned Harp: Memories of the Last&#x00A0;Years of the Crown in Ireland" page="145" place="Dublin" publisher="Allen Figgis and Co" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Nora" mainName="Robertson" role="author">Nora Robertson</nameGrp>, <i>Crowned Harp: Memories of the Last&#x00A0;Years of the Crown in Ireland</i> (Dublin: Allen Figgis and Co., 1960), 145.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-29" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>29</sup></enumerator> The effect of the agreement was that persons resident in the Free State and not in the United Kingdom paid only Irish income tax on their income deriving from both jurisdictions (and vice versa): <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-30" class="book" date="1932" title="Saorst&#x00E1;t &#x00C9;ireann: Irish Free State Official Handbook" page="91" place="Dublin" publisher="Talbot Press" purpose="display"><i>Saorst&#x00E1;t &#x00C9;ireann: Irish Free State Official Handbook</i> (Dublin: Talbot Press, 1932), 91.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-30" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>30</sup></enumerator> These data are charted in Kenny and McLaughlin, &#x2018;The Political Economy of Secession: Lessons from the Early&#x00A0;Years of the Irish Free State&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-31" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>31</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-31" class="journalArticle" author="Johnston, Joseph" date="1939" journalIssue="110" title="An Outlook on Irish Agriculture" journalName="Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review" vol="28" page="195" pageLast="209" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Joseph" mainName="Johnston" role="author">Joseph Johnston</nameGrp>, &#x2018;An Outlook on Irish Agriculture&#x2019;. <i>Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review</i> 28, 110 (1939): 195&#x2013;209.</bibItem> Edward Nevin, &#x2018;The Irish Price Level: A Comparative Study&#x2019;, Economic Research Institute Paper No. 9, 1962.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-32" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>32</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-32" class="book" author="Moynihan, Maurice" date="1975" title="Currency and Central Banking in Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1960" page="20" place="Dublin" publisher="Gill and Macmillan and Central Bank of Ireland" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Maurice" mainName="Moynihan" role="author">Maurice Moynihan</nameGrp>, <i>Currency and Central Banking in Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1960</i> (Dublin: Gill and Macmillan and Central Bank of Ireland, 1975), 20.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-33" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>33</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-33" class="journalArticle" author="Thomas, Ryland|Dimsdale, Nicholas" date="2017" title="A Millennium of Macroeconomic Data for the UK" journalName="Bank of England&#x2019;s Historical Macroeconomic and Financial Statistics: Version" vol="3" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Ryland" mainName="Thomas" role="author">Ryland Thomas</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Nicholas" mainName="Dimsdale" role="author">Nicholas Dimsdale</nameGrp>. &#x2018;A Millennium of Macroeconomic Data for the UK&#x2019;. <i>Bank of England&#x2019;s Historical Macroeconomic and Financial Statistics: Version</i> 3 (2017)</bibItem>: Sheet A47.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-34" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>34</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-34" class="book" author="Clavin, Patricia" date="2000" title="The Great Depression in Europe, 1929&#x2013;1939" page="31" pageLast="33" place="New York" publisher="Macmillan" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Patricia" mainName="Clavin" role="author">Patricia Clavin</nameGrp>, <i>The Great Depression in Europe, 1929&#x2013;1939</i> (New York: Macmillan, 2000), 31&#x2013;33.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-35" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>35</sup></enumerator> Membership of the sterling bloc has been found to have facilitated lower borrowing costs during the troubled interwar period: FitzGerald and Kenny, &#x2018;&#x201C;Till Debt Do Us Part&#x201D;: Financial Implications of the Divorce of the Irish Free State from the United Kingdom, 1922&#x2013;1926&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-36" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>36</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-35" class="journalArticle" author="Honohan, Patrick" date="1997" journalIssue="200" title="Currency Board or Central Bank? Lessons from the Irish Pound&#x2019;s Link with Sterling, 1928&#x2013;79" journalName="Banca Nazionale del Lavoro Quarterly Review" vol="50" page="39" pageLast="67" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Patrick" mainName="Honohan" role="author">Patrick Honohan</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Currency Board or Central Bank? Lessons from the Irish Pound&#x2019;s Link with Sterling, 1928&#x2013;79&#x2019;. <i>Banca Nazionale del Lavoro Quarterly Review</i> 50, 200 (1997): 39&#x2013;67.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-37" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>37</sup></enumerator> Cited in Moynihan, <i>Currency and Central Banking in Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1960</i>, 109.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-38" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>38</sup></enumerator> Honohan, &#x2018;Currency Board or Central Bank?</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-39" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>39</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-36" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Gr&#x00E1;da, Cormac &#x00D3;" partTitle="Money and Banking in the Irish Free State 1921&#x2013;1939" editor="Feinstein, Charles H." date="1995" title="Banking, Currency and Finance in Europe between the Wars" place="Oxford" publisher="Clarendon Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Cormac &#x00D3;" mainName="Gr&#x00e1;da" role="partAuthor">Cormac &#x00D3; Gr&#x00E1;da</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Money and Banking in the Irish Free State 1921&#x2013;1939&#x2019;, in <i>Banking, Currency and Finance in Europe between the Wars</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Charles H." mainName="Feinstein" role="editor">Charles H. Feinstein</nameGrp> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1995), 414&#x2013;33.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-40" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>40</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-37" class="journalArticle" author="FitzGerald, John|Kenny, Se&#x00E1;n" date="2018" title="Managing a Century of Debt" journalName="Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland" vol="48" page="1" pageLast="40" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John" mainName="Fitzgerald" role="author">John FitzGerald</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Se&#x00E1;N" mainName="Kenny" role="author">Se&#x00E1;n Kenny</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Managing a Century of Debt&#x2019;. <i>Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland</i> 48 (2018): 1&#x2013;40.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-41" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>41</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-38" class="book" author="Cullen, Louis M." date="1983" title="Princes &#x0026; Pirates: The Dublin Chamber of Commerce, 1783&#x2013;1983" page="92" place="Dublin" publisher="Dublin Chamber of Commerce" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Louis M." mainName="Cullen" role="author">Louis M. Cullen</nameGrp>, <i>Princes &#x0026; Pirates: The Dublin Chamber of Commerce, 1783&#x2013;1983</i> (Dublin: Dublin Chamber of Commerce, 1983), 92.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-42" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>42</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-39" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Gr&#x00E1;da, Cormac &#x00D3;" partTitle="Irish Agriculture after the Land War" editor="Engerman, Stanley|Metzer, Jacob" date="2004" title="Land Rights, Ethno-nationality and Sovereignty in History" page="131" pageLast="152" place="London" publisher="Routledge" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Cormac &#x00D3;" mainName="Gr&#x00e1;da" role="partAuthor">Cormac &#x00D3; Gr&#x00E1;da</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Irish Agriculture after the Land War&#x2019;, in <i>Land Rights, Ethno-nationality and Sovereignty in History</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Stanley" mainName="Engerman" role="editor">Stanley Engerman</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Jacob" mainName="Metzer" role="editor">Jacob Metzer</nameGrp> (London: Routledge, 2004), 131&#x2013;52.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-43" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>43</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-40" class="book" author="Hooker, Elizabeth R." date="1938" title="Readjustments of Agricultural Tenure in Ireland" page="103" place="Chapel Hill, NC" publisher="University of North Carolina Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Elizabeth R." mainName="Hooker" role="author">Elizabeth R. Hooker</nameGrp>, <i>Readjustments of Agricultural Tenure in Ireland</i> (Chapel Hill, NC: University of North Carolina Press, 1938), 103.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-44" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>44</sup></enumerator> Cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-41" class="book" author="Daly, Mary E." date="2002" title="The First Department: A History of the Department of Agriculture" page="114" place="Dublin" publisher="Institute of Public Administration" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Mary E." mainName="Daly" role="author">Mary E. Daly</nameGrp>, <i>The First Department: A History of the Department of Agriculture</i> (Dublin: Institute of Public Administration, 2002), 114.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-45" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>45</sup></enumerator> Hooker, <i>Readjustments of Agricultural Tenure in Ireland</i>. Land distribution remained hugely divisive into the Fianna F&#x00E1;il era. The decline in smaller land holdings would ultimately be driven primarily by emigration: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-42" class="journalArticle" author="O&#x2019;Donoghue, Cathal" date="2022" title="A Century of Irish Agriculture: A Policy Driven Sector" journalName="Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland" vol="51" page="86" pageLast="127" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Cathal" mainName="O&#x2019;donoghue" role="author">Cathal O&#x2019;Donoghue</nameGrp>, &#x2018;A Century of Irish Agriculture: A Policy Driven Sector&#x2019;. <i>Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland</i> 51 (2022): 86&#x2013;127.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-46" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>46</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-43" class="book" author="Manning, Maurice|McDowell, Moore" date="1984" title="Electricity Supply in Ireland: The History of the ESB" page="37" place="Dublin" publisher="Gill and Macmillan" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Maurice" mainName="Manning" role="author">Maurice Manning</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Moore" mainName="Mcdowell" role="author">Moore McDowell</nameGrp>, <i>Electricity Supply in Ireland: The History of the ESB</i> (Dublin: Gill and Macmillan, 1984), 37.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-47" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>47</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-44" class="journalArticle" author="de Cogan, Dominic" date="2013" journalIssue="2" title="The Wartime Origins of the Irish Corporation Tax" journalName="Irish Journal of Legal Studies" vol="3" page="15" pageLast="32" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Dominic" mainName="de Cogan" role="author">Dominic de Cogan</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Wartime Origins of the Irish Corporation Tax&#x2019;. <i>Irish Journal of Legal Studies</i> 3, 2 (2013): 15&#x2013;32.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-48" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>48</sup></enumerator> <i>Weekly Irish Times</i>, 17 May 1924.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-49" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>49</sup></enumerator> Joseph Brennan, cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-45" class="book" author="Fanning, Ronan" date="1978" title="The Irish Department of Finance, 1922&#x2013;58" page="97" place="Dublin" publisher="Institute of Public Administration" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Ronan" mainName="Fanning" role="partAuthor">Ronan Fanning</nameGrp>, <i>The Irish Department of Finance,</i> 1922&#x2013;58 (Dublin: Institute of Public Administration, 1978), 97.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-50" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>50</sup></enumerator> Banking Commission, <i>Second, Third and Fourth Interim Reports</i> (Dublin: Banking Commission, 1926).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-51" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>51</sup></enumerator> Mary E. Daly, &#x2018;Government Finance for Industry in the Irish Free State: The Trade Loans (Guarantee) Acts&#x2019;. <i>Irish Economic and Social History</i> 11, 1 (1984): 73&#x2013;93.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-52" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>52</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-46" class="book" author="Farmar, Tony" date="2013" title="The Versatile Profession: A History of Accountancy in Ireland since 1850" page="70" place="Dublin" publisher="Chartered Accountants Ireland" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Tony" mainName="Farmar" role="author">Tony Farmar</nameGrp>, <i>The Versatile Profession: A History of Accountancy in Ireland since 1850</i> (Dublin: Chartered Accountants Ireland, 2013), 70.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-53" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>53</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-47" class="journalArticle" author="Browne, R. F." date="1947" title="The Electricity Supply Board" journalName="Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland" page="18" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="R. F." mainName="Browne" role="author">R. F. Browne</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Electricity Supply Board&#x2019;. <i>Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland</i> 18 (1947): 564.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-54" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>54</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-48" class="book" author="Schoen, Lothar" editor="Bielenberg, Andy" date="2002" title="The Shannon Scheme and the Electrification of the Irish Free State" page="28" pageLast="47" place="Dublin" publisher="Lilliput Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Lothar" mainName="Schoen" role="partAuthor">Lothar Schoen</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Irish Free State and the Electricity Industry, 1922&#x2013;1927&#x2019;, in <i>The Shannon Scheme and the Electrification of the Irish Free State</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Andy" mainName="Bielenberg" role="editor">Andy Bielenberg</nameGrp> (Dublin: Lilliput Press, 2002), 28&#x2013;47.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-55" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>55</sup></enumerator> Cromien, &#x2018;Brennan, Joseph&#x2019;; Daly, &#x2018;Government Finance for Industry in the Irish Free State: The Trade Loans (Guarantee) Acts&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-56" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>56</sup></enumerator> Schoen, &#x2018;The Irish Free State and the Electricity Industry, 1922&#x2013;1927&#x2019;, 41.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-57" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>57</sup></enumerator> Manning and McDowell, <i>Electricity Supply in Ireland: The History of the ESB</i>, 37.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-58" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>58</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-49" class="book" author="Schoen, Lothar" date="2002" title="The Shannon Scheme and the Electrification of the Irish Free State" page="28" pageLast="47" place="Dublin" publisher="Lilliput Press" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-48">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 68.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-59" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>59</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 5 and 6 April 1927.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-60" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>60</sup></enumerator> Daly, <i>The First Department: A History of the Department of Agriculture</i>, 129.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-61" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>61</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-50" class="book" author="Fathartaigh, M&#x00ED;che&#x00E1;l &#x00D3;" date="2014" title="Irish Agriculture Nationalised: The Dairy Disposal Company and the Making of the Modern Irish Dairy Industry" place="Dublin" publisher="Institute of Public Administrations" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="M&#x00ED;Che&#x00E1;L &#x00D3;" mainName="Fathartaigh" role="author">M&#x00ED;che&#x00E1;l &#x00D3; Fathartaigh</nameGrp>, <i>Irish Agriculture Nationalised: The Dairy Disposal Company and the Making of the Modern Irish Dairy Industry</i> (Dublin: Institute of Public Administrations, 2014).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-62" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>62</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-51" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Fox, P. F.|Breathnach, Proinnsias" partTitle="Proprietary Creameries in Ireland" date="2014" title="Butter in Ireland: From Earliest Times to the 21st Century" page="96" place="Cork" publisher="Cork Butter Museum" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="P. F." mainName="Fox" role="partAuthor">P. F. Fox</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Proinnsias" mainName="Breathnach" role="partAuthor">Proinnsias Breathnach</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Proprietary Creameries in Ireland&#x2019;, in <i>Butter in Ireland: From Earliest Times to the 21st Century</i>, ed. Peter Foynes, Colin Rynne, and Chris Synnott (Cork: Cork Butter Museum, 2014), 96.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-63" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>63</sup></enumerator> It has not been possible to determine exact employment numbers for the Dairy Disposal Company prior to 1964. The estimates provided for earlier decades are based on the assertion by Smith and Quinn, among others, that it had handled over 20 per cent of manufacturing milk since its establishment: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-52" class="book" author="Smith, Louis P. F.|Quinn, Gerard" date="1975" title="A Study of the Evolution of Concentration in the Irish Food Industry 1968&#x2013;1973" page="16" place="Brussels" publisher="EU Commission" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Louis P. F." mainName="Smith" role="author">Louis P. F. Smith</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Gerard" mainName="Quinn" role="author">Gerard Quinn</nameGrp>, <i>A Study of the Evolution of Concentration in the Irish Food Industry 1968&#x2013;1973</i> (Brussels: EU Commission, 1975), 16.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-64" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>64</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-53" class="journalArticle" author="Daniel, T. K." date="1976" journalIssue="1" title="Griffith on His Noble Head: The Determinants of Cumann na nGaedheal Economic Policy, 1922&#x2013;32" journalName="Irish Economic and Social History" vol="3" page="55" pageLast="65" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="T. K." mainName="Daniel" role="author">T. K. Daniel</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Griffith on His Noble Head: The Determinants of Cumann na nGaedheal Economic Policy, 1922&#x2013;32&#x2019;. <i>Irish Economic and Social History</i> 3, 1 (1976): 55&#x2013;65.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-65" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>65</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-54" class="book" author="Daly, Mary E." date="1992" title="Industrial Development and Irish National Identity, 1922&#x2013;1939" place="New York" publisher="Syracuse University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Mary E." mainName="Daly" role="author">Mary E. Daly</nameGrp>, <i>Industrial Development and Irish National Identity, 1922&#x2013;1939</i> (New York: Syracuse University Press, 1992), 97&#x2013;98.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-div1-4" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004.021.0004">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-titleGroup-4"><title id="C4S3"><p><page id="80" chapter=""/><enumerator>4.3</enumerator> Trade Policy Debate</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C4P39">Tariff policy was the subject of impassioned debate from the foundation of the state. Supporters of free trade included the major exporting firms and sectors such as transport, banking, and trade, which were closely integrated into the British economy. In the case of agriculture, as Meenan notes,</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-displayText-5" class="prosequote">
<p>Farmers could be prosperous only if they were able to export. But precisely because the British market was open to the world, the Irish farmer could compete only if his products were of good quality and capable of being sold at a competitive price. Tariffs, rates and taxes had to be kept as low as possible.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-66"><sup>66</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C4P40">Following some dissension within the ranks of smaller Irish manufacturers, the Dublin Industrial Development Association had joined the Federation of Irish Industries in endorsing protection in 1924.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-67"><sup>67</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The republican parties&#x2014;Sinn F&#x00E9;in and later Fianna F&#x00E1;il&#x2014;were strongly supportive, while Cumann na nGaedheal, as an alliance born solely of acceptance of the Treaty, was divided on the issue, as the Irish Parliamentary Party had been.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-68"><sup>68</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P41">A Fiscal Inquiry Committee was appointed by the Executive Council in June 1923 to report on the effects of existing or proposed trade restrictions.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-69"><sup>69</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Four of its five members were university economists. It heard evidence from interested parties in over forty sessions held between July and September 1923, though few of the larger export-oriented firms made submissions. In its final report, the Committee concluded that the volume of industry keen to obtain a protective tariff was small. Most of the industries seeking protection were described as &#x2018;debilitated&#x2019; rather than of the infant-industry type that underlay the analysis of German economist Friedrich List, who had been a major influence on Arthur Griffith.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-70"><sup>70</sup></xref></xrefGrp> It also pointed to the adverse impact it would have on consumers and on the cost base of exporting industries. Presciently, it also warned that the new vested interests that protectionism would create would make it difficult to reverse course later.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-71"><sup>71</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P42">In his subsequent discussions with Ernest Blythe, the Minister for Finance, McElligott argued:</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-displayText-6" class="prosequote">
<p><page id="81" chapter=""/>The largest element in costs is wages and wages depend largely on the cost of living, which is always high in protected countries. The best way we can help [manufacturers] is to bring down, say, charges for transport and power [.&#x00A0;.&#x00A0;.] Better organisation, better marketing etc., are matters independent of protection and the incentive to them is often removed by protection.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-72"><sup>72</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C4P43">The protectionist voice diminished within the pro-Treaty camp over the course of the decade. Two supporters of the Griffith approach&#x2014;Defence Minister Richard Mulcahy and Minister for Industry and Commerce Joseph McGrath&#x2014;left the cabinet in the aftermath of the Army Mutiny of 1924, though Mulcahy returned in 1927. A memo from Gordon Campbell suggesting fifteen industries that could be protected without impacting on the cost of living was withdrawn on the resignation of McGrath.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-73"><sup>73</sup></xref></xrefGrp> J. J. Walsh, the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs, complained of the government&#x2019;s pandering to &#x2018;ranchers and importers&#x2019;. He publicly supported Fianna F&#x00E1;il in the 1932 general election.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-74"><sup>74</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Se&#x00E1;n Milroy, a founder of the Irish Protectionist League, resigned from the party along with McGrath, accusing ministers of relying on civil servants whose loyalties, if not pro-British, were controlled by the Freemasons.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-75"><sup>75</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The standing committee of the party agreed, branding those in the Department of Finance as &#x2018;alien and anti-Irish&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-76"><sup>76</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P44">The conclusions of the Fiscal Inquiry Committee were not accepted in their entirety by government however. W. T. Cosgrave, President of the Executive Council, had stated at the outset that &#x2018;the Committee is not expected to advocate policy. That will be a matter for the people and the government when they have the facts before them.&#x2019;<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-77"><sup>77</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Blythe announced in the D&#x00E1;il in 1924:</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-displayText-7" class="prosequote">
<p>[While not prepared] to recommend anything approaching a general tariff with the substantial rise in the cost of living which would inevitably follow [.&#x00A0;.&#x00A0;.] neither are we prepared to let the industrial drift continue, and content themselves with preaching efficiency and the virtues.</p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C4P45"><page id="82" chapter=""/>It was decided to &#x2018;impose certain duties which will give us a limited but sufficient experiment in the use of a tariff for the stimulation of Irish industry&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-78"><sup>78</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P46">Tariffs were imposed in the Finance Act of 1924 on a range of items including boots and shoes, soap and candles, sugar confectionary, cocoa preparations, and glass bottles. The duty on tea was reduced in order to counteract the impact on the cost of living.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-79"><sup>79</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Duties on tea, coffee, and cocoa were abolished completely in 1925 in conjunction with the announcement of further tariffs on apparel, woollen textiles, and furniture. University College Dublin economist George O&#x2019;Brien, who had served on the Fiscal Inquiry Committee, noted that &#x2018;protection is a costly process but [.&#x00A0;.&#x00A0;.] the result may be worth the cost [.&#x00A0;.&#x00A0;.] The mischief begins when people deceive themselves into the belief that protection is a method of getting something for nothing.&#x2019;<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-80"><sup>80</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P47">Though the Department of Agriculture remained solidly anti-protectionist, farmers joined the campaign for protection in 1926 as agricultural prices fell and bad weather persisted.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-81"><sup>81</sup></xref></xrefGrp> An experimental duty on oatmeal was imposed in 1926, and a Tariff Commission was established later that year. Presumably to avoid being directly importuned by those seeking protection, Industry and Commerce accepted that the Minister for Finance be granted sole power to refer applications to the Commission and to nominate both the secretary and chairman. McElligott considered that it was &#x2018;the duty of the Department of Finance to see that the time of the Tariff Commission is not wasted in examining a particular proposal unless there appears, <i>prima facie</i>, to be a case that is worthy of consideration&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-82"><sup>82</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P48">From August 1927, when they entered the D&#x00E1;il, Fianna F&#x00E1;il subjected the Commission to constant criticism. Lemass complained about the time taken to prepare its reports and the waste of time and money in making submissions to a body that he suggested was likely to prove doctrinaire in its opposition. In providing a forum for opposition to tariffs to be voiced, the Commission adopted a more holistic view than similar bodies in Britain and the Commonwealth.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-83"><sup>83</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Its reports are described by Meenan as &#x2018;models of clarity&#x2019; and commended for their awareness of &#x2018;the many links that bind even the most dissimilar industries to one another&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-84"><sup>84</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Of the fourteen reports issued by <page id="83" chapter=""/>the Commission between its establishment and the general election of 1932, ten nevertheless adjudicated in favour of tariffs.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-85"><sup>85</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The government, meanwhile, sought to remove some of the disabilities of Irish industry through the provision of electric power and by means of low taxation.</p>
<p id="C4P49">From 1930, with the onset of the Great Depression, the potential for import substitution began to be looked at more closely. Agriculture&#x2019;s opposition weakened as export volumes and output prices fell and other agricultural exporters began to target the UK market more aggressively.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-86"><sup>86</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The global downturn prompted Cosgrave to announce the establishment of a permanent Tariff Commission in late 1930. All five of the reports of the reconstituted Commission&#x2014;on butter, bacon, oats, linen goods, and certain categories of leather&#x2014;granted protection within&#x00A0;months of the applications for tariffs being submitted.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-87"><sup>87</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P50">In November 1931, following the election of a protectionist government in Britain, the Executive Council took powers under the Customs Duties (Provisional Imposition) Act to impose such duties as it might decide were &#x2018;immediately necessary to prevent an expected dumping of goods or other threatened industrial injury&#x2019;. The first batch of duties was imposed in late November.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-88"><sup>88</sup></xref></xrefGrp> This Act, similar to those adopted elsewhere around this time, was seen as a response to temporary abnormal circumstances and was intended to operate only for nine months. It was used sparingly during the remainder of Cumann na nGaedheal&#x2019;s period in office. The political environment would change dramatically with the formation of the first Fianna F&#x00E1;il government in 1932.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-66" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>66</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-55" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Meenan, James" partTitle="From Free Trade to Self-Sufficiency" editor="MacManus, Francis" date="1967" title="The Years of the Great Test 1926&#x2013;39" page="69" pageLast="79" place="Cork" publisher="Mercier Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="James" mainName="Meenan" role="partAuthor">James Meenan</nameGrp>, &#x2018;From Free Trade to Self-Sufficiency&#x2019;, in <i>The Years of the Great Test 1926&#x2013;39</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Francis" mainName="Macmanus" role="editor">Francis MacManus</nameGrp> (Cork: Mercier Press, 1967), 69&#x2013;79.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-67" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>67</sup></enumerator> Daly, <i>Industrial Development and Irish National Identity</i>, 22&#x2013;23.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-68" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>68</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-56" class="book" author="McConnell, James" date="2013" title="The Irish Parliamentary Party and the Third Home Rule Crisis" place="Dublin" publisher="Four Courts Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="James" mainName="Mcconnell" role="author">James McConnell</nameGrp>, <i>The Irish Parliamentary Party and the Third Home Rule Crisis</i> (Dublin: Four Courts Press, 2013),</bibItem> <xrefGrp>ch. <xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-10">10</xref></xrefGrp>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-69" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>69</sup></enumerator> <i>PDDE</i>, 15 June 1923.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-70" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>70</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-57" class="book" author="Fiscal Inquiry Committee" date="1923" title="Final Report" place="Dublin" publisher="Stationery Office" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Fiscal Inquiry Committee">Fiscal Inquiry Committee</nameGrp>, Final Report (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1923)</bibItem>, para. 96; Daniel, &#x2018;Griffith on His Noble Head: The Determinants of Cumann na nGaedheal Economic Policy, 1922&#x2013;32&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-71" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>71</sup></enumerator> Fiscal Inquiry Committee, Final Report para. 124.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-72" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>72</sup></enumerator> Memorandum from McElligott to Blythe, September 1923, cited in Devlin and Barry, &#x2018;Protection versus Free Trade in the Free State Era: The Finance Attitude&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-73" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>73</sup></enumerator> Campbell to McElligott, 3 March 1924, cited in Girvin, <i>Between Two Worlds: Politics and Economy in Independent Ireland</i>, 33.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-74" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>74</sup></enumerator> Patrick Maume, &#x2018;Walsh, James Joseph&#x2019;, in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-58" class="book" date="2009" title="Dictionary of Irish Biography" place="Cambridge" publisher="Cambridge University Press" purpose="display"><i>Dictionary of Irish Biography</i> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009)</bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-75" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>75</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-59" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Regan, John M." partTitle="The Politics of Utopia: Party Organisation, Executive Autonomy and the New Administration" editor="Cronin, Mike|Regan, John M" date="2000" title="Ireland: the Politics of Independence" page="40" place="New York" publisher="St Martin&#x2019;s Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John M." mainName="Regan" role="partAuthor">John M. Regan</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Politics of Utopia: Party Organisation, Executive Autonomy and the New Administration&#x2019;, in <i>Ireland: the Politics of Independence</i> ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Mike" mainName="Cronin" role="editor">Mike Cronin</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="John M" mainName="Regan" role="editor">John M Regan</nameGrp> (New York: St Martin&#x2019;s Press, 2000), 40.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-76" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>76</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-60" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Regan, John M." partTitle="The Politics of Utopia: Party Organisation, Executive Autonomy and the New Administration" editor="Cronin, Mike|Regan, John M" date="2000" title="Ireland: the Politics of Independence" page="40" place="New York" publisher="St Martin&#x2019;s Press" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-59">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 47&#x2013;49.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-77" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>77</sup></enumerator> <i>PDDE</i>, 15 June 1923.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-78" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>78</sup></enumerator> <i>PDDE</i>, 25 April 1924.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-79" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>79</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-61" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Regan, John M." partTitle="The Politics of Utopia: Party Organisation, Executive Autonomy and the New Administration" editor="Cronin, Mike|Regan, John M" date="2000" title="Ireland: the Politics of Independence" page="40" place="New York" publisher="St Martin&#x2019;s Press" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-59">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-80" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>80</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-62" class="journalArticle" author="O&#x2019;Brien, George" date="1925" journalIssue="54" title="The Budget" journalName="Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review" vol="14" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="George" mainName="O&#x2019;brien" role="author">George O&#x2019;Brien</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Budget&#x2019;. <i>Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review</i> 14, 54 (1925).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-81" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>81</sup></enumerator> Daly, <i>Industrial Development and Irish National Identity</i>, 27.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-82" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>82</sup></enumerator> McElligott to Blythe, 22 October 1926, cited in Girvin, <i>Between Two Worlds: Politics and Economy in Independent Ireland</i>, 37&#x2013;38.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-83" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>83</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-63" class="unclassified" author="Ryan, Louden" date="1949" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Louden" mainName="Ryan" role="author">Louden Ryan</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Nature and Effects of Protective Policy in Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1939&#x2019;. Ph.D. thesis, Trinity College Dublin, 1949, 42&#x2013;50.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-84" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>84</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-64" class="journalArticle" author="Meenan, James" date="1943" title="Irish Industry and Industrial Policy 1921&#x2013;1943" journalName="Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review" page="209" pageLast="218" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="James" mainName="Meenan" role="author">James Meenan</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Irish Industry and Industrial Policy 1921&#x2013;1943&#x2019;. <i>Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review</i> (1943): 209&#x2013;18.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-85" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>85</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-65" class="unclassified" author="Ryan" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Ryan">Ryan</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Nature and Effects of Protective Policy in Ireland&#x2019;, 41&#x2013;42.</bibItem> Daly notes that the number of applications is likely to have far exceeded the number of reports issued: Daly, <i>Industrial Development and Irish National Identity</i>, 39&#x2013;41.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-86" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>86</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-66" class="unclassified" author="Ryan" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-65">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 56.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-87" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>87</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-67" class="unclassified" author="Ryan" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-65">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 46.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-88" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>88</sup></enumerator> <i>PDDE</i>, 4 November1931.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-div1-5" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004.021.0005">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-titleGroup-5"><title id="C4S4"><p><enumerator>4.4</enumerator> Sectoral and Firm-Level Consequences of Selective Protection</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C4P51">The first Irish tariffs, which came into effect with the establishment of a customs frontier in April 1923, duplicated those of Britain. The most significant of these in the Irish case were the duties on manufactured tobacco and on motor vehicles and parts. Employment in tobacco manufacturing quadrupled over the next three years. Though tariff announcements were generally followed by a rush to import stocks, the experimental tariffs introduced in 1924 <page id="84" chapter=""/>and 1925 also had an immediate impact on output and employment, as is evident from contemporary newspaper reports. By 1930, there had been a marked decline in imports of most of the tariffed items other than footwear, and more than 100 new factories had been opened in the newly protected sectors.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-89"><sup>89</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P52">The first Census of Industrial Production (CIP) was produced for 1926. The data in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-1">4.1</xref></xrefGrp> suggest that some 9,000 jobs had already been created in sectors that had been tariffed by that date. Though partly a consequence of recovery (rather than solely of protection), this was a far from inconsiderable achievement.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-90"><sup>90</sup></xref></xrefGrp> By 1930, a further 4,000 jobs had been added in these sectors.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-91"><sup>91</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-1"?></p>
<p id="C4P53">By contrast, only 400 jobs had been added by 1930 in the sectors that had been tariffed <i>since</i> 1926, suggesting that the lowest-hanging fruit had been picked first.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-92"><sup>92</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The most effective of the tariffs were those on consumer products. The 1924 tariff on glass bottles was set at too low a level to resuscitate the industry as it had met with strong resistance from the drinks producers, jam makers and chemists for whom bottles represented a significant cost. The 1929 tariff on woollen and worsted textiles was vigorously opposed by clothing producers.</p>
<p id="C4P54">An issue that had yet to be resolved concerned the policy to be adopted towards British firms that established operations behind the tariff wall. Most of the substantial UK firms that commenced production in the Free State in the 1920s and 1930s already had experience of operating &#x2018;tariff factories&#x2019; in other Commonwealth countries.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-93"><sup>93</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Within a&#x00A0;year of the establishment of the customs frontier, three constituent firms of the Imperial Tobacco Company&#x2014;Players, Wills, and pipe tobacco and snuff producer William Clarke &#x0026; Son&#x2014;had opened factories in Dublin. As the same tariff was automatically levied on goods shipped in the opposite direction, indigenous tobacco manufacturer P. J. Carroll &#x0026; Co. opened a plant in Liverpool to protect its British and cross-border sales. Two Northern Irish tobacco firms, <page id="85" chapter=""/>Murray &#x0026; Sons and Gallahers, would also commence operations in Dublin over the next several years.</p>
<p id="C4P55">Government minister J. J. Walsh was particularly vocal in his opposition to the entry of external firms because of the detrimental impact this would have on their domestic competitors.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-94"><sup>94</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Goodbody Tobacco had taken on an extra 100 workers in 1923. It ceased production in 1929. Fianna F&#x00E1;il would seek to <page id="86" chapter=""/>address the issue through the Control of Manufactures Acts of 1932 and 1934. Gallahers would close its plant in 1932 when the new Fianna F&#x00E1;il government imposed a discriminatory duty on raw tobacco imports by firms established since 1922. (The government claimed that the aim of the policy was to protect small firms rather than specifically indigenous enterprises.) Three hundred workers &#x2013; many of them former Goodbody employees &#x2013; lost their jobs with the closure of the Gallaher plant, which caused the first serious rift between the new Fianna F&#x00E1;il administration and its Labour Party allies.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-95"><sup>95</sup></xref></xrefGrp> As the main domestic rival to Players&#x2013;Wills, Carrolls would expand significantly over the following decades. Its workforce increased to 400 by 1934 and would exceed 500 from the early 1950s.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-2"?></p>
<p id="C4P56">The other major tariff that came into effect automatically with the establishment of a customs frontier was on motor vehicles and parts. This raised a dilemma for government. Ford has ceased tractor production with the collapse of the agricultural boom in 1920, and the Cork plant had been repurposed to produce parts for the company&#x2019;s vehicle assembly plant in Manchester. Ford&#x2019;s trade with the United Kingdom would now be subject to tariffs. It appeared likely that an agreement could be secured to have the charges on trade between the jurisdictions waived. Ford&#x2019;s refusal to commit to remaining in Cork however meant that the loss in tariff revenue on imported cars dominated government considerations and the potential agreement was not pursued. Employment at the Cork plant fluctuated massively over the decade. It reached a high of 7,000 in 1929 when tractor production resumed, but 6,000 were laid off the following&#x00A0;year as a consequence of the Great Depression.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-96"><sup>96</sup></xref></xrefGrp> A decision by the company to close the Cork plant was reversed when the new Fianna F&#x00E1;il government banned the importation of fully assembled vehicles.</p>
<p id="C4P57">Details of some of the firm-level developments in tobacco and other sectors impacted by the tariffs of the early Cumann na nGaedheal&#x00A0;years are provided in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-2">4.2</xref></xrefGrp>. The tariff on confectionery products introduced in 1924 was regarded by the Cosgrave administration as the most successful of its protectionist experiments. Its introduction has been credited to the influence of Joseph Milroy, proprietor of the recently established Dublin Confectionery Works and brother of one of the TDs who had resigned from Cumann na nGaedheal over the government&#x2019;s reluctance to introduce more thoroughgoing protectionist policies. Within a&#x00A0;year of the tariff, Williams &#x0026; Woods, the largest confectionery firm, had taken on &#x2018;from 400 to 500 <page id="87" chapter=""/><page id="88" chapter=""/>extra hands&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-97"><sup>97</sup></xref></xrefGrp> It was acquired by UK firm Crosse &#x0026; Blackwell in 1928. Williams &#x0026; Woods would remain a major employer through to 1972. Other British firms to establish behind the tariff barrier included Mackintosh, which acquired NKM in 1925, and Rowntree, which acquired Savoy Cocoa the following year. The firms would operate in partnership in Ireland under the aegis of Associated Chocolate and Confectionery from 1931. Clarnico-Murray opened a factory in Dublin in 1926. Scottish jam maker R. &#x0026; W. Scott followed in 1927.</p>
<p id="C4P58">New indigenous firms established in the wake of the tariff included Liam Devlin&#x2019;s Blue Badge Cream Toffee in Dublin and Oatfield Sweets in Letterkenny, County Donegal. Urney Chocolates&#x2014;named for the parish in West Tyrone where the business was started in 1917&#x2014;shifted production to Tallaght in 1924 following a fire at its Northern Ireland factory. Urney would become a major employer and would acquire Devlins and a number of other smaller firms before itself being acquired by US firm W. R. Grace &#x0026; Co. in 1963. Employment at the Shannon Confectionery Works expanded from 30 to 120 over the next few years. Inchicore jam producer Lambs diversified into sweets. Lemons opened a new factory in Drumcondra.</p>
<p id="C4P59">There were rapid employment increases also in ready-made clothing, shirt making, and furniture. Of the sixteen new ready-made tailoring factories established in 1925 and 1926, the most significant were Lee Clothing in Cork (part of the Dwyer family group), Belfast firm Wilson and McBrinn in Drogheda, and two Leeds firms: Montague Burton in Dublin and Taylor &#x0026; Co. in Dundalk.</p>
<p id="C4P60">Sixteen new shirt factories opened over this two-year period, the majority of them in Donegal. Most were Northern Ireland firms. These included the Foyle Shirt and Collar factory in Lifford, Tillie &#x0026; Henderson (&#x00C9;ire) in Carndonagh, and A. B. Grant and McCloskey and Co. in Buncrana. Some Northern Ireland shirtmakers outsourced work to Derry firm Porter and Co., which was already in operation in Castlefin. The Donegal factories generally employed a workforce of 100 or so. Shirt making remained concentrated in Dublin, where much of the work was conducted in-house in Pim Brothers, Todd, Burns and Co., and other department stores.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-98"><sup>98</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P61">The major development in soap products was the opening by Lever Bros of the Castle Forbes works on Dublin&#x2019;s Sheriff Street in 1927, into which the old Dublin soap manufacturer Barringtons was integrated.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-99"><sup>99</sup></xref></xrefGrp> New hosiery firms <page id="89" chapter=""/>included Sunbeam in Cork and W. P. McCarter &#x0026; Co. in Buncrana. Sunbeam would go on to become a massive employer throughout the period to EEC accession. McCarter would rise to prominence in the 1980s as producer of the US brand &#x2018;Fruit of the Loom&#x2019;. Martin Mahony built a new hosiery factory in Blarney. Greenmount and Boyne expanded into blouses and lingerie. The corset maker alluded to in the sectoral statistics was British firm Leethem and Co., which established in Dublin in 1925.</p>
<p id="C4P62">There were also substantial developments in footwear. Within a&#x00A0;year of the tariff, employment at Lee Boot, one of the Dwyer family companies, expanded from 200 working primarily part-time to 300 working full-time.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-100"><sup>100</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The Dwyers also established a new women&#x2019;s footwear firm, Hanover Shoes. Within a&#x00A0;year of its opening in 1925, it had a workforce of 150. The firms would merge to form Lee Footwear in 1965. The Dwyers had been strong lobbyists for protection and all of their various operations&#x2014;in clothing, shirt making, and footwear&#x2014;expanded as a consequence of the policies adopted. Hosiery and knitwear producer Sunbeam was established by a younger generation of the family.</p>
<p id="C4P63">Leeds firm Halliday, which specialized in heavy agricultural boots, transferred production to Dundalk in 1928. It would enter into an agreement to produce for Clarks Shoes in 1938, when the market for its boots contracted with the growing popularity of rubber wellingtons. The agreement formed part of Clark&#x2019;s efforts to circumvent the restrictions imposed by the Control of Manufactures Acts that Fianna F&#x00E1;il would introduce in the 1930s.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-101"><sup>101</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P64">The final major episode of foreign direct investment of the Cumann na nGaedheal era was the acquisition of the Bannatyne&#x2013;Goodbody milling group by UK firm Ranks in 1930. Proposals for a tariff on flour had been rejected on the grounds that it might induce Jacobs to shift further production to the United Kingdom.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-102"><sup>102</sup></xref></xrefGrp> It was clear however that some form of intervention was in the offing. The acquisition proved timely as British and Irish millers responded to overcapacity by forming a cartel in 1931, which gave Irish-based producers a disproportionate share of the market. Imports of flour other than under licence would be banned in 1933.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-103"><sup>103</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Resolutions objecting to the industry passing into foreign hands were passed by a number of local authorities.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-104"><sup>104</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P65">The extent of &#x2018;tariff jumping&#x2019; by British firms was stronger than anticipated, and the Department of Industry and Commerce shared some of the <page id="90" chapter=""/>concerns expressed by the Cumann na nGaedheal Minister J. J. Walsh and by the opposition Fianna F&#x00E1;il party at these developments. An analysis prepared by the department in October 1928 noted how, by the sale of domestic firms in protected sectors, &#x2018;the owners turned into cash for their own pocket the concession which they, in common with other firms in the industry, were given by the state on national grounds&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-105"><sup>105</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Departmental officials recommended that the minister be empowered to prohibit such transfers or to approve them only after the increased value had been surrendered to the state. Though the report expressed doubt &#x2018;that the economic penetration which had followed on the wake of protection here had yet attained the dimension of a national evil&#x2019;, it was feared that foreign staff might retain the key positions within such companies and that further tariff-driven industrial expansion might see &#x2018;effective control in the new industrial enterprises [.&#x00A0;.&#x00A0;.] pass to outside concerns&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-106"><sup>106</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C4P66">Se&#x00E1;n Lemass, who was shortly to become Minister for Industry and Commerce in the new Fianna F&#x00E1;il administration, had stated in 1927 that &#x2018;unless we can ensure that the benefits derived from the imposition of protection are reserved for the Irish manufacturers as well as the consumers it is a dangerous policy to embark on protection&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-107"><sup>107</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Given Fianna F&#x00E1;il&#x2019;s commitment to import substitution, it is no surprise that legislation to control foreign ownership would be among the first matters to be addressed by the department under the new dispensation.</p>
<p id="C4P67">Another unanticipated consequence of the tariffs of the 1920s and beyond was the share of the resulting jobs that went to women.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-108"><sup>108</sup></xref></xrefGrp> This aroused disquiet among politicians and male trade union leaders and clauses would be introduced in the 1936 Conditions of Employment Act granting the Minister (Lemass) the power to ban women from certain areas of employment and to impose gender quotas on industries. Mary Daly characterizes the act as &#x2018;otherwise a progressive piece of legislation guaranteeing workers holidays with pay and regulating overtime, shift-work and night-work&#x2019;. Noting that there is no evidence of efforts being made to enforce the clauses relating to women, she suggests that their inclusion may have been &#x2018;a cynical political response to popular pressure&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-109"><sup>109</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-89" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>89</sup></enumerator> <i>Saorst&#x00E1;t &#x00C9;ireann: Irish Free State Official Handbook</i>, 143.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-90" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>90</sup></enumerator> A figure of 9,000 new jobs was reported in the <i>Irish Times</i> of 11 December 1926, though the total has been calculated on a somewhat different basis here.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-91" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>91</sup></enumerator> The CIP reports that manufacturing employment increased by 6,000 between 1926 and 1929, with job gains in tariffed sectors thought to have exceeded job losses in other areas (Daly, <i>Industrial Development and Irish National Identity</i>, 77). While coverage of the CIP may have improved over these years, the scope of the 1929 census actually narrowed. The preliminary figures for 1926 reported in the <i>Irish Trade Journal</i> were revised in line with those for 1929 when the censuses were published jointly in 1933 (CIP, 1926 and 1929, vi).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-92" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>92</sup></enumerator> <i>Saorst&#x00E1;t &#x00C9;ireann: Irish Free State Official Handbook</i>, 142.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-93" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>93</sup></enumerator> These included Imperial Tobacco (which operated as British American Tobacco beyond the former UK), Rowntree, Cadbury, and Dunlop, as well as less prominent firms such as Wilson and McBrinn.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-94" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>94</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 12 May 1923; Daly, <i>Industrial Development and Irish National Identity</i>, 35&#x2013;36.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-95" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>95</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, June 11, 1932.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-96" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>96</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 7 March 1929; <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-68" class="unclassified" author="Grimes, Thomas" date="2008" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Thomas" mainName="Grimes" role="author">Thomas Grimes</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Starting Ireland on the Road to Industry: Henry Ford in Cork&#x2019;. Unpublished Ph.D. thesis, National University of Ireland, Maynooth, 2008, 125.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-97" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>97</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 17 April 1925.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-98" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>98</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Trade Journal</i>, January 1927, 57.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-99" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>99</sup></enumerator> Unilever archives: GB1752.IRE&#x2014;Unilever Ireland (Holdings) Ltd and Subsidiary Companies (GB1752.IRE/JB); <i>Irish Independent</i>, 8 July 1927, 9.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-100" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>100</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 17 April 1925.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-101" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>101</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-69" class="book" author="Press, Jon" date="1989" title="The Footwear Industry in Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1973" page="70" place="Dublin" publisher="Irish Academic Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Jon" mainName="Press" role="author">Jon Press</nameGrp>, <i>The Footwear Industry in Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1973</i> (Dublin: Irish Academic Press, 1989), 70.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-102" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>102</sup></enumerator> <i>Manchester Guardian</i>, 12 May 1928.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-103" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>103</sup></enumerator> Daly, <i>Industrial Development and Irish National Identity</i>, 49, 50, 94.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-104" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>104</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 7 March 1930.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-105" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>105</sup></enumerator> Cited in Girvin, <i>Between Two Worlds: Politics and Economy in Independent Ireland</i>, 67.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-106" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>106</sup></enumerator> Cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-70" class="book" author="Press, Jon" date="1989" title="The Footwear Industry in Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1973" page="70" place="Dublin" publisher="Irish Academic Press" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-69">ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 68.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-107" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>107</sup></enumerator> Cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-71" class="journalArticle" author="Daly, Mary E." date="1984" journalIssue="94" title="An Irish-Ireland for Business?: The Control of Manufactures Acts, 1932 and 1934" journalName="Irish Historical Studies" vol="24" page="252" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Mary E." mainName="Daly" role="author">Mary E. Daly</nameGrp>, &#x2018;An Irish-Ireland for Business?: The Control of Manufactures Acts, 1932 and 1934&#x2019;. <i>Irish Historical Studies</i> 24, 94 (1984): 252.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-108" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>108</sup></enumerator> Daly, <i>Industrial Development and Irish National Identity</i>, 123&#x2013;126.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-109" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>109</sup></enumerator> Mary E. Daly, &#x2018;Women in the Irish Free State, 1922&#x2013;39: The Interaction between Economics and Ideology&#x2019;, <i>Journal of Women&#x0027;s History</i> 7, 1 (1995), 99&#x2013;116.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-floatGroup-1">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004.007.0001" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-table-1" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-titleGroup-6"><title id="C4T1"><p><enumerator>Table 4.1</enumerator> Employment in 1926 and 1930 in sectors tariffed by 1926</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Industry</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Date of tariff</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Full-time employment equivalent at date of tariff</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Employment in September/ October 1926</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>Employment on 1 September 1930</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Manufactured tobacco</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1923</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>500&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>2,096&#x2020;&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>2,081&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Footwear</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1924</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>250&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>967&#x2020;&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>1,227&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Glass bottles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1924</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>25&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>127&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>193&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Soap and candles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1924</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>230&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>410&#x2020;&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>620&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Confectionery, jams, and biscuits<sup>*</sup></p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1924</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>3,400&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>5,051&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>5,367&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Wholesale clothing: men&#x2019;s and boy&#x2019;s factory-made clothing, hats, caps, ties, and umbrellas</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1925</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>805&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>2,290&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>3,733&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Shirt making</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1925</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>410&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>1,572&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>1,844&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Hosiery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1925</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>500&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>849&#x2020;&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>1,354&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Blanket making</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1925</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>130&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>548&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>462&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Furniture, including brush making and metallic bedsteads</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1925</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>444&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>1,274&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>2,010&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Corset making</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1925</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>&#x2013;&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>83&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>n.a.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Oatmeal</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1 April 1926</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>250&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>500&#x2020;&#x2020;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>544&#x2020;</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Total employment</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>6,944</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>15,767</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>19,435</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Sources</i>: &#x2020;<i>Saorst&#x00E1;t Eireann Irish Free State Official Handbook</i> (Dublin: Talbot Press, 1932), 142; &#x2020;&#x2020;&#x2018;Protection in Free State&#x2019;, <i>Irish Times</i>, 11 December 1926 (based on results reported in various issues of the <i>Irish Trade Journal</i>); &#x2020;&#x2020;&#x2020;CIP, 1926; <sup>*</sup>: the numbers provided for the confectionary sector differ from those reported in the CIP as biscuits were also included (<i>Irish Trade Journal</i>, August 1928, 139).</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-2" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004.007.0002" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-table-2" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-titleGroup-7"><title id="C4T2"><p><enumerator>Table 4.2</enumerator> Selected firms established/acquired as a result of the tariffs of 1923&#x2013;1926</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Sector</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Firm and date of establishment or acquisition</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Nationality</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Employment</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Tobacco</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Imperial Tobacco (1923)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>1,500 (1928), major employer (to 1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Murray and Co. (1925)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 100</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Gallaher Tobacco (1931)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>300 (1932)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Confectionery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Williams &#x0026; Woods (acquired by Crosse &#x0026; Blackwell, 1928)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK from 1928</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>477 (1924), 900 (1926), remains &#x2265;500 (to 1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Savoy Cocoa (Rowntree from 1926)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK from 1926</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>150 (1923), &#x003E; 500 (from 1932)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>NKM (Mackintosh from 1925)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK from 1925</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>100 (1922), 200&#x2013;300 from mid-1920s; in partnership with Rowntree from 1931</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Clarnico&#x2013;Murray (1926)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>200&#x2013;300</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>R. &#x0026; W. Scott (1927)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>200&#x2013;300</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Urney Chocolates (1924)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>250 (1929, 1939), &#x003E;500 (from 1960)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Blue Badge Cream Toffee (Devlin&#x2019;s) (1924)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>100&#x2013;200; acquired by Urney (1960)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Oatfield Sweets (McKinney&#x2019;s) (1927)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 100</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Clothing</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Wilson &#x0026; McBrinn (1926)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>200 (1927), 250 (1932), 300 (1939), 400 (1960, 1966)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Montague Burton (1927)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 300</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Taylor &#x0026; Co. (1925)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>150 (1936), 200 (1953)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Corsets</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Leethem and Co. (1925)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>66 (1926), 100 (1929), 300 (1936), 225 (1966)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Hosiery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Sunbeam (1928)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>200 (1931), 250 (1933), &#x003E;500 (from 1935)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>W. P. McCarter &#x0026; Co. (1931)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>200 (1937), 300 (1958)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Soap and candles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Castle Forbes Soap Factory (Lever Bros) (1927)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>300 (1929), 350 (1935), 400 (1961), 500 (1971)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Footwear</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Halliday (1928)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>100 (1928), 200 (1933), 300 (1934), 360 (1941), &#x003E;500 (from 1946)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Hanover Shoes (Dwyer family) (1925)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>150 (1926), 200 (1962)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-div1-6" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004.021.0006">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-titleGroup-8"><title id="C4S5"><p><page id="91" chapter=""/><enumerator>4.5</enumerator> Largest Manufacturing Employers of 1929</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C4P68">The CIP reveals that &#x2013; excluding the railway engineering works &#x2013; there were nine manufacturing establishments employing 500 workers or more in 1929.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-110"><sup>110</sup></xref></xrefGrp> There were, in addition, at least a further six multi-establishment firms employing a workforce of this size. These firms, along with a number of others employing close to this figure, are listed in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-3">4.3</xref></xrefGrp>.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-3"?></p>
<p id="C4P69">Even by 1929, four of the five largest firms were foreign-owned. These included Guinness, whose registered office had been in London since 1886, though the daily management of the company was overseen in Dublin. Players&#x2013;Wills and Crosse &#x0026; Blackwell were tariff-jumping operations. The takeover by Ranks of Bannatyne and Co. in 1930 might be considered an example of &#x2018;precautionary&#x2019; tariff jumping. Among the firms with workforces of 500 or more, around half of the jobs were in foreign-owned companies. It is known both from the international evidence and from later Irish data that foreign companies are strongly over-represented in the larger firm-size and establishment-size categories. An educated guess as to the foreign share across all of industry in 1929 might be in the region of 20 per cent.</p>
<p id="C4P70">The foreign share would have been lower in 1926 when Ford employed a substantially smaller workforce and Williams &#x0026; Woods had not yet been acquired. The share would have been lower still in 1922, prior to the opening of the British-owned tobacco factories in Dublin. Guinness and Ford, along with Furness &#x0026; Withy (UK owners of Rushbrooke Dockyard), were the sole foreign-owned enterprises employing workforces of 500 or more at independence.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-111"><sup>111</sup></xref></xrefGrp> This might suggest a foreign share of perhaps 15 per cent at the time, slightly higher than the 10 per cent suggested as an upper bound in previous research.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-112"><sup>112</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-110" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>110</sup></enumerator> Players&#x2013;Wills was a multi-establishment firm but is included in the single-establishment category in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-3">4.3</xref></xrefGrp> as the South Circular Road factory employed well in excess of 500 by this time. Wills had moved from Marrowbone Lane to the William Clarke site when the firms integrated in 1928. Players would remain in Glasnevin until the 1960s when it too moved to the South Circular Road site. The figure in the table includes employment at all of these establishments.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-111" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>111</sup></enumerator> On the basis of the data in <xrefGrp>Chapter&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3">3</xref></xrefGrp>, these three companies employed around 5,000 in the Free State in 1922. The denominator for 1922 is unknown but, on a CIP basis, may have been somewhere in the region of 50,000.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-note-112" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>112</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-bibItem-72" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank|Barry, Linda|Menton, Aisling" date="2016" journalIssue="4" title="Tariff&#x2010;Jumping Foreign Direct Investment in Protectionist Era Ireland" journalName="Economic History Review" vol="69" page="1285" pageLast="1308" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, <nameGrp foreNames="Linda" mainName="Barry" role="author">Linda Barry</nameGrp>, and <nameGrp foreNames="Aisling" mainName="Menton" role="author">Aisling Menton</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Tariff&#x2010;Jumping Foreign Direct Investment in Protectionist Era Ireland&#x2019;. <i>Economic History Review</i> 69, 4 (2016): 1285&#x2013;308.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-floatGroup-2">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-tableGroup-3" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0004.007.0003" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-table-3" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-4-titleGroup-9"><title id="C4T3"><p><page id="92" chapter=""/><enumerator>Table 4.3</enumerator> Firms employing <i>c</i>. 400 or more in 1929</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Firm name</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Sector/products</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Employment <i>c</i>. 1929</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Ownership</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p><b>Single-establishment firms</b></p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Ford</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Tractors and motor vehicle parts</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>3,800</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>US</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Guinness</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Brewing</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>3,210</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Jacobs</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Biscuits</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>3,000</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Players&#x2013;Wills</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Tobacco</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>1,500</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Williams and Woods/Crosse &#x0026; Blackwell</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Sugar confectionary and jams</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>900</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>UK</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Goodbody (Jute)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Non-woollen textiles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>800</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Martin Mahony &#x0026; Bros</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Woollen textiles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>600</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p><i>Irish Independent</i></p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Printing and publishing</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>600</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Bolands</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Bread and flour</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>500</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p><b>Multi-establishment firms</b></p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Dwyer and Co.</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Clothing and footwear</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>800</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Bannatyne &#x0026; Sons (Ranks from 1930)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Flour and grain milling</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>800</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish (UK from 1930)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Gouldings</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Fertilizers</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>700</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Dairy Disposal Company</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Dairy products</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 600</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Semi-state company</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Greenmount &#x0026; Boyne</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Non-woollen textiles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>590</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Johnston, Mooney and O&#x2019;Brien</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Bread and flour</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>500</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Firms with close to 500 employees</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Philip Pierce &#x0026; Co.</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Agricultural machinery and bicycles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>250&#x2013;450</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Denny</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Bacon</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 400</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish/UK</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Limerick Clothing Factory</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Clothing</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 300&#x2013;400</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Alexander Thom &#x0026; Co.</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Printing and publishing</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>400</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Helys</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Printing, publishing, stationery</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 300&#x2013;450</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Carrolls</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Tobacco</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 400</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Irish</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div1>
</textMatter>
</chapter>
</mainText>
</book>