<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OXFORD//DTD OXCHAPML//EN" "OxChapML.dtd">
<book id="oso-9780198878230-book-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.001.0001" OSOsubject="physics">
<bookMeta id="oso-9780198878230-bookMeta-1">
<versionInfo>
<versionDate>2023-05-08</versionDate>
<versionDesc>Proofs</versionDesc>
</versionInfo>
<metaItem about="book">
<metaItem about="DTD">
<metaDescribes predicate="DTDname">OxChapML</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
<metaItem about="TCIgroup">
<metaItem about="TCI">
<metaDescribes predicate="TCIname">OUP TCI</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="version">20170301.0</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaItem>
<metaDescribes predicate="product">oso</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="colour-figures-for-online">Yes</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="publishing-group">oso US</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="captured-by">Integra</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</bookMeta>
<mainText id="oso-9780198878230-mainText-1">
<chapter id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007">
<metaInfo id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-metaInfo-1">
<versionInfo>
<versionDate>2023-05-08</versionDate>
<versionDesc>Proofs</versionDesc>
</versionInfo>
<creatorGroup>
<creator class="author" invertedForm="Barry, Frank"><forenames>Frank</forenames><surname>Barry</surname></creator>
</creatorGroup>
<abstract>
<p>T. K. Whitaker, Secretary of the Department of Finance and lead author of the 1958 report which is generally credited with triggering the dismantling of protectionism, underestimated the difficulties of the adjustment required. It would in any case be another five&#x00A0;years before tariff barriers would begin to be dismantled. These steps were taken as part of the campaign to gain entry to the European Economic Community, which could not have been envisaged at the time of the Whitaker Report. De Gaulle&#x2019;s veto of the British application gave Ireland a further ten&#x00A0;years to prepare. Education was revamped, new export-oriented foreign industry expanded, a Free Trade Area Agreement (AIFTA) was signed with the United Kingdom, the Exchequer&#x2019;s dependence on trade taxes was reduced, and restructuring of protectionist-era industry began. This chapter provides details of the major restructurings and mergers and acquisitions of the period. Much of Whitaker&#x2019;s advice however, particularly on macroeconomic policy and cost competitiveness, was ignored. AIFTA was associated with far more industrial redundancies than had been anticipated. By 1972, export-oriented foreign firms accounted for almost 20 per cent of manufacturing employment, with the United States the single most significant source of inward investment. Responsibility for the contested issue of regional industrial dispersal was ultimately devolved to the Industrial Development Authority. The competitive pressures associated with trade liberalization contributed to the erosion of enduring sectarian divisions in the workplace and in Irish business life.</p>
</abstract>
<keySubjectWords>
<keyword>Whitaker Report</keyword>
<keyword>AIFTA</keyword>
<keyword>regional policy</keyword>
<keyword>regional industrial dispersal</keyword>
<keyword>industrial restructuring</keyword>
<keyword>mergers and acquisitions</keyword>
<keyword>brownfield FDI</keyword>
<keyword>sectarian divisions</keyword>
<keyword>free education</keyword></keySubjectWords>
<disclaimer><p><i>Industry and Policy in Independent Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1972</i>. Frank Barry, Oxford University Press. &#x00A9; Frank Barry (2023). DOI: 10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007</p></disclaimer>
<metaItem about="book">
<metaItem about="DTD">
<metaDescribes predicate="DTDname">OxChapML</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
<metaItem about="TCIgroup">
<metaItem about="TCI">
<metaDescribes predicate="TCIname">OUP TCI</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="version">20170301.0</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaItem>
<metaDescribes predicate="product">oso</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="colour-figures-for-online">Yes</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="publishing-group">oso US</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="captured-by">Integra</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaInfo>
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-1"><title id="C7"><p><page id="150" chapter=""/><enumerator>7</enumerator> Trade Liberalization and the Road to Europe</p></title></titleGroup>
<textMatter id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-textMatter-1">
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div1-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.021.0001" role="prelim">
<p id="C7P1">T. K. Whitaker would suggest in later life that &#x2018;perhaps Ireland owes de Gaulle a vote of thanks for delaying enlargement&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-1"><sup>1</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The remark refers to the&#x00A0;years that elapsed between Ireland&#x2019;s first application for membership of the European Economic Community (EEC) and eventual accession in 1973. Ireland had scrambled in 1961 to prepare an application when it became clear that Britain was to do so. The French President, Charles de Gaulle, deeply sceptical of Britain&#x2019;s commitment to the European project, blocked the way. This gave Ireland time to get its house in order. Industrial restructuring began, redundancy entitlements were overhauled, education revamped and the Exchequer&#x2019;s dependence on trade taxes reduced.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-2"><sup>2</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Crucially, the expansion of export-oriented foreign industry would serve as a counterbalance to the job losses experienced as protectionist-era industries went into decline.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-1" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>1</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-1" class="book" author="Chambers, Anne" date="2014" title="TK Whitaker: Portrait of a Patriot" place="Dublin" publisher="Random House" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Anne" mainName="Chambers" role="author">Anne Chambers</nameGrp>, <i>TK Whitaker: Portrait of a Patriot</i> (Dublin: Random House, 2014).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-2" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>2</sup></enumerator> Trade taxes accounted for 41 per cent of tax revenue in 1960. By the time of EEC accession, with the introduction of new forms of taxation, the share had declined to 20 per cent. Most remaining tariffs would be reclassified as excise duties over the next several years: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-2" class="book" author="Haughton, Jonathan" date="2002" title="Trade Agreements and Tax Incentives: The Irish Experience" place="Washington, DC" publisher="Inter-American Development Bank" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Jonathan" mainName="Haughton" role="author">Jonathan Haughton</nameGrp>, Trade Agreements and Tax Incentives: The Irish Experience. ITD&#x2013;INTAL Tax and Integration Series (Washington, DC: Inter-American Development Bank, 2002).</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div1-2" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.021.0002">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-2"><title id="C7S1"><p><enumerator>7.1</enumerator> The Whitaker Report: Context and Content</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C7P2">Whitaker&#x2019;s 1958 report <i>Economic Development</i> has generally been credited with triggering the dismantling of the trade barriers then in place.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-3"><sup>3</sup></xref></xrefGrp> As his remark reflects, he underestimated the difficulties involved in adjusting to freer trade. Policy did indeed pivot in the early 1960s, though not as rapidly as&#x2014;and frequently not in the direction&#x2014;Whitaker had advocated. The document&#x2019;s true significance can be argued to lie as much in context as in content. Whitaker&#x2019;s macroeconomic views are presented more sharply in the address he delivered to the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society a week before his appointment as Secretary of the Department of Finance in 1956. His thinking <page id="151" chapter=""/>on outward reorientation is shown to best effect in the civil service debates of 1959&#x2013;1960 on policy towards the European Free Trade Association (EFTA), the UK-centred trade bloc then in the process of formation in response to the establishment of the EEC.</p>
<p id="C7P3">The EFTA correspondence would be published many&#x00A0;years later under the title <i>Protection or Free Trade&#x2014;The Final Battle</i>.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-4"><sup>4</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The title is something of a misnomer. The outcome of the battle serves as a reminder of the dominance of agricultural considerations in Irish trade policy. Lemass&#x2019;s 1961 submission to the EEC Council of Ministers stated that &#x2018;because of the close inter-relationship of the economy of Ireland and that of the UK, and the vital interest of Ireland in agricultural trade&#x2019;, Ireland hoped that its application would be considered alongside that of the United Kingdom.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-5"><sup>5</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Agricultural interests favoured not free trade but access to the sheltered European market.</p>
<p id="C7P4">Though the Whitaker Report helped to lift the mood of despondency and prepared the country psychologically for the onset of freer industrial trade, it would be another five&#x00A0;years before tariff barriers would begin to be dismantled. The official announcement of the first unilateral tariff cuts in 1963 explicitly stated that the step was taken as part of the campaign to gain entry to the EEC, which could not have been envisaged at the time of the Whitaker Report. To credit the turnaround in trade policy solely or primarily to <i>Economic Development</i> is to ignore this crucial factor.</p>
<p id="C7P5">Nor was <i>Economic Development</i>, as seen in <xrefGrp>Chapter&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-6">6</xref></xrefGrp>, responsible for the new export-oriented foreign direct investment strategy. By the time it was written, the new strategy was already in place. Though Whitaker favoured inward investment and removing the restrictions on foreign ownership, only in 1960 did the Department of Finance explicitly accept that &#x2018;tax concessions must continue to play a vital role in our industrial promotion campaign&#x2019;. Revenue continued to withhold its support.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-6"><sup>6</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P6">The vast bulk of the sectoral analysis in <i>Economic Development</i> was devoted to agriculture and the agri-food industries, which it assumed would be the engine of future growth. Other branches of manufacturing received relatively little attention. The document placed its money, in Liam Kennedy&#x2019;s phrase, &#x2018;on the agricultural donkey rather than the industrial horse&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-7"><sup>7</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The <page id="152" chapter=""/>associated government Programme for Economic Expansion (1958&#x2013;1963) was welcomed particularly warmly by the farming community.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-8"><sup>8</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P7">Publishing the Whitaker report and the government White Paper within weeks of each other provided useful political cover for Fianna F&#x00E1;il. It indicated that &#x2018;the Programme was not, and was not claimed to be, a policy prepared by the government party, but was a national programme, prepared by the head of the civil service&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-9"><sup>9</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Lemass, while asserting that protectionism had secured &#x2018;a basis of industrial organization [and] a pool of managerial competence and industrial skill&#x2019;, accepted that &#x2018;there is a need now to raise our targets and, I believe, also to change our methods&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-10"><sup>10</sup></xref></xrefGrp> De Valera claimed that &#x2018;we set out these policies in 1926&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-11"><sup>11</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P8">There was no meeting of minds between Whitaker and Lemass on broader economic policy. A later Fianna F&#x00E1;il minister has suggested that the approach outlined in the documents may have been viewed by the new Taoiseach as overly grounded in traditional Department of Finance orthodoxy.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-12"><sup>12</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The expansion in government spending and lax wage controls over which Lemass and his successor Jack Lynch presided resulted in a sharp deterioration in international competitiveness just as trade barriers were being dismantled.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-13"><sup>13</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Though Irish economic growth was substantially higher in the 1960s than in earlier periods, so too was growth elsewhere. The country continued to underperform by international&#x2014;and by other low-income Western European economy&#x2014;standards.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-14"><sup>14</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P9">The Whitaker Report inaugurated a new era of coordination between private enterprise and the public sector, something that even conservative commentators had hoped for from the establishment of the Industrial Development Authority (IDA) almost a decade earlier.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-15"><sup>15</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Occasional references to Whitaker&#x2019;s &#x2018;Keynesianism&#x2019;, however, inappropriately employ the term as a synonym for economic planning. Protectionism itself was a highly <page id="153" chapter=""/>state-directed strategy: decision-making as to which sectors to protect and the extent to which they were to be protected was centralized to a large extent in the hands of the Minister for Industry and Commerce. More formally, the French type of indicative planning, which came into vogue in Ireland and elsewhere in the 1960s, entailed detailed and consistent quantitative targets. The First Programme, which was based on the Department of Finance report, was not a plan in this sense. Indeed, it explicitly stated that &#x2018;in an economy in which private enterprise predominates and which is so exposed to fluctuations in external trade, there would be little point in drawing up a detailed plan based on predetermined production targets&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-16"><sup>16</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The recovery that followed was read by many however (including Whitaker) as providing an indication of what planning could achieve.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-17"><sup>17</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Though quantitative targets <i>were</i> adopted in the Second and Third Programmes, which covered the periods from 1964 to 1972, in neither case were the targets achieved.</p>
<p id="C7P10">To an economist, Keynesianism refers not to economic planning but to the conduct of macroeconomic policy. On this and many other matters, Whitaker did indeed adhere strongly to traditional Department of Finance orthodoxy. He warned in his 1956 address to the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of the adverse balance-of-payment consequences of expansionary fiscal spending directed towards goals other than raising productivity. For an economy of Ireland&#x2019;s size, much of the hoped-for stimulus effect would be lost through increased imports.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-18"><sup>18</sup></xref></xrefGrp> These warnings were reiterated in <i>Economic Development</i>.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-19"><sup>19</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P11">Patrick McGilligan&#x2019;s 1950 budget was the first to have shown clear evidence of Keynesian influences. McGilligan would later express his regret that he had not accepted the Finance portfolio in the second Inter-Party government as &#x2018;he might have avoided some of the mistakes in the finance policy of that time&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-20"><sup>20</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Whitaker, by contrast, would remark of Sweetman, who took on the portfolio and implemented the austerity programme, that he was &#x2018;singularly unfortunate [.&#x00A0;.&#x00A0;.] in that his government was overthrown before the ideas which he implemented could bear fruit&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-21"><sup>21</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Indeed, in what can only be seen as an implicit criticism of Lemass, he told an interviewer in 1986 that Sweetman <page id="154" chapter=""/>&#x2018;had both the energy and capacity to carry a thing like <i>Economic Development</i> through&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-22"><sup>22</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P12">Whitaker&#x2019;s 1956 address outlined the supply-side measures by which he believed industrial development could be best advanced. In its advocacy of education and training, adequate provision of utilities, low taxation, tackling restrictive work practices, and aligning pay with productivity, it bore striking parallels to the memorandum that McElligott had furnished to Finance Minister Ernest Blythe in 1923.</p>
<p id="C7P13">The most substantive difference between <i>Economic Development</i> and the government <i>Programme</i> was on regional policy. Joseph Brennan, Whitaker&#x2019;s distant predecessor as Secretary of Finance, had been sceptical of the value of any such policy.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-23"><sup>23</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Less trenchantly, Whitaker argued:</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-displayText-1" class="prosequote">
<p>A realistic appraisal of development prospects indicates that, apart from exceptional cases, industries must be at or near the larger centres of population. Special subsidisation of remote areas by more extensive grants for industrial development is wasteful and retards progress in areas better situated.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-24"><sup>24</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C7P14">Mary Daly describes the First Programme as &#x2018;a watered-down version of <i>Economic Development</i> that expunged or diluted many of the tougher, politically-unpalatable recommendations&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-25"><sup>25</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Whitaker&#x2019;s views on industrial location were not incorporated. The rationale was clearly political, though the political reality is that popular support is required if reform programmes are to be sustained. Responsibility for regional industrial dispersal would ultimately devolve to the IDA.</p>
<p id="C7P15">Whitaker believed that most pre-existing firms and industries would survive outward reorientation. So, too, did Garret FitzGerald, Ireland&#x2019;s leading economic commentator of the time. This expectation would prove hugely overoptimistic. While tariff reductions are of immediate benefit to consumers, the benefits on the production side would accrue only over time through the emergence of new businesses. Most of the protectionist-era firms would have disappeared or downsized dramatically by the mid-to-late 1980s. The industrial transition would be more difficult than either had anticipated.</p>
<p id="C7P16"><page id="155" chapter=""/><i>Economic Development</i>&#x2019;s most immediate consequences were in the realm of administrative politics. Lemass had clashed continuously with the Department of Finance during his long tenure as Minister for Industry and Commerce. There was a danger, as Lee notes, that he might, upon becoming Taoiseach, make other departments central to the formulation of economic policy.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-26"><sup>26</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Already in 1957, Whitaker was urging his assistant secretaries that the department &#x2018;should do some independent thinking and not simply wait for Industry and Commerce or the IDA to produce ideas&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-27"><sup>27</sup></xref></xrefGrp> This accorded with Lemass&#x2019;s view that all of the organs of government should function as &#x2018;development corporations&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-28"><sup>28</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Publication of the report signalled that the primacy of the department had been re-established. Though Whitaker largely subscribed to traditional Department of Finance orthodoxy, he differed from his predecessors Brennan and McElligott in his diplomatic nous and his political skills.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-29"><sup>29</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-3" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>3</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-3" class="book" author="Department of Finance" date="1958" title="Economic Development" place="Dublin" publisher="Stationery Office" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Department of Finance">Department of Finance</nameGrp>, <i>Economic Development</i> (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1958)</bibItem>, (hereafter Whitaker Report).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-4" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>4</sup></enumerator> T. K. Whitaker (ed.), <i>Protection or Free Trade: The Final Battle</i> (Dublin: Institute of Public Administration, 2006).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-5" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>5</sup></enumerator> Cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-4" class="book" author="Murphy, Gary" date="2003" title="Economic Realignment and the Politics of EEC Entry: Ireland, 1948&#x2013;1972" page="141" place="Bethesda, MD" publisher="Academica Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Gary" mainName="Murphy" role="author">Gary Murphy</nameGrp>, <i>Economic Realignment and the Politics of EEC Entry: Ireland, 1948&#x2013;1972</i> (Bethesda, MD: Academica Press, 2003), 141.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-6" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>6</sup></enumerator> NAI, DT 2001/3/122, Letter from Murray to MacCarthy, 30 September 1960.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-7" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>7</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-5" class="book" author="Kennedy, Liam" date="1989" title="The Modern Industrialisation of Ireland, 1940&#x2013;1988" page="14" pageLast="15" place="Dundalk" publisher="Dundalgan Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Liam" mainName="Kennedy" role="author">Liam Kennedy</nameGrp>, <i>The Modern Industrialisation of Ireland, 1940&#x2013;1988</i> (Dundalk: Dundalgan Press, 1989), 14&#x2013;15.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-8" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>8</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-6" class="book" author="Rouse, Paul" date="2000" title="Ireland&#x2019;s Own Soil: Government and Agriculture in Ireland, 1945&#x2013;65" page="139" pageLast="140" place="Dublin" publisher="Irish Farmers Journal" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Paul" mainName="Rouse" role="author">Paul Rouse</nameGrp>, <i>Ireland&#x2019;s Own Soil: Government and Agriculture in Ireland, 1945&#x2013;65</i> (Dublin: Irish Farmers Journal, 2000), 139&#x2013;40.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-9" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>9</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-7" class="book" author="FitzGerald, Garret" date="1968" title="Planning in Ireland" page="26" place="Dublin" publisher="Institute of Public Administration" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Garret" mainName="Fitzgerald" role="author">Garret FitzGerald</nameGrp>, <i>Planning in Ireland</i> (Dublin: Institute of Public Administration, 1968), 26.</bibItem> See also <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-8" class="book" author="Lee, J. J." date="1989" title="Ireland 1912&#x2013;1985: Politics and Society" page="352" place="Cambridge" publisher="Cambridge University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="J. J." mainName="Lee" role="author">J. J. Lee</nameGrp>, <i>Ireland 1912&#x2013;1985: Politics and Society</i> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), 352.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-10" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>10</sup></enumerator> Cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-9" class="book" author="Meenan, James" date="1970" title="The Irish Economy since 1922" page="144" place="Liverpool" publisher="Liverpool University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="James" mainName="Meenan" role="author">James Meenan</nameGrp>, <i>The Irish Economy since 1922</i> (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 1970), 144.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-11" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>11</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-10" class="book" author="Coogan, Tim Pat" date="1995" title="De Valera: Long Fellow, Long Shadow" page="671" place="Arrow Books" publisher="London" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Tim Pat" mainName="Coogan" role="author">Tim Pat Coogan</nameGrp>, <i>De Valera: Long Fellow, Long Shadow</i> (London: Arrow Books, 1995), 671.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-12" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>12</sup></enumerator> Cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-11" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank" date="2009" journalIssue="4" title="Politics and Fiscal Policy under Lemass: A Theoretical Appraisal" journalName="Economic and Social Review" vol="40" page="393" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Politics and Fiscal Policy under Lemass: A Theoretical Appraisal&#x2019;. <i>Economic and Social Review</i> 40, 4 (2009): 393.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-13" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>13</sup></enumerator> On fiscal policy over the period, see <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-12" class="journalArticle" author="Ryan, Louden" date="1971" journalIssue="2" title="Fiscal Policy and Demand Management in Ireland, 1960&#x2013;70" journalName="Economic and Social Review" vol="2" page="253" pageLast="308" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Louden" mainName="Ryan" role="author">Louden Ryan</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Fiscal Policy and Demand Management in Ireland, 1960&#x2013;70&#x2019;. <i>Economic and Social Review</i> 2, 2 (1971): 253&#x2013;308.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-14" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>14</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-13" class="journalArticle" author="Kevin, O&#x2019;Rourke" date="2017" journalIssue="1" title="Independent Ireland in Comparative Perspective" journalName="Irish Economic and Social History" vol="44" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="O&#x2019;Rourke" mainName="Kevin" role="author">Kevin O&#x2019;Rourke</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Independent Ireland in Comparative Perspective&#x2019;. <i>Irish Economic and Social History</i> 44, 1 (2017), 31</bibItem>: figure 7; <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-14" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank" date="2003" journalIssue="5" title="Economic Integration and Convergence Processes in the EU Cohesion Countries" journalName="Journal of Common Market Studies" vol="41" page="897" pageLast="921" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Economic Integration and Convergence Processes in the EU Cohesion Countries&#x2019;. <i>Journal of Common Market Studies</i> 41, 5 (2003): 897&#x2013;921.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-15" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>15</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-15" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank|&#x00D3; Fathartaigh, M&#x00ED;che&#x00E1;l" date="2015" journalIssue="155" title="The Industrial Development Authority, 1949&#x2013;58: Establishment, Evolution and Expansion of Influence&#x2019;" journalName="Irish Historical Studies" vol="39" page="460" pageLast="478" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="M&#x00ED;Che&#x00E1;L" mainName="&#x00d3; Fathartaigh" role="author">M&#x00ED;che&#x00E1;l &#x00D3; Fathartaigh</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Industrial Development Authority, 1949&#x2013;58: Establishment, Evolution and Expansion of Influence&#x2019;. <i>Irish Historical Studies</i> 39, 155 (2015): 460&#x2013;78.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-16" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>16</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-16" class="book" date="1958" title="Programme for Economic Expansion" page="7" place="Dublin" publisher="Stationery Office" purpose="display"><i>Programme for Economic Expansion</i> (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1958), 7.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-17" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>17</sup></enumerator> Cormac &#x00D3; Gr&#x00E1;da, <i>A Rocky Road: The Irish Economy since the 1920s</i> (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 1997), 75.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-18" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>18</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-17" class="journalArticle" author="Whitaker, T. K." date="1955" title="Capital Formation, Saving and Economic Progress" journalName="Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland" vol="16" page="184" pageLast="209" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="T. K." mainName="Whitaker" role="author">T. K. Whitaker</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Capital Formation, Saving and Economic Progress&#x2019;. <i>Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland</i> 16 (1955/56): 184&#x2013;209.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-19" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>19</sup></enumerator> Whitaker Report, 4, 16, 206.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-20" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>20</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 21 February 1973.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-21" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>21</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-18" class="book" author="Fanning, Ronan" date="1978" title="The Irish Department of Finance, 1922&#x2013;58" page="19" place="Dublin" publisher="Institute of Public Administration" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Ronan" mainName="Fanning" role="author">Ronan Fanning</nameGrp>, <i>The Irish Department of Finance, 1922&#x2013;58</i> (Dublin: Institute of Public Administration, 1978), 19.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-22" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>22</sup></enumerator> Cited in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-19" class="book" author="McCarthy, John F." date="1990" title="Planning Ireland&#x2019;s Future: The Legacy of TK Whitaker" page="43" place="Dublin" publisher="Glendale Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John F." mainName="Mccarthy" role="author">John F. McCarthy</nameGrp>, <i>Planning Ireland&#x2019;s Future: The Legacy of TK Whitaker</i> (Dublin: Glendale Press, 1990), 43.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-23" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>23</sup></enumerator> Lee, <i>Ireland 1912&#x2013;1985: Politics and Society</i>, 196.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-24" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>24</sup></enumerator> Whitaker Report, 218.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-25" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>25</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-20" class="book" author="Daly, Mary E." date="2016" title="Sixties Ireland: Reshaping the Economy, State and Society, 1957&#x2013;1973" page="23" place="Cambridge" publisher="Cambridge University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Mary E." mainName="Daly" role="author">Mary E. Daly</nameGrp>, <i>Sixties Ireland: Reshaping the Economy, State and Society, 1957&#x2013;1973</i> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2016), 23.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-26" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>26</sup></enumerator> Lee, <i>Ireland 1912&#x2013;1985: Politics and Society</i>, 343.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-27" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>27</sup></enumerator> Fanning, <i>The Irish Department of Finance, 1922&#x2013;58</i>, 509.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-28" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>28</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-21" class="journalArticle" author="Lemass, Sean F." date="1961" journalIssue="1" title="The Organisation behind the Economic Programme" journalName="Administration" vol="9" page="4" pageLast="10" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Sean F." mainName="Lemass" role="author">Sean F. Lemass</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Organisation behind the Economic Programme&#x2019;. <i>Administration</i> 9, 1 (1961): 4&#x2013;10.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-29" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>29</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-22" class="journalArticle" author="Whitaker, T. K." date="1961" journalIssue="2" journalName="Administration" vol="9" title="The Civil Service and Development" page="107" pageLast="113" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="T. K." mainName="Whitaker" role="author">T. K. Whitaker</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Civil Service and Development&#x2019;. <i>Administration</i> 9, 2 (1961): 107&#x2013;13.</bibItem> Though a planning unit was set up within the department around this time, many of its proposals were stymied by others into whose territories it was perceived to have strayed: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-23" class="unclassified" author="Ryan, Louden" date="2004" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Louden" mainName="Ryan" role="author">Louden Ryan</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Opening Up to the International Economy: Ireland in the 1950s&#x2019;. TCD Witness Seminar, Centre for Contemporary Irish History, 8 December 2004.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div1-3" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.021.0003">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-3"><title id="C7S2"><p><enumerator>7.2</enumerator> European Trade Liberalization: The Inner Six and the Outer Seven</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C7P17">It was presumed, when <i>Economic Development</i> was in preparation, that a Western European Free Trade Area was in the offing. The negotiations sponsored by the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation (OEEC) broke down at the end of 1958 and the region divided into competing trading blocs: the &#x2018;inner six&#x2019; (the original EEC) and the &#x2018;outer seven&#x2019; (the UK-centred EFTA). The formation of these blocs forced a reappraisal of policy across much of the rest of Western Europe.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-30"><sup>30</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P18">EFTA&#x2019;s primary focus was on reducing barriers to industrial trade. As Ireland&#x2019;s industrial exports already enjoyed largely tariff-free access to the UK market, the benefits of this privileged position would be eroded no matter what course of action the Irish government chose to pursue. What the policy response should be was debated by a committee of senior civil servants over a period of several&#x00A0;months in late 1959 and early 1960. The <page id="156" chapter=""/>memos exchanged were intended especially for the eyes of Lemass, who had just become Taoiseach. Industry and Commerce had suggested in previous discussions that two-thirds of existing manufacturing jobs could be lost if industrial trade were liberalized across all of Western Europe. Between 20 and 40 per cent would be at risk, it believed, if Ireland were to join EFTA even under the concessionary terms accorded to the Portuguese. As the United Kingdom comprised over half of the entire EFTA economy, it could foresee little prospect of gains to offset the import penetration that would ensue.</p>
<p id="C7P19">Whitaker disagreed. The Industry and Commerce position paid no attention to competitiveness. Increasing competition on the home market was, in Whitaker&#x2019;s view, a better way of improving efficiency than the &#x2018;special aids and incentives&#x2019; of recent&#x00A0;years &#x2018;to which only the progressive undertakings would respond&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-31"><sup>31</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The discipline of tariff reduction would reduce costs and improve quality and would thereby enhance export prospects not only in EFTA but also more broadly. Membership would also encourage further export-oriented inward foreign direct investment (FDI).</p>
<p id="C7P20">The memos exchanged were models of clarity and succinctness. One raised the challenging question of whether&#x2014;given the freedom of movement of labour between Ireland and Britain&#x2014;&#x2018;a setback in industrial production [would] result not in higher productivity and greater competitiveness but in an outflow of redundant manpower&#x2019;. Whitaker&#x2019;s response was to ask how maintaining the existing regime could be expected to raise living standards sufficiently to reduce emigration.</p>
<p id="C7P21">The crucial intervention came from the Department of Agriculture. It pointed to the likelihood that Irish membership would see pressure brought to bear on the United Kingdom to extend equivalent agricultural access to other EFTA member states. Irish interests would be better served, it suggested, by seeking a Free Trade Area agreement with Britain alone. Whitaker accepted this proposition and EFTA membership was not pursued.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-32"><sup>32</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P22">A free trade agreement with the United Kingdom would not resolve the differences between the Department of Finance and the Department of Industry and Commerce. Nor would EEC membership, though this would be far more attractive to agriculture as it offered a route out from under Britain&#x2019;s traditional &#x2018;cheap food&#x2019; policy. The National Farmers&#x2019; Association saw merit in seeking EEC membership even without the United Kingdom, though the <page id="157" chapter=""/>Department of Agriculture judged that the adverse impact this would have on access to the UK market would outweigh any possible benefits. Britain&#x2019;s surprise decision to submit an application to join the EEC in 1961 resolved this dilemma. A further benefit would be that the &#x2018;traditional links between the United Kingdom and the Commonwealth would be weakened to the advantage of the Irish&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-33"><sup>33</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P23">When news reached Dublin of the United Kingdom&#x2019;s change of heart, an Irish application for membership was immediately submitted. Commission officials, judging that Irish industry would be unable to withstand the shock of full membership, proposed associate membership instead. This would not have guaranteed full access either to the emerging Common Agricultural Policy or to EEC regional aid. The Irish priority then became to demonstrate a willingness and ability to compete on a level playing field.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-34"><sup>34</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P24">The unilateral tariff reductions of 1963 and 1964 were part of this process. The official announcement of the first tariff cut stated that &#x2018;in anticipation of our entry to the EEC, the Government has decided to make a unilateral reduction of 10 percent in protective duties on industrial products on 1st January next&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-35"><sup>35</sup></xref></xrefGrp> These were the across-the-board tariff cuts that Whitaker had been advocating since at least 1956. The signing of the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Area Agreement (AIFTA) in 1965 was the next step in the process.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-36"><sup>36</sup></xref></xrefGrp> De Gaulle&#x2019;s veto of the British application in 1963 gave Ireland a further ten&#x00A0;years to prepare.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-30" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>30</sup></enumerator> On the Finnish case, see, e.g. <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-24" class="journalArticle" author="Paavonen, Tapani" date="2001" journalIssue="1" title="From Isolation to the Core: Finland&#x2019;s Position towards European Integration, 1960&#x2013;95" journalName="Journal of European Integration History" vol="7" page="53" pageLast="75" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Tapani" mainName="Paavonen" role="author">Tapani Paavonen</nameGrp>, &#x2018;From Isolation to the Core: Finland&#x2019;s Position towards European Integration, 1960&#x2013;95&#x2019;. <i>Journal of European Integration History</i> 7, 1 (2001): 53&#x2013;75.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-31" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>31</sup></enumerator> &#x2018;Reasons for Reducing Protection&#x2019;: Department of Finance memo, 14 December 1959.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-32" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>32</sup></enumerator> It is not clear in any case that the United Kingdom would have supported Irish membership. As the Secretary of the Department of Agriculture pointed out, to do so &#x2018;would [bring] additional competition for her exporters into a market where at present they are predominant&#x2019;. See also <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-25" class="book" author="Fitzgerald, Maurice" date="2000" title="Protectionism to Liberalisation: Ireland and the EEC, 1957 to 1966" place="Aldershot" publisher="Ashgate" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Maurice" mainName="Fitzgerald" role="author">Maurice Fitzgerald</nameGrp>, <i>Protectionism to Liberalisation: Ireland and the EEC, 1957 to 1966</i> (Aldershot: Ashgate, 2000)</bibItem>, 31.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-33" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>33</sup></enumerator> Murphy, <i>Economic Realignment and the Politics of EEC Entry</i>, 215.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-34" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>34</sup></enumerator> Fitzgerald, <i>Protectionism to Liberalisation</i>, 121.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-35" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>35</sup></enumerator> Murphy, <i>Economic Realignment and the Politics of EEC Entry</i>, 88.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-36" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>36</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-26" class="book" author="Maher, Denis J." date="1986" title="The Tortuous Path: The Course of Ireland&#x2019;s Entry into the EEC, 1948&#x2013;73" page="172" place="Dublin" publisher="Institute of Public Administration" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Denis J." mainName="Maher" role="author">Denis J. Maher</nameGrp>, <i>The Tortuous Path: The Course of Ireland&#x2019;s Entry into the EEC, 1948&#x2013;73</i> (Dublin: Institute of Public Administration, 1986), 172</bibItem>, 200; Fitzgerald, <i>Protectionism to Liberalisation</i> 2, 292.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div1-4" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.021.0004">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-4"><title id="C7S3"><p><enumerator>7.3</enumerator> Policy Developments</p></title></titleGroup>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div2-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.022.0001">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-5"><title><p id="C7S4">Committee on Industrial Organisation</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C7P25">A new tripartite body, the Committee on Industrial Organisation (CIO), was established by government in 1961 to consider how industry might be assisted in preparing for the onset of freer trade. Twenty-six branches of manufacturing were identified as likely to be particularly strongly impacted and were earmarked for careful examination.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-37"><sup>37</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The Department of Agriculture was tasked with reporting on the issues pertaining to dairy products, grain milling, and fresh meats. The reports published by the CIO over the <page id="158" chapter=""/>next several years provided clear evidence of the structural defects to which decades of protection had given rise. These included small firm size, excessive diversification, short production runs, and inferior quality. Garret FitzGerald&#x2019;s reading of the reports nevertheless led him to conclude that there was a &#x2018;viable industrial base, with individual inefficient firms, rather than a series of industries incapable of withstanding competition&#x2019;. &#x2018;With the possible exception of vehicle assembly work&#x2019;, he believed, &#x2018;the industrial activities started in Ireland since 1932 were likely, in one form or another, to survive free trade.&#x2019;<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-38"><sup>38</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P26">One of the purposes of the surveys was to &#x2018;encourage the businessman himself to start asking more questions and to assess his own position more critically&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-39"><sup>39</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Many business leaders soon came to understand the extent of the rationalization required.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-40"><sup>40</sup></xref></xrefGrp> A 1975 report of the Restrictive Practices Commission records the massive wave of mergers and acquisitions that occurred across all of industry in the&#x00A0;years leading up to EEC accession. These developments are discussed towards the end of this chapter and in <xrefGrp>Chapter&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-8">8</xref></xrefGrp>.</p>
<p id="C7P27">One of the CIO reports was devoted to the role of state aid in promoting the necessary adjustment. A later National Economic and Social Council review suggested that the various types of financial assistance that became available from 1963 were less than adequate.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-41"><sup>41</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Grant payments do not appear to have been carefully targeted however, and many ended up being extended to business sectors that had not been surveyed by the CIO.</p>
<p id="C7P28">The issue of redundancy payments, the subject of another of the Committee&#x2019;s reports, was tackled more successfully. A Redundancy Payments Act was introduced in the United Kingdom in 1965 as part of the Labour government&#x2019;s efforts to promote industrial modernization. While Irish social security reforms generally followed those in the United Kingdom with a long lag, an Irish act followed in this case within two years. &#x2018;From very restricted and ad hoc coverage under protectionism&#x2019;, Murray notes, &#x2018;state compensation for redundancy became a basic employment right in the course of adaptation to free trade.&#x2019;<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-42"><sup>42</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-37" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>37</sup></enumerator> On the choice of the branches of industry to be surveyed, see FitzGerald, <i>Planning in Ireland</i>, 58&#x2013;59.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-38" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>38</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-27" class="book" author="Maher, Denis J." date="1986" title="The Tortuous Path: The Course of Ireland&#x2019;s Entry into the EEC, 1948&#x2013;73" page="172" place="Dublin" publisher="Institute of Public Administration" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-26">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 64&#x2013;65.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-39" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>39</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-28" class="journalArticle" author="Brock, Catherine" date="1964" journalIssue="2" title="The CIO Industrial Survey" journalName="Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland" vol="21" page="184" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Catherine" mainName="Brock" role="author">Catherine Brock</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The CIO Industrial Survey&#x2019;. <i>Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland</i> 21, 2 (1964): 184.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-40" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>40</sup></enumerator> See, e.g. the reflections of the former owner of Killarney footwear manufacturer Hilliard, who had overseen its acquisition by UK company G. B. Britton (Ireland) in 1965: <i>Irish Times</i>, 25 February 1972.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-41" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>41</sup></enumerator> See, e.g. <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-29" class="book" author="Blackwell, John|Danaher, Gerard|Eoin, O&#x2019;Malley" date="1983" title="An Analysis of Job Losses in Irish Manufacturing Industry" page="47" place="Dublin" publisher="National Economic and Social Council" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John" mainName="Blackwell" role="author">John Blackwell</nameGrp>, <nameGrp foreNames="Gerard" mainName="Danaher" role="author">Gerard Danaher</nameGrp>, and <nameGrp foreNames="O&#x2019;Malley" mainName="Eoin" role="author">Eoin O&#x2019;Malley</nameGrp>, <i>An Analysis of Job Losses in Irish Manufacturing Industry</i> (Dublin: National Economic and Social Council 1983), 47.</bibItem> For details of the incentives and incentive structures of the period, see <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-30" class="book" author="Eoin, O&#x2019;Malley" date="1980" title="Industrial Policy and Development: A Survey of Literature from the Early 1960s" place="Dublin" publisher="National Economic and Social Council" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="O&#x2019;Malley" mainName="Eoin" role="author">Eoin O&#x2019;Malley</nameGrp>, <i>Industrial Policy and Development: A Survey of Literature from the Early 1960s</i> (Dublin: National Economic and Social Council, 1980).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-42" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>42</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-31" class="book" author="Murray, Peter" date="2009" title="Facilitating the Future: US Aid, European Integration and Irish Industrial Viability: 1948&#x2013;73" page="96" place="Dublin" publisher="University College Dublin Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Peter" mainName="Murray" role="author">Peter Murray</nameGrp>, <i>Facilitating the Future: US Aid, European Integration and Irish Industrial Viability: 1948&#x2013;73</i> (Dublin: University College Dublin Press, 2009), 96.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div2-2" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.022.0002">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-6"><title><p id="C7S5"><page id="159" chapter=""/>Education</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C7P29">The overhauling of the country&#x2019;s education system was a consequence of the change in mindset associated with outward reorientation. Garvin characterizes the education system of the time as designed to reproduce &#x2018;a certain social type, pious, familial, loyal to the native acres, culturally ingrown and obedient to clerical guidance in matters moral and intellectual&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-43"><sup>43</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Richard Mulcahy had described his role as Education Minister in the mid-1950s as &#x2018;a kind of dungaree man [to] take the knock out of the pipes&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-44"><sup>44</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The country&#x2019;s increasing contacts with multilateral organizations encouraged it to benchmark itself against international standards. When a suggestion was made at a conference in Washington in 1961 that the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) examine a number of educational systems in their entirety, Ireland was the first country to volunteer to be surveyed.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-45"><sup>45</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Whitaker was instrumental in shepherding the potentially divisive proposal through the Irish administrative system.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-46"><sup>46</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P30">The resulting report, <i>Investment in Education</i>, was published in 1965.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-47"><sup>47</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Conducted by a team of Irish economists and educationalists under the auspices of the OECD, its central propositions were that a non-meritocratic education system was wasteful of natural talent and that investment in human capital had made a substantial contribution to post-war European growth. The finding that attracted most attention was that one-third of Irish children were leaving school at or before the age of thirteen.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-48"><sup>48</sup></xref></xrefGrp> An appendix provided information on the educational attainment levels of the populations of seventeen countries across the globe, including seven in Eastern Europe. No equivalent statistics could be produced for Ireland. Questions on educational attainment would be included in the Irish population census from the following year.</p>
<p id="C7P31">The changing industrial environment also influenced the work of the corporatist National Industrial Economic Council. One of its first reports, issued under Whitaker&#x2019;s chairmanship, alluded to the concept known to economists as &#x2018;the ladder of comparative advantage&#x2019;: as the average level of skills and technical competence rises, &#x2018;the range of economic activity which can be <page id="160" chapter=""/>carried on efficiently in Ireland will grow and the pace of economic development will be accelerated&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-49"><sup>49</sup></xref></xrefGrp> This was the background to Donogh O&#x2019;Malley&#x2019;s announcement of &#x2018;free education&#x2019; in his first major speech as Education Minister in September 1966. Universal access to free second-level schooling and to free or subsidized school transport was introduced the following year. The school-leaving age was raised shortly afterwards. That O&#x2019;Malley&#x2019;s announcement had not been approved by the Cabinet caused consternation in the Department of Finance, though any failure to sanction the policy would have been politically disastrous given the enthusiasm with which it had been greeted.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-50"><sup>50</sup></xref></xrefGrp> In its by-passing of the Department of Finance, it bears similarities to Costello&#x2019;s announcement of export profits tax relief almost exactly ten&#x00A0;years earlier.</p>
<p id="C7P32">There was a discernible surge in the numbers attending second-level institutions following the removal of tuition fees, and a particularly sharp increase in the number of girls completing the senior cycle.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-51"><sup>51</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Overall completions increased by 150 per cent over the decade between the lapse of Ireland&#x2019;s first EEC application and eventual accession. Attendance at third-level educational institutions expanded in tandem, and new types of institutions were created to provide the technical skills necessary to meet prospective industrial requirements. The first five Regional Technical Colleges (RTCs) were established in 1970. Those established later in the decade would be financed to a large extent by the European Social Fund. Many have combined in recent&#x00A0;years to form the country&#x2019;s new technological universities.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-43" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>43</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-32" class="book" author="Garvin, Tom" date="2004" title="Preventing the Future: Why Was Ireland So Poor for So Long?" page="184" place="Dublin" publisher="Gill and Macmillan" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Tom" mainName="Garvin" role="author">Tom Garvin</nameGrp>, <i>Preventing the Future: Why Was Ireland So Poor for So Long?</i> (Dublin: Gill and Macmillan, 2004), 184.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-44" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>44</sup></enumerator> <i>PDDE</i>, 19 July 1956.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-45" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>45</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-33" class="book" author="White, Tony" date="2001" title="Investing in People: Higher Education in Ireland from 1960 to 2000" place="Dublin" publisher="Institute of Public Administration" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Tony" mainName="White" role="author">Tony White</nameGrp>, <i>Investing in People: Higher Education in Ireland from 1960 to 2000</i> (Dublin: Institute of Public Administration, 2001).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-46" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>46</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-34" class="book" author="Walsh, John" date="2009" title="The Politics of Expansion: The Transformation of Educational Policy in the Republic of Ireland, 1957&#x2013;72" page="64" pageLast="65" place="Manchester" publisher="Manchester University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John" mainName="Walsh" role="author">John Walsh</nameGrp>, <i>The Politics of Expansion: The Transformation of Educational Policy in the Republic of Ireland, 1957&#x2013;72</i> (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2009), 64&#x2013;65.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-47" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>47</sup></enumerator> <i>Investment in Education</i> (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1965).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-48" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>48</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-35" class="journalArticle" author="FitzGerald, Garret" date="1965" journalIssue="216" title="Investment in Education" journalName="Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review" vol="54" page="361" pageLast="374" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Garret" mainName="Fitzgerald" role="author">Garret FitzGerald</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Investment in Education&#x2019;. <i>Studies: An Irish Quarterly Review</i> 54, 216 (1965): 361&#x2013;74.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-49" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>49</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-36" class="book" author="NIEC (National Industrial Economic Council)" date="1964" title="Report on Manpower Policy" page="19" place="Dublin" publisher="National Industrial Economic Council" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="NIEC (National Industrial Economic Council)">NIEC (National Industrial Economic Council)</nameGrp>, <i>Report on Manpower Policy</i> (Dublin: National Industrial Economic Council, 1964), 19.</bibItem> See also the <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-37" class="book" date="1967" title="Survey of Grant-Aided Industry: Survey Team&#x2019;s Report" page="98" place="Dublin" publisher="Stationery Office" purpose="display"><i>Survey of Grant-Aided Industry: Survey Team&#x2019;s Report</i> (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1967), 98.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-50" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>50</sup></enumerator> Walsh, <i>The Politics of Expansion</i>, 190. Whether Lemass had prior knowledge of the announcement and had given it his approval remains unclear: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-38" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank" date="2014" journalIssue="2" title="Outward-Oriented Economic Development and the Irish Education System" journalName="Irish Educational Studies" vol="33" page="213" pageLast="223" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Outward-Oriented Economic Development and the Irish Education System&#x2019;. <i>Irish Educational Studies</i> 33, 2 (2014): 213&#x2013;23.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-51" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>51</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-39" class="journalArticle" author="Raftery, Adrian E.|Hout, Michael" date="1993" journalIssue="1" title="Maximally Maintained Inequality: Expansion, Reform, and Opportunity in Irish Education, 1921&#x2013;75" journalName="Sociology of Education" vol="66" page="41" pageLast="62" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Adrian E." mainName="Raftery" role="author">Adrian E. Raftery</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Michael" mainName="Hout" role="author">Michael Hout</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Maximally Maintained Inequality: Expansion, Reform, and Opportunity in Irish Education, 1921&#x2013;75&#x2019;. <i>Sociology of Education</i> 66, 1 (1993): 41&#x2013;62;</bibItem> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-40" class="journalArticle" author="Kellaghan, Thomas|Hegarty, Mary" date="1984" title="Participation in the Leaving Certificate Examination, 1961&#x2013;1980" journalName="Irish Journal of Education" page="72" pageLast="106" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Thomas" mainName="Kellaghan" role="author">Thomas Kellaghan</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Mary" mainName="Hegarty" role="author">Mary Hegarty</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Participation in the Leaving Certificate Examination, 1961&#x2013;1980&#x2019;. <i>Irish Journal of Education</i> (1984): 72&#x2013;106.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div2-3" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.022.0003">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-7"><title><p id="C7S6">Industrial Relations and Macroeconomic Policy</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C7P33"><i>Economic Development</i> had advocated that the margin between British and Irish wages and salaries be maintained, at least into the near term.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-52"><sup>52</sup></xref></xrefGrp> This was not achieved. Compensation per manufacturing employee increased at one-and-a half times the UK rate between 1960 and 1972.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-53"><sup>53</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Though these wage pressures may have been independent of trade liberalization, the <page id="161" chapter=""/>employment consequences were not. Costs could not be passed on as easily to consumers in a world of freer trade.</p>
<p id="C7P34">Lemass&#x2019;s macroeconomic policies were influenced more by his desire to maintain the support of the trade union movement than by <i>Economic Development</i>. Within a&#x00A0;year of becoming Taoiseach, &#x2018;he had abandoned the cautious economic policy, and budgets began to expand with increased investment in those areas identified by Congress both in policy documents and in its private research&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-54"><sup>54</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Tensions over his perceived acquiescence to trade union demands led to the resignation of his agriculture minister in 1964.</p>
<p id="C7P35">Lemass appears to have desired to emulate the social partnership arrangements that prevailed across much of Continental Europe. These involved unions committing to wage moderation in exchange for increased social spending.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-55"><sup>55</sup></xref></xrefGrp> In 1963 he proposed that &#x2018;wages and salaries should [.&#x00A0;.&#x00A0;.] be adjusted upward at an average rate slightly less than the realised growth of national production&#x2019; in order to provide a margin &#x2018;for social insurance benefits or other desirable social objects&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-56"><sup>56</sup></xref></xrefGrp> In the highly fragmented Irish industrial relations system of the time, such a deal could not be secured.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-57"><sup>57</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Hardiman notes that &#x2018;no single bargaining group believed it had to pay any attention to the impact of its activities on the overall state of economic performance&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-58"><sup>58</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Lemass&#x2019;s wooing of the unions, in Horgan&#x2019;s estimation, gave them &#x2018;a new sense of their industrial strength, which was to usher in unparalleled unrest in 1964 and 1965 and wage settlements that ran quickly out of control&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-59"><sup>59</sup></xref></xrefGrp> As a later Fianna F&#x00E1;il finance minister, Ray MacSharry, would comment of the &#x2018;ill-fated&#x2019; 1977 Fianna F&#x00E1;il Manifesto, &#x2018;all the benefits were front-loaded, and the payback never came&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-60"><sup>60</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P36">Though unemployment was higher and productivity growth lower than in the other less advanced economies to which the Ireland of the time bears <page id="162" chapter=""/>comparison, Irish real wage growth was far more rapid. Greece, Spain, and Portugal all converged strongly on Western European living standards over the period 1960&#x2013;1973. Ireland did not.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-52" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>52</sup></enumerator> Whitaker Report, 27.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-53" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>53</sup></enumerator> Wage data from European Commission AMECO database.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-54" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>54</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-41" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Girvin, Brian" partTitle="Trade Unions and Economic Development" editor="Nevin, Donal" date="1994" title="Trade Union Century" page="117" pageLast="132" place="Dublin" publisher="Mercier Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Brian" mainName="Girvin" role="partAuthor">Brian Girvin</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Trade Unions and Economic Development&#x2019;, in <i>Trade Union Century</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Donal" mainName="Nevin" role="editor">Donal Nevin</nameGrp> (Dublin: Mercier Press, 1994), 117&#x2013;32.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-55" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>55</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-42" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Eichengreen, Barry" partTitle="Institutions and Economic Growth: Europe after World War II" editor="Crafts, Nicholas|Toniolo, Gianni" date="1996" title="European Economic Growth" page="38" pageLast="72" place="Cambridge" publisher="Cambridge University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Barry" mainName="Eichengreen" role="partAuthor">Barry Eichengreen</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Institutions and Economic Growth: Europe after World War II&#x2019;, in <i>European Economic Growth</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Nicholas" mainName="Crafts" role="editor">Nicholas Crafts</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Gianni" mainName="Toniolo" role="editor">Gianni Toniolo</nameGrp> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996), 38&#x2013;72.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-56" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>56</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-43" class="book" author="Horgan, John" date="1999" title="Se&#x00E1;n Lemass, The Enigmatic Patriot" page="229" place="Dublin" publisher="Gill and Macmillan" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John" mainName="Horgan" role="author">John Horgan</nameGrp>, <i>Se&#x00E1;n Lemass, The Enigmatic Patriot</i> (Dublin: Gill and Macmillan 1999), 229.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-57" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>57</sup></enumerator> This was also the case in France, Italy, and the United Kingdom, where the industrial relations environment impacted adversely on economic growth: Eichengreen, &#x2018;Institutions and Economic Growth: Europe after World War II&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-58" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>58</sup></enumerator> Niamh Hardiman, &#x2018;Pay Bargaining: Confrontation and Consensus&#x2019;, in <i>Trade Union Century</i>, ed. Nevin.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-59" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>59</sup></enumerator> Horgan, <i>Se&#x00E1;n Lemass, The Enigmatic Patriot</i>, 190. Roche, too, concludes that Lemass had &#x2018;seriously underestimated the challenge of transforming the Irish industrial relations system&#x2019;: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-44" class="journalArticle" author="Roche, William K." date="2009" journalIssue="2" title="Social Partnership: From Lemass to Cowen" journalName="Economic and Social Review" vol="40" page="183" pageLast="205" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="William K." mainName="Roche" role="author">William K. Roche</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Social Partnership: From Lemass to Cowen&#x2019;. <i>Economic and Social Review</i> 40, 2 (2009): 183&#x2013;205.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-60" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>60</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-45" class="book" author="MacSharry, Ray|White, Padraic A." date="2000" title="The Making of the Celtic Tiger: The Inside Story of Ireland&#x2019;s Booming Economy" place="Cork" publisher="Mercier Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Ray" mainName="Macsharry" role="author">Ray MacSharry</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Padraic A." mainName="White" role="author">Padraic A. White</nameGrp>, <i>The Making of the Celtic Tiger: The Inside Story of Ireland&#x2019;s Booming Economy</i> (Cork: Mercier Press, 2000).</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div2-4" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.022.0004">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-8"><title><p id="C7S7">Anglo-Irish Free Trade Area Agreement</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C7P37">The Anglo-Irish Free Trade Area Agreement (AIFTA) was signed in 1965 and came into effect the following year. It committed the Irish government to eliminating restrictions on non-agricultural imports from the United Kingdom over the next ten years. Tariffs were to be eliminated in ten equal annual steps. Given the height of the restrictions at the outset of the process, the effects were expected to become apparent only around 1970. The United Kingdom for its part liberalized access to Irish agri-food exports and eliminated its tariffs on products containing man-made fibres, which were among the few items that remained dutiable at this point.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-61"><sup>61</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P38">AIFTA was clearly perceived as a trade-off between Ireland&#x2019;s agri-food interests and the interests of protectionist-era industry.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-62"><sup>62</sup></xref></xrefGrp> To the latter, it was seen as an even greater threat than EEC membership. There would be little gain in market access to compensate for the increase in imports, and Britain&#x2019;s export drive would be concentrated on Ireland rather than dispersed more broadly across the EEC.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-63"><sup>63</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The share of the market captured by competing imports would have continued to expand in any case as consumption across the developed world was becoming increasingly &#x2018;cosmopolitan&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-64"><sup>64</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Contemporary analyses that took this into account concluded that the net job losses specifically ascribable to the agreement would be quite modest.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-65"><sup>65</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The most comprehensive analysis, by McAleese and Martin, suggested that AIFTA would result in around 3,000 job losses alongside a gain of around 1,000 in artificial fibres.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-66"><sup>66</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P39">The McAleese and Martin study was focused particularly on quantifying the import effects. It may have underestimated the number of new jobs that would be created. In extrapolating from agriculture it largely ignored the job gains associated with the expansion of agri-food businesses.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-67"><sup>67</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The dramatic <page id="163" chapter=""/>increase in exports of butter, cheese, and beef from 1965 created almost 3,500 new jobs in these sectors by 1972.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-68"><sup>68</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The impact of AIFTA on inward FDI was also not taken into consideration.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-69"><sup>69</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Two major AIFTA-related synthetic-fibre projects, &#x2018;Pretty Polly&#x2019; in Killarney and Lana-Knit at Shannon, employed over 1,300 by 1972.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-70"><sup>70</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P40">In most industrial sectors&#x2014;as anticipated&#x2014;competing imports captured an increased share of the domestic market. The increase in the export share of Irish output was largely ascribable to the increasing presence of new export-oriented foreign firms.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-71"><sup>71</sup></xref></xrefGrp> For the few existing firms for which data are available, there were particularly large increases in the cases of Sunbeam&#x2013;Wolsey, Seafield&#x2013;Gentex and Martin Mahony.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-72"><sup>72</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Janelle, a recently established indigenous manufacturer of synthetic-fibre garments for British department stores, also expanded strongly as a result of the agreement.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-73"><sup>73</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P41">AIFTA was associated, nevertheless, with a striking increase in the number of industrial redundancies. Job losses <i>per annum</i> in the early 1970s were multiples of the entire <i>aggregate</i> job losses considered likely by McAleese and Martin.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-74"><sup>74</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The conflict-ridden industrial relations system of the time was at least partly to blame. The emerging &#x2018;dual-economy&#x2019; nature of Irish manufacturing may have further distorted wage-setting behaviour. The much more rapid productivity growth of the era&#x2014;another consequence of the influx of new modern industries&#x2014;appears to have driven wage settlements across the entire manufacturing sector.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-75"><sup>75</sup></xref></xrefGrp> This would have hastened the demise of cost-sensitive traditional industry.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-76"><sup>76</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-61" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>61</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-46" class="journalArticle" author="McAleese, Dermot|Martin, John" date="1973" title="Irish Manufactured Imports from the UK in the Sixties: The Effects of AIFTA" journalName="Economic and Social Research Institute (ESRI) Research Series" vol="70" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Dermot" mainName="Mcaleese" role="author">Dermot McAleese</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="John" mainName="Martin" role="author">John Martin</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Irish Manufactured Imports from the UK in the Sixties: The Effects of AIFTA&#x2019;. <i>Economic and Social Research Institute (ESRI) Research Series</i>, 70 (1973): 9, 54&#x2013;55.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-62" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>62</sup></enumerator> Fitzgerald, <i>Protectionism to Liberalisation</i>, <xrefGrp>ch. <xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-3">3</xref></xrefGrp>, <xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-127">127</xref></xrefGrp>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-63" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>63</sup></enumerator> Daly, <i>Sixties Ireland: Reshaping the Economy, State and Society, 1957&#x2013;1973</i>, 31.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-64" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>64</sup></enumerator> McAleese and Martin, &#x2018;Irish Manufactured Imports from the UK in the Sixties&#x2019;, 40.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-65" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>65</sup></enumerator> Garret FitzGerald, <i>Irish Times</i>, 14 January 1972; McAleese and Martin, &#x2018;Irish Manufactured Imports from the UK in the Sixties&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-66" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>66</sup></enumerator> McAleese and Martin, &#x2018;Irish Manufactured Imports from the UK in the Sixties&#x2019;.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-67" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>67</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-47" class="journalArticle" author="McAleese, Dermot|Martin, John" date="1973" title="Irish Manufactured Imports from the UK in the Sixties: The Effects of AIFTA" journalName="Economic and Social Research Institute (ESRI) Research Series" vol="70" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-46">Ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>., 57.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-68" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>68</sup></enumerator> Around one-third of the jobs were in beef processing. Beef exports, which had been encouraged by subsidy payments introduced by agriculture minister Charles Haughey, partly substituted for live cattle exports: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-48" class="book" author="Baker, Terence J.|Robert, O&#x2019;Connor|Dunne, Rory" date="1973" title="A Study of the Irish Cattle and Beef Industries" page="75" place="Dublin" publisher="Economic and Social Research Institute" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Terence J." mainName="Baker" role="author">Terence J. Baker</nameGrp>, <nameGrp foreNames="O&#x2019;Connor" mainName="Robert" role="author">Robert O&#x2019;Connor</nameGrp>, and <nameGrp foreNames="Rory" mainName="Dunne" role="author">Rory Dunne</nameGrp>, <i>A Study of the Irish Cattle and Beef Industries</i> (Dublin: Economic and Social Research Institute 1973), 75</bibItem>; <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-49" class="book" author="Declan, O&#x2019;Brien" date="2021" title="The Dublin Cattle Market&#x2019;s Decline, 1955&#x2013;1973" page="27" place="Dublin" publisher="Four Courts Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="O&#x2019;Brien" mainName="Declan" role="author">Declan O&#x2019;Brien</nameGrp>, <i>The Dublin Cattle Market&#x2019;s Decline, 1955&#x2013;1973</i> (Dublin: Four Courts Press, 2021), 27.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-69" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>69</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-50" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="McAleese, Dermot" partTitle="Anglo-Irish Economic Interdependence: From Excessive Intimacy to a Wider Embrace" editor="Drudy, P. J." date="1986" title="Ireland and Britain since 1922" page="96" place="Cambridge" publisher="Cambridge University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Dermot" mainName="Mcaleese" role="partAuthor">Dermot McAleese</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Anglo-Irish Economic Interdependence: From Excessive Intimacy to a Wider Embrace&#x2019;, in <i>Ireland and Britain since 1922</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="P. J." mainName="Drudy" role="editor">P. J. Drudy</nameGrp> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1986), 96.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-70" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>70</sup></enumerator> Teeling provides evidence that the marketing plans of new foreign companies became increasingly focussed on the United Kingdom in the late 1960s: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-51" class="unclassified" author="Teeling, John" date="1975" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="John" mainName="Teeling" role="author">John Teeling</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Evolution of Offshore Investment&#x2019;. DBA thesis, Harvard University, 1975, 28</bibItem>, tables 2.1.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-71" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>71</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-52" class="journalArticle" author="McAleese, Dermot" date="1977" journalIssue="1" title="Do Tariffs Matter? Industrial Specialization and Trade in a Small Economy" journalName="Oxford Economic Papers" vol="29" page="117" pageLast="127" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Dermot" mainName="Mcaleese" role="author">Dermot McAleese</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Do Tariffs Matter? Industrial Specialization and Trade in a Small Economy&#x2019;. <i>Oxford Economic Papers</i> 29, 1 (1977): 117&#x2013;27.</bibItem>; Blackwell et al., <i>An Analysis of Job Losses in Irish Manufacturing Industry</i>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-72" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>72</sup></enumerator> The expansion relates to the period 1966/67&#x2013;1971/72: <i>Irish Times</i>, Fifty largest Irish industrial companies, November&#x2013;December, various years.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-73" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>73</sup></enumerator> Janelle&#x2019;s workforce grew from less than 50 in 1961 to 622 in 1972.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-74" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>74</sup></enumerator> &#x2018;The Disappearing Jobs&#x2019;, <i>Irish Times</i>, 11 August 1972.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-75" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>75</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-53" class="journalArticle" author="Baccaro, Lucio|Simoni, Marco" date="2007" journalIssue="3" title="Centralized Wage Bargaining and the &#x201C;Celtic Tiger&#x201D; Phenomenon" journalName="Industrial Relations: A Journal of Economy and Society" vol="46" page="426" pageLast="455" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Lucio" mainName="Baccaro" role="author">Lucio Baccaro</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Marco" mainName="Simoni" role="author">Marco Simoni</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Centralized Wage Bargaining and the &#x201C;Celtic Tiger&#x201D; Phenomenon&#x2019;. <i>Industrial Relations: A Journal of Economy and Society</i> 46, 3 (2007): 426&#x2013;55.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-76" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>76</sup></enumerator> The differential productivity patterns of indigenous and foreign industry continue to complicate the measurement of Irish cost competitiveness: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-54" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank" date="2017" journalIssue="4" title="The Central Bank&#x2019;s Harmonised Competitiveness Indicators: Users Beware" journalName="Administration" vol="65" page="73" pageLast="82" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Central Bank&#x2019;s Harmonised Competitiveness Indicators: Users Beware&#x2019;. <i>Administration</i> 65, 4 (2017): 73&#x2013;82.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div2>
<div2 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div2-5" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.022.0005">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-9"><title><p id="C7S8"><page id="164" chapter=""/>The IDA, &#x2018;New Industry&#x2019;, and Regional Development</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C7P42">The IDA expanded in size and significance as its success in attracting foreign industry became increasingly apparent. Its first overseas office had been opened in New York in the late 1950s. By 1966 it also had offices in London and Cologne. There were six overseas IDA offices in 1970, eight in 1972, and eleven by the end of 1973.</p>
<p id="C7P43">It was restructured twice, in 1959 and 1969, in line in each case with its own recommendations. In the second more substantial restructuring the grant-giving agency (An Foras Tionscal) was merged with the promotional and advisory authority and the &#x2018;new&#x2019; IDA was established as an autonomous, state-sponsored body entirely outside the confines of the civil service. IDA staff numbers had increased from around a dozen in the late 1940s to sixty in 1967. The &#x2018;new&#x2019; IDA had a staff complement of 250 in 1972.</p>
<p id="C7P44">One recommendation of the 1967 Arthur D. Little consultancy report that had advised on the second restructuring was not acted upon. This was that the functions of the state rescue agency Taisc&#x00ED; St&#x00E1;it Teoranta be transferred to the new body. It was instead reconstituted as F&#x00F3;ir Teoranta in the early 1970s. The IDA is unlikely to have coveted such a poisoned chalice. One of the few stains on its reputation had been its experience with the French company Potez Aerospace, which had established a venture at Baldonnel in 1961 to build small executive aircraft. None was ever built and the plant closed in 1968 with significant losses to the Exchequer.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-77"><sup>77</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P45">By the eve of EEC accession, post-1955 export-oriented foreign firms accounted for almost 20 per cent of manufacturing employment, with the United States the single most significant source of inward investment.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-78"><sup>78</sup></xref></xrefGrp> US firms accounted for at least one-third of the jobs among the group.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-79"><sup>79</sup></xref></xrefGrp> As illustrated in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-1">7.1</xref></xrefGrp>, they continued to comprise the bulk of foreign multinational enterprise employment at Shannon.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-80"><sup>80</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-1"?></p>
<p id="C7P46"><page id="165" chapter=""/>Across much of the developing world, export-platform foreign investment of this type led to a large increase in the female share of employment. In Ireland, the female share of new grant-aided industry did not differ significantly from that of existing industry. The Irish authorities, with the support of the trade unions, focussed heavily on projects that would provide jobs for male workers.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-81"><sup>81</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The low status of factory work for women, furthermore, meant that it could be difficult to attract and retain female labour.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-82"><sup>82</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The Shannon Free Airport Development Company (SFADCo) announced in 1963 that:</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-displayText-2" class="prosequote">
<p>In order to maintain the balance in favour of male employment, and to ensure that the demand for women workers by firms already established and engaged in expanding their operations will be met, [&#x2026;] the Company&#x0027;s current promotional campaign is being directed towards firms such as those in the light engineering industry who would require male employees predominantly.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-83"><sup>83</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C7P47"><page id="166" chapter=""/>The Industrial Development Authority noted in 1973 that the male-female employment ratio of roughly 3-to-1 associated with the projects it had approved for grant aid over the previous&#x00A0;year was &#x2018;in line with our target&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-84"><sup>84</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C7P48">The IDA had not been an integral part of the planning process initiated under the First Programme for Economic Expansion. This changed from 1966, when it was granted responsibility for evaluating and promoting new indigenous industrial projects as well as those from overseas sources.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-85"><sup>85</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Though the quantitative targets set out in the Second and Third Programmes were not achieved, the practice of quantitative targeting, paradoxically, would become part of the modus operandi of the &#x2018;new&#x2019; restructured IDA.</p>
<p id="C7P49">Its rise within the policymaking hierarchy would also see it assume responsibility for regional industrial development. O&#x2019;Farrell comments that &#x2018;no single development problem in Ireland has generated so much controversy and emotion as the concept of spatially polarised growth&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-86"><sup>86</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The Committee on Industrial Organisation and the National Industrial Economic Council had both largely concurred with the Department of Finance that industry should be concentrated rather than dispersed, as did the most thorough regional policy document of the era, the Buchanan Report of 1969.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-87"><sup>87</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Neither of the major political parties could afford to adopt this position. The Industrial Development Authority Act of 1969 formally assigned the IDA a regional development mandate, imparting an added impetus, as one senior IDA manager put it, &#x2018;to an activity that had been underway for some time&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-88"><sup>88</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Its Small Industries Programme was launched on a pilot basis in 1967 and extended across the country two&#x00A0;years later. IDA offices were opened in eight of the country&#x2019;s nine planning regions in 1971. (Responsibility for the Mid-West region, which included Shannon, had been allocated to SFADCo.) The IDA&#x2019;s Regional Industrial Plans for 1973&#x2013;1977 set out manufacturing job targets for large numbers of grouped towns and villages. Only 50 per cent of the new jobs envisaged were to be located in the nine growth centres recommended by Buchanan.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-89"><sup>89</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P50"><page id="167" chapter=""/>The period since 1961, and particularly since 1966, had already witnessed substantial industrial dispersal.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-90"><sup>90</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The Census of Industrial Production data presented in <xrefGrp>Chapter&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-5">5</xref></xrefGrp> showed that 42&#x2013;43 per cent of industrial employment had been located in Dublin in the 1930s and 1940s. The proportion remained around the same in 1961. It had fallen to 31 per cent by 1972. Redundancies were highest in the capital. New export-oriented industries were choosing or being induced to locate elsewhere.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-91"><sup>91</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P51">The developing pattern is presented to best effect in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-2">7.2</xref></xrefGrp>, which is based on data for 1974. It compares the regional distribution of &#x2018;new industry&#x2019; employment and overall manufacturing employment.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-92"><sup>92</sup></xref></xrefGrp> As revealed in the final column, the Mid-West/SFADCo region performed best by this measure, followed by the group of least-developed planning regions. The relatively low share of new industry locating in the advanced Eastern region is immediately apparent.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-2"?></p>
<p id="C7P52">The planning regions referred to in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-2">7.2</xref></xrefGrp> had been established under the Local Government (Planning and Development) Act of 1963. There was not an exact overlap between the least developed of these regions (Donegal, Sligo&#x2013;Leitrim, Mayo&#x2013;Galway and the Midlands) and the &#x2018;designated areas&#x2019; which were eligible for preferential grant treatment.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-93"><sup>93</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Westmeath, <page id="168" chapter=""/>for example, was in one of the least developed regions&#x2014;the Midlands&#x2014;but was not a designated area, while Kerry, which was not in one of the least developed regions, <i>was</i> a designated area.</p>
<p id="C7P53">Among the largest of the new foreign industries to have established in the latter areas by 1972 were Snia in Sligo; Pretty Polly and Liebherr in Kerry; and Digital, Standard Pressed Steel, Potez, and Steinbock/Crown Controls in Galway. These firms were of diverse nationalities. Snia was Italian; Potez was French; Steinbock and Liebherr were German; Pretty Polly was British. Digital, Standard Pressed Steel, and Crown Controls, which took over Steinbock in 1968, were American.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-77" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>77</sup></enumerator> Potez Industries employed around 100 at a separate plant in Galway over this period.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-78" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>78</sup></enumerator> McAleese provides a figure of 36,000 for &#x2018;new&#x2019; foreign industry employment in 1974 (Dermot McAleese, <i>A Profile of Grant-Aided Industry in Ireland</i>, (Dublin: Industrial Development Authority, 1977), table 3.3, 21). The more recent data source upon which <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-1">7.1</xref></xrefGrp> is based suggests a higher figure.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-79" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>79</sup></enumerator> The figure of 12,000 US-firm jobs in 1972 comes from <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-55" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank|O&#x2019;Mahony, Clare" date="2017" title="Regime Change in 1950s Ireland: The New Export-Oriented Foreign Investment Strategy" journalName="Irish Economic and Social History" vol="44" page="1" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Clare" mainName="O&#x2019;mahony" role="author">Clare O&#x2019;Mahony</nameGrp> (&#x2018;Regime Change in 1950s Ireland: The New Export-Oriented Foreign Investment Strategy&#x2019;. <i>Irish Economic and Social History</i> 44, 1 (2017): 46&#x2013;65</bibItem>) and is broadly consistent with the numbers reported by the US Chamber of Commerce for 1973 (<i>Irish Times</i>, 17 August 1973).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-80" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>80</sup></enumerator> The figure of 750 for Shannon in 1962 refers to employment at Lana-Knit (a joint US/UK venture) and Standard Pressed Steel.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-81" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>81</sup></enumerator> Jean L. Pyle, &#x2018;Export-Led Development and the Underemployment of Women: The Impact of Discriminatory Development Policy in the Republic of Ireland&#x201D;, in <i>Women Workers and Global Restructuring</i>, ed. Kathryn Ward (New York: Cornell University Press, 1990).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-82" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>82</sup></enumerator> Damien Hannan, <i>Rural Exodus: A Study of the Forces Influencing Large-Scale Migration of Irish Rural Youth</i> (London: Geoffrey Chapman, 1970); Mary Muldowney, &#x2018;We were conscious of the sort of people we mixed with: the state, social attitudes and the family in mid twentieth century Ireland&#x2019;, <i>History of the Family</i>, 13, 4 (2008): 402&#x2013;415; <i>Survey of Grant-Aided Industry: Survey Team&#x2019;s Report</i>, 97.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-83" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>83</sup></enumerator> SFADCo Report and Accounts for&#x00A0;Year ended 31st March 1963 (Shannon: Shannon Free Area Development Company Ltd., 1963), 18.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-84" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>84</sup></enumerator> IDA Annual Report 1972/73 (Dublin: Industrial Development Authority, 1973), 12.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-85" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>85</sup></enumerator> FitzGerald, <i>Planning in Ireland</i>, 240; <i>Survey of Grant-Aided Industry: Survey Team&#x2019;s Report</i>, 98.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-86" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>86</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-56" class="journalArticle" author="Patrick N., O&#x2019;Farrell" date="1971" journalIssue="4" title="The Regional Problem in Ireland: Some Reflections upon Development Strategy" journalName="Economic and Social Review" vol="2" page="453" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="O&#x2019;Farrell" mainName="Patrick N." role="author">Patrick N. O&#x2019;Farrell</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Regional Problem in Ireland: Some Reflections upon Development Strategy&#x2019;. <i>Economic and Social Review</i> 2, 4 (1971): 453.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-87" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>87</sup></enumerator> NESC (National Economic and Social Council), <i>Regional Policy in Ireland: A Review</i> (Dublin: National Economic and Social Council, 1975).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-88" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>88</sup></enumerator> <i>Irish Times</i>, 20 November 1973. Though grants had been available for industrial projects located in the &#x2018;undeveloped areas&#x2019; since 1952, their relative efficacy had been eroded by the introduction in 1956 of grants for investments elsewhere in the country.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-89" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>89</sup></enumerator> NESC, <i>Regional Policy in Ireland: A Review</i>, 48; Industrial Development Authority, Regional Industrial Plans 1973&#x2013;1977, (Dublin, Industrial Development Authority, 1972), 16.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-90" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>90</sup></enumerator> See Table 1, &#x2018;Regional industrial development&#x2019;, <i>Irish Times</i>, 20 November 1973.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-91" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>91</sup></enumerator> As pointed out earlier, almost all of the manufacturing employment increase between 1966 and 1972 was in &#x2018;new&#x2019; foreign industry.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-92" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>92</sup></enumerator> Dermot McAleese. <i>A Profile of Grant-Aided Industry in Ireland</i>, (Dublin: Industrial Development Authority, 1977), table 3.4, 9, 23. &#x2018;New industries&#x2019; refer to projects supported by SFADCo and by &#x2018;new industry grants&#x2019; (as opposed to &#x2018;small-industry&#x2019; or &#x2018;re-equipment grants&#x2019;) from the IDA.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-93" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>93</sup></enumerator> For a map of these regional groupings, see Patrick N. <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-57" class="journalArticle" author="O&#x2019;Farrell" date="1976" journalIssue="4" title="An Analysis of Industrial Closures: Irish Experience 1960&#x2013;1973" journalName="Regional Studies" vol="10" page="433" pageLast="448" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="O&#x2019;Farrell">O&#x2019;Farrell</nameGrp> (1976) &#x2018;An Analysis of Industrial Closures: Irish Experience 1960&#x2013;1973&#x2019;. <i>Regional Studies</i> 10, 4 (1976): 433&#x2013;448</bibItem>, Figure 1.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-floatGroup-1">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.007.0001" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-table-1" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-10"><title id="C7T1"><p><enumerator>Table 7.1</enumerator> Shannon and &#x2018;new foreign industry&#x2019;, 1962 and 1972</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1962</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>1972</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Employment in &#x2018;new&#x2019; foreign industry (including Shannon)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>7,000</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>36,000</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p><i>Of which</i>: US firms</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,700<sup>*</sup></p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>12,000</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Employment at Shannon Industrial Estate</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1,000</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>4,000</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p><i>Of which</i>: US firms</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>750</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>3,000</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>1963</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>1973</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Irish manufactured exports other than food, drink, and tobacco</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>&#x00A3;47 million</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>&#x00A3;430 million</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Shannon share of manufactured exports other than food, drink, and tobacco</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>11%</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>11%</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Note</i>: <sup>*</sup>Calculations based on Shannon Free Airport Development Company Ltd (SFADCo) annual reports and Industrial Development Authority lists of principal new industries with foreign participation, 1971 and 1973.</p>
<p><i>Source</i>: Denis O&#x2019;Hearn, &#x2018;Estimates of New Foreign Manufacturing Employment in Ireland 1956&#x2013;1972&#x2019;; Frank Barry and Clare O&#x2019;Mahony. &#x2018;Regime Change in 1950s Ireland&#x2019;; SFADCo Annual Reports (various years).</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-2" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.007.0002" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-table-2" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-11"><title id="C7T2"><p><enumerator>Table 7.2</enumerator> Regional distribution of manufacturing and &#x2018;new industry&#x2019; employment, 1974</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"/>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Share of total manufacturing employment (I) (%)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Share of &#x2018;new industry&#x2019; employment (II) (%)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Ratio (II/I)</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Least-developed regions</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>13.1</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>19.1</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>1.5</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Mid-West</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>7.7</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>12.9</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>1.7</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>East</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>46.4</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>23.6</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>0.5</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Rest of the country</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>32.8</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>44.4</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>1.4</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Total</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>100</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>100</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>1</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: derived from Dermot McAleese. <i>A Profile of Grant-Aided Industry in Ireland</i>, (Dublin: Industrial Development Authority, 1977), Table 3.4, 23.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div1-5" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.021.0005">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-12"><title id="C7S9"><p><enumerator>7.4</enumerator> Sectoral and Firm-Level Developments</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C7P54">The primary focus of both SFADCo and the IDA was on new &#x2018;greenfield&#x2019; investment projects. &#x2018;Brownfield&#x2019; FDI, entailing the acquisition and restructuring of existing businesses, is another common feature of the adjustment to freer trade.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-94"><sup>94</sup></xref></xrefGrp> It too would have been enhanced by the relaxation of foreign-ownership restrictions and the introduction of export profits tax relief. The acquisitions by Guinness and Halliday/Clarks have been discussed in earlier chapters. Other major brownfield investors included the US firms Grace Brothers and St Joe Paper, and British firms Courtaulds, Lyons, and Bond Worth. Unilever would expand further by acquisition. Each would be among the seventy or so largest manufacturing employers in the state in 1972.</p>
<p id="C7P55">Florida firm St Joe Paper had had a management agreement with National Board and Paper Mills in Waterford since 1958. National Board bought out Killeen Paper Mills in 1963 and both companies were acquired by St Joe Paper the following year.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-95"><sup>95</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Grace &#x0026; Co. bought out the indigenous chocolate confectionery firm Urney in 1963, acquiring a number of other smaller confectionery producers in the process. Its acquisition of the large Dublin milk distribution company Hughes Brothers in 1964 triggered the formation of Premier Dairies, upon which Hughes Brothers&#x2019; milk distribution business was swapped for Premier&#x2019;s ice cream interests. Anglo-Dutch Unilever had acquired the long-established fertilizer and animal feed producer Paul &#x0026; <page id="169" chapter=""/>Vincent in 1966 and would acquire both H. B. Ice Cream and Urney (which had been renamed H. B. Chocolates) from Grace &#x0026; Co. in 1973.</p>
<p id="C7P56">British industry was also restructuring over this period.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-96"><sup>96</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Man-made fibre producer Courtaulds, already a major employer in Northern Ireland, acquired several assets south of the border as part of its takeover of UK companies Symington &#x0026; Co. and Ashton Brothers in the late 1960s. Dundalk Textiles had been part of Symington &#x0026; Co. since 1941. Pre-independence linen and cotton producer Robert Usher, which had since diversified into rayon, had been acquired by Ashton Brothers in the mid-1960s, as had several of its suppliers and associated companies. The takeover of the British parent companies yielded Courtaulds an Irish workforce of over 1,000 by 1972.</p>
<p id="C7P57">Batchelors, the largest Irish vegetable processor after Erin Foods, was acquired by British Oxygen in 1969 and would be sold to Beechams in 1974. Gateaux, whose fruitcakes had established a foothold in the United Kingdom in the deprived conditions of the immediate post-war era, was acquired by tea-blender Lyons Irish Holdings in 1970. English carpet firm Bond Worth took over Kincora Carpets and O&#x2019;Brien Brothers (Spinners) in 1967, Donegal Carpets and Dublin furniture and bedding manufacturer O&#x2019;Dea in 1969, and Slumberland in 1972. It also held a large shareholding in G. T. Carpets of Donegal. <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-3">7.3</xref></xrefGrp> provides details of some of the major brownfield FDI acquisitions of the period.</p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-3"?></p>
<p><?Insert-Table ID="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-4"?></p>
<p alignment="centre"></p>
<p id="C7P58">There were numerous significant mergers and acquisitions within indigenous industry also.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-97"><sup>97</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Selected developments in sectors other than food and drink are outlined in <xrefGrp>Table&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-4">7.4</xref></xrefGrp>. Cement Roadstone Holdings (CRH) was formed through the merger of Irish Cement and Roadstone in 1970. Cement Ltd.&#x2019;s workforce had doubled over the course of the 1960s; Roadstone&#x2019;s had expanded by a factor of six. The latter was by far the larger of the two by the time of the merger. With a workforce in excess of 5,500, CRH was, along with the Guinness group, the largest manufacturing employer in the state at the time of EEC accession.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-98"><sup>98</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P59"><page id="170" chapter=""/>Smurfit, too, had expanded hugely over the course of the decade, when it vied with Clondalkin Paper Mills for control of the print, paper, and packaging sector. Gibson, Guy &#x0026; Smalldridge, formed from an earlier merger in 1964, employed around 1,000 when acquired by Clondalkin in 1969. <page id="171" chapter=""/><page id="172" chapter=""/>Michael Smurfit ascribed his loss in the acquisition battle, despite apparently having made a higher offer, to a desire among the firms involved to maintain control in Protestant hands.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-99"><sup>99</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Smurfit&#x2019;s packaging materials business had benefited from the rapid growth in manufactured exports of the era. Its acquisition of both Browne &#x0026; Nolan and the (Protestant) Hely Group in 1970 saw its workforce increase more than tenfold over the course of a decade.</p>
<p id="C7P60">There were major consolidations also in textiles, clothing, and leather. Seafield&#x2013;Gentex was formed from the merger of Seafield Fabrics and General Textiles in 1965. It employed more than 2,000 across its eleven factories in 1966.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-100"><sup>100</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Major acquisitions by Sunbeam&#x2013;Wolsey included the buy-out of UK company Salts in 1965 and indigenous producer Mulcahy Brothers in 1970. Its workforce increased from 2,500 in 1960 to almost 4,000 by 1972. Most of the leather tanneries also merged over this period. Carrick-on-Suir firm Plunder &#x0026; Pollock acquired New Ross Tanning in 1955, Gorey Leather in 1966, and Irish Tanners of Portlaw in 1969. Known for a period as Industrial and Commercial Holdings, it was renamed Irish Leathers in 1972. Plunder &#x0026; Pollock had employed a workforce of 300 in 1960; Irish Leathers had a workforce of 1,300 in 1972.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-101"><sup>101</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The acquisition of Dungarvan Leathers would be completed in 1973.</p>
<p id="C7P61">Consolidation in the vehicle assembly sector was associated with the formation of British Leyland in the United Kingdom. G. A. Brittain and Lincoln &#x0026; Nolan, the main assemblers of Morris and Austin vehicles respectively, <page id="173" chapter=""/>merged to form Brittain, Lincoln &#x0026; Nolan in 1966. Wexford agricultural machinery manufacturer Philip Pierce &#x0026; Co. was subsequently acquired, as was vehicle assembler Booth Poole, and the Brittain Group was awarded the contract to assemble Datsuns in 1972. Of the group&#x2019;s workforce of 1,878 at this time, around 1,000 were engaged in vehicle assembly, 300 were employed at the Pierce plant, and the remainder worked in sales and distribution. Ford&#x2019;s assembly operation remained larger.</p>
<p id="C7P62">Acquisitions by tobacco company P. J. Carroll of Dundalk doubled the size of its workforce over this period. Carrolls had taken over the leading pipe tobacco manufacturer Murray in 1960 and transferred production to Dundalk. Carrolls also integrated across the supply chain, acquiring a print and packaging company in 1971 and a distribution company in 1972. The formation of Masser-Waterford Ironfounders and acquisitions by clothing companies Glen Abbey and Doreen also saw the workforce at these firms expand to 500 or more by 1972.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-102"><sup>102</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-94" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>94</sup></enumerator> As explained by the former owner of Killarney footwear manufacturer Hilliard, it was hoped that the sale of the company to the British group G. B. Britton would allow the Killarney operation to narrow its product range and gain export market sales (<i>Irish Times</i>, 25 February 1972).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-95" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>95</sup></enumerator> St Joe&#x2019;s expansion into Europe was a consequence of the restrictions on price competition imposed by the US export cartel of which it was a member. These restrictions did not apply to trade between associate companies. This also explains US firm Continental Can&#x2019;s acquisition of a 20 per cent share in Smurfit in 1972: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-58" class="book" author="Smurfit, Michael" date="2014" title="A Life Worth Living" page="93" place="Dublin" publisher="Oaktree Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Michael" mainName="Smurfit" role="author">Michael Smurfit</nameGrp>, <i>A Life Worth Living</i> (Dublin: Oaktree Press, 2014), 93.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-96" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>96</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-59" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Hughes, Alan" partTitle="Mergers and Economic Performance in the UK: A Survey of the Empirical Evidence, 1950&#x2013;1990" editor="Bishop, Matthew|Kay, John" date="1993" title="European Mergers and Merger Policy" page="9" pageLast="95" place="Oxford" publisher="Oxford University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Alan" mainName="Hughes" role="partAuthor">Alan Hughes</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Mergers and Economic Performance in the UK: A Survey of the Empirical Evidence, 1950&#x2013;1990&#x2019;, in <i>European Mergers and Merger Policy</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="Matthew" mainName="Bishop" role="editor">Matthew Bishop</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="John" mainName="Kay" role="editor">John Kay</nameGrp> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1993), 9&#x2013;95.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-97" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>97</sup></enumerator> Many of the mergers and acquisitions are documented in <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-60" class="book" author="Restrictive Practices Commission" date="1975" title="Report of Studies into Industrial Concentration and Mergers in Ireland" place="Dublin" publisher="Stationery Office" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Restrictive Practices Commission">Restrictive Practices Commission</nameGrp>, <i>Report of Studies into Industrial Concentration and Mergers in Ireland</i> (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1975);</bibItem> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-61" class="book" author="Smith, Louis P. F.|Quinn, Gerard" date="1975" title="A Study of the Evolution of Concentration in the Irish Food Industry 1968&#x2013;1973" place="Brussels" publisher="EU Commission" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Louis P. F." mainName="Smith" role="author">Louis P. F. Smith</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Gerard" mainName="Quinn" role="author">Gerard Quinn</nameGrp>, <i>A Study of the Evolution of Concentration in the Irish Food Industry 1968&#x2013;1973</i> (Brussels: EU Commission, 1975).</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-98" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>98</sup></enumerator> Technically, quarrying&#x2014;in which Roadstone was primarily engaged&#x2014;is not included within the definition of manufacturing.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-99" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>99</sup></enumerator> Smurfit, <i>A Life Worth Living</i>, 79.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-100" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>100</sup></enumerator> Youghal Carpets and Navan Carpets merged in 1972 but continued to be reported upon as separate companies until 1973.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-101" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>101</sup></enumerator> Irish Leathers also had other minor interests in Ireland and owned a small UK manufacturer of chemical finishes.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-102" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>102</sup></enumerator> Waterford Iron Founders had been established as Allied Iron Founders (Ireland), a subsidiary of a large UK company, in 1936.</p></note>
</noteGroup>
<floatGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-floatGroup-2">
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-3" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.007.0003" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-table-3" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-13"><title id="C7T3"><p><enumerator>Table 7.3</enumerator> Selected Brownfield FDI acquisitions, 1960&#x2013;1972</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Acquiror</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Workforce prior to acquisition</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Acquired companies</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Workforce at time of acquisition</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>Employment, <i>c</i>. 1972</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Grace Brothers</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>&#x2013;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>HB Ice Cream,</p>
<p>HB Confectionery (formerly Urney),</p>
<p>Liam Devlin &#x0026; Sons, Old Dutch Confections, and others</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>300</p>
<p>670</p>
<p>150</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>1,500 (1973)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>St Joe Paper</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>&#x2013;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>National Board and Paper Mills,</p>
<p>Killeen Paper Mills</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>450</p>
<p>670</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 1,000 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Courtaulds</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>300 (sold to Sunbeam, 1965)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Robert Usher,</p>
<p>Slane Manufacturing, Loughrea Cottons, Dundalk Textiles</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>400</p>
<p>450</p>
<p>100</p>
<p>160</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>950 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Unilever</p>
<p>(Castleforbes Soap Factory and McDonnells Margarine)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>640</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Paul &#x0026; Vincent</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>250</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>900 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Lyons Irish Holdings</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>150</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Gateaux</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>660</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>538 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Bond Worth</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>&#x2013;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Kincora Carpets, O&#x2019;Brien Brothers (Spinners) Ltd, Donegal Carpets, O&#x2019;Dea, and others</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 500</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 500 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>British Oxygen</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>&#x2013;</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Batchelors</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 500</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p><i>c</i>. 500 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
<tableGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-tableGroup-4" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.007.0004" placement="float">
<table id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-table-4" frame="topbot">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-14"><title id="C7T4"><p><enumerator>Table 7.4</enumerator> Selected mergers and acquisitions (M/A) in indigenous industry, 1960&#x2013;1972</p></title></titleGroup>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Company</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>Workforce prior to major M/A</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Merged or acquired companies</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>Workforce <i>c</i>. M/A</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>Employment, 1972</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Irish Cement Group</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>900 (1962), 1,843 (1970)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Roadstone Holdings</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>3,491 (1970)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>CRH: 5,578 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Smurfit</p>
<p>post-acquisition of Browne &#x0026; Nolan</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>300 (1964),</p>
<p>920 (1970)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Hely Group (1970)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>2,300 (1970)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>Smurfit Group: 3,884 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Clondalkin Paper Mills</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>620 (1969)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Swift Brook (1969),</p>
<p>Gibson, Guy and Smalldridge (1969)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>200 (1970),</p>
<p>1,000 (1964)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>1,460 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Sunbeam&#x2013;Wolsey</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>2,500 (1960)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Salts (1965),</p>
<p>Mulcahy Bros (1970)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>850 (1960),</p>
<p>610 (1970)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>4,000 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Seafield Fabrics (including Blackwater Cottons, acquired in 1962)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>800 (1962)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Castleguard Textiles (1965),</p>
<p>General Textiles (1965)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>400 (1965),</p>
<p>830 (1964)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>Seafield&#x2013;Gentex: 2,100 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Plunder &#x0026; Pollock</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>330 (1960)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Gorey Leather (1967),</p>
<p>Irish Tanners (1969),</p>
<p>Dungarvan Leathers (1972&#x2013;1973)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>200 (1966),</p>
<p>400 (1966),</p>
<p>250 (1972)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>Irish Leathers: 1,300 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>G. A. Brittain</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>400 (1963)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Lincoln &#x0026; Nolan, Philip Pierce,</p>
<p>Booth Poole</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>500 (1960),</p>
<p>450 (1960),</p>
<p>140 (1971)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>Brittain Group: 1,878 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>P. J. Carroll (tobacco)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>840 (1968)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Murray (pipe tobacco) (1960),</p>
<p>Dakota (print and packaging) (1971),</p>
<p>P. C. Cahill (wholesale chemist &#x0026; distributor) (1972)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>100 (1961),</p>
<p>170 (1971),</p>
<p>520 (1972)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>1,540 (1973)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Glen Abbey</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>250 (1963)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Bradmola Mills (1964), Dublin Hosiery (1968)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>150 (1964), <i>c</i>. 500 (1968)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>919 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>Doreen</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>200 (1965)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Jack Toohey (1972)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>400 (1972)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>650 (1973)</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1" align="left"><p>A. H. Masser, Dublin</p></entry>
<entry colname="col2" align="left"><p>170 (1960)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col3" align="left"><p>Allied Ironfounders (Ireland)/Waterford Ironfounders (1955)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col4" align="left"><p>110 (1954)</p></entry>
<entry colname="col5" align="left"><p>Masser-Waterford Ironfounders: 600 (1972)</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<source><p><i>Source</i>: author.</p></source>
</table>
</tableGroup>
</floatGroup>
</div1>
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-div1-6" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0007.021.0006">
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-titleGroup-15"><title id="C7S10"><p><enumerator>7.5</enumerator> Erosion of the Sectarian Divide in Irish Business Life</p></title></titleGroup>
<p id="C7P63">Though sectarian divisions in the workplace had diminished over time, many firms continued into the 1960s to be known to the public as either Protestant or Catholic.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-103"><sup>103</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Paradoxically, while protectionism had led to a large increase in the number of Catholic firms, it facilitated the survival of older Protestant enterprises.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-104"><sup>104</sup></xref></xrefGrp> As Stephen Odlum recounts in his history of the Odlum flour milling family, the quota system introduced in the 1930s had effectively banished competition: &#x2018;With the market carved up between the participants, and penalties imposed on those who exceeded their production quota&#x2019;, the family was left &#x2018;with more time for pursuits such as hunting, fishing and yachting&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-105"><sup>105</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Trade liberalization made such cartels unsustainable. Increased scale was necessary for survival in the new more competitive environment, and most Irish firms were tiny by international standards. Family firms were perceived <page id="174" chapter=""/>as particularly problematic.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-106"><sup>106</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The determination among some Protestant businesses to keep control in the hands of a shrinking body of co-religionists had become a source of acute weakness.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-107"><sup>107</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P64">The mergers and acquisitions of the era paid no heed to the religious associations of earlier times. The earliest high-profile developments in this regard were in banking. To avoid the threat of foreign takeover, the Bank of Ireland merged with the Hibernian Bank in 1958, a development that &#x2018;would have astounded the Hibernian&#x2019;s founders&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-108"><sup>108</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The National Bank, another of the traditionally Catholic banks, joined the group in 1966. A similar fusion of traditions occurred with the formation of Allied Irish Banks later that year.</p>
<p id="C7P65">In manufacturing, the entry of foreign firms frequently acted as a catalyst. Beamish &#x0026; Crawford was sold to Canadian Breweries in 1962. By the middle of the decade, many of the other Irish breweries, including Catholic-owned Macardles and Smithwicks, had been acquired by Guinness. The milk distribution companies that merged in the wake of the entry of Grace &#x0026; Co. included traditionally Protestant and Catholic firms. The&#x00A0;year 1966 witnessed the formation of Irish Distillers and the merger of Jacobs and Bolands Biscuits. The Hely Group had been formed from the merger of the largest print, paper, and publishing firms of the 1920s. It was acquired by Smurfit in 1970. By 1972, Gouldings and Dockrells had been acquired by a consortium controlled by Catholic entrepreneur Tony O&#x2019;Reilly.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-109"><sup>109</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C7P66">An anecdote recounted by Tony Farmar illustrates the broader changes taking place in Irish society. Asked in the 1960s to recommend a new company secretary for an old-style Protestant building firm, Craig Gardner felt obliged to point out that the candidate &#x2018;dug with the other foot&#x2019;. They were informed that this was of no significance as long as the candidate was competent.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-110"><sup>110</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Stokes Brothers &#x0026; Pim merged with the Catholic firm Kennedy Crowley in 1972. Craig Gardner became part of the worldwide network of UK firm Price Waterhouse later in the decade.</p>
<p id="C7P67">Not all of the imbalances in recruitment and management had been ascribable to sectarianism. As Cullen observes in his study of Easons:</p>
<p><displayText id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-displayText-3" class="prosequote">
<p><page id="175" chapter=""/>Staff were recruited from the immediate circle of the principal, and since many recruits were accepted on the recommendation of the senior people in the firm, continued recruitment tended to be slanted in that direction.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-111"><sup>111</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
</displayText></p>
<p fullOut="Y" id="C7P68">By the time of EEC entry, the era of tightly controlled family businesses was coming to an end, many of the traditionally Protestant and Catholic firms had merged, denominationally distinct workplaces had all but disappeared, and educational credentials were eroding the significance of personal connections in recruitment and promotion.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-103" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>103</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-62" class="book" author="Farmar, Tony" date="1996" title="Heitons&#x2014;a Managed Transition: Heitons in the Irish Coal, Iron and Building Markets, 1818&#x2013;1996" page="34" place="Dublin" publisher="A. &#x0026; A. Farmar" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Tony" mainName="Farmar" role="author">Tony Farmar</nameGrp>, <i>Heitons&#x2014;a Managed Transition: Heitons in the Irish Coal, Iron and Building Markets, 1818&#x2013;1996</i> (Dublin: A. &#x0026; A. Farmar, 1996), 34.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-104" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>104</sup></enumerator> Many of the most significant companies of the pre-independence era remained among the largest Irish industrial companies traded on the Dublin Stock Exchange in 1966: <i>Irish Times</i>, 8 November 1966.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-105" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>105</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-63" class="book" author="Odlum, Stephen" date="2015" title="Flour Power, the Story of the Odlum Flour Milling Families" page="6" place="Dublin" publisher="Zest Publications" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Stephen" mainName="Odlum" role="author">Stephen Odlum</nameGrp>, <i>Flour Power, the Story of the Odlum Flour Milling Families</i> (Dublin: Zest Publications, 2015), 6.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-106" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>106</sup></enumerator> Garret FitzGerald, <i>Irish Times</i>, 3 July 1968; <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-64" class="book" author="Committee on Industrial Progress" date="1973" title="General Report" page="37" pageLast="38" place="Stationery Office" publisher="Dublin" purpose="display"><nameGrp nameType="nonPersonal" mainName="Committee on Industrial Progress">Committee on Industrial Progress</nameGrp>, <i>General Report</i> (Dublin: Stationery Office, 1973), 37&#x2013;38</bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-107" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>107</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-65" class="unclassified" author="Quinn, James" date="2002" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="James" mainName="Quinn" role="author">James Quinn</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Industry Evolution: A Comparative Study of Irish Wholesaling&#x2019;. Ph.D. thesis, Dublin City University, 2002.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-108" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>108</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-66" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Lyons, F. S. L." partTitle="Reflections on a Bicentenary" editor="Lyons, F. S. L." date="1983" title="Bank of Ireland 1783&#x2013;1983, Bicentenary Essays" page="209" place="Dublin" publisher="Gill and Macmillan" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="F. S. L." mainName="Lyons" role="partAuthor">F. S. L. Lyons</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Reflections on a Bicentenary&#x2019;. In <i>Bank of Ireland 1783&#x2013;1983, Bicentenary Essays</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="F. S. L." mainName="Lyons" role="editor">F. S. L. Lyons</nameGrp> (Dublin: Gill and Macmillan, 1983), 209.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-109" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>109</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-67" class="bookChapter" partAuthor="Barry, Frank" partTitle="The Life and Death of Protestant Businesses in Independent Ireland" editor="Ian, d&#x2019;Alton|Milne, Ida" date="2019" title="Protestant and Irish: The Minority&#x2019;s Accommodation with Independent Ireland" page="155" pageLast="170" place="Cork" publisher="Cork University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="partAuthor">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Life and Death of Protestant Businesses in Independent Ireland&#x2019;, in <i>Protestant and Irish: The Minority&#x2019;s Accommodation with Independent Ireland</i>, ed. <nameGrp foreNames="D&#x2019;Alton" mainName="Ian" role="editor">Ian d&#x2019;Alton</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Ida" mainName="Milne" role="editor">Ida Milne</nameGrp> (Cork: Cork University Press, 2019), 155&#x2013;70.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-110" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>110</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-68" class="book" author="Farmar, Tony" date="2013" title="The Versatile Profession: A History of Accountancy in Ireland since 1850" page="119" place="Dublin" publisher="Chartered Accountants Ireland" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Tony" mainName="Farmar" role="author">Tony Farmar</nameGrp>, <i>The Versatile Profession: A History of Accountancy in Ireland since 1850</i> (Dublin: Chartered Accountants Ireland, 2013), 119.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-note-111" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>111</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-7-bibItem-69" class="book" author="Cullen, Louis M." date="1989" title="Eason &#x0026; Son: A History" page="111" place="Dublin" publisher="Eason &#x0026; Son" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Louis M." mainName="Cullen" role="author">Louis M. Cullen</nameGrp>, <i>Eason &#x0026; Son: A History</i> (Dublin: Eason &#x0026; Son, 1989), 111.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div1>
</textMatter>
</chapter>
</mainText>
</book>