<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OXFORD//DTD OXCHAPML//EN" "OxChapML.dtd">
<book id="oso-9780198878230-book-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.001.0001" OSOsubject="physics">
<bookMeta id="oso-9780198878230-bookMeta-1">
<versionInfo>
<versionDate>2023-05-08</versionDate>
<versionDesc>Proofs</versionDesc>
</versionInfo>
<metaItem about="book">
<metaItem about="DTD">
<metaDescribes predicate="DTDname">OxChapML</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
<metaItem about="TCIgroup">
<metaItem about="TCI">
<metaDescribes predicate="TCIname">OUP TCI</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="version">20170301.0</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaItem>
<metaDescribes predicate="product">oso</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="colour-figures-for-online">Yes</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="publishing-group">oso US</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="captured-by">Integra</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</bookMeta>
<mainText id="oso-9780198878230-mainText-1">
<chapter id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0009">
<metaInfo id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-metaInfo-1">
<versionInfo>
<versionDate>2023-05-08</versionDate>
<versionDesc>Proofs</versionDesc>
</versionInfo>
<creatorGroup>
<creator class="author" invertedForm="Barry, Frank"><forenames>Frank</forenames><surname>Barry</surname></creator>
</creatorGroup>
<abstract>
<p>The epilogue provides a brief overview of some key findings. The industrial expansion of the Cumann na nGaedheal&#x00A0;years is likely to have been more substantial than has generally been supposed, and the conservative approach adopted in most areas of economic policy is understandable in light of the circumstances of the times. Though the contemporary economics community had been highly critical of Fianna F&#x00E1;il policy in the 1930s, governments of all political dispositions became more protectionist and interventionist with the onset of the Great Depression, and quantitative economic historians judge Ireland to have emerged a net beneficiary from the economic war with the United Kingdom. The large number of jobs that had been created under protectionism, however, made it difficult to dismantle the tariff regime when external circumstances changed. The strategy of &#x2018;industrialization by invitation&#x2019; provided a route through the difficult interest-group politics of outward reorientation. Comparison with the performance of other independent states may in any case entail the application of an overly taxing standard: Ireland was unusual in that it continued to share a common labour market with its larger and more prosperous neighbour. Economies of this type can expand more dramatically when circumstances are advantageous and decline more precipitously when they are not. This provides a framework through which the later Celtic Tiger era might be viewed. The book ends by summarizing the evidence on the share of foreign-owned firms in manufacturing employment over the first half-century of independence.</p>
</abstract>
<keySubjectWords>
<keyword>Cumann na nGaedheal</keyword>
<keyword>Fianna F&#x00E1;il</keyword>
<keyword>EEC accession</keyword>
<keyword>EEC membership</keyword>
<keyword>regional economy</keyword>
<keyword>income convergence</keyword>
<keyword>Celtic Tiger era</keyword>
<keyword>foreign-owned industry</keyword></keySubjectWords>
<disclaimer><p><i>Industry and Policy in Independent Ireland, 1922&#x2013;1972</i>. Frank Barry, Oxford University Press. &#x00A9; Frank Barry (2023). DOI: 10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0009</p></disclaimer>
<metaItem about="book">
<metaItem about="DTD">
<metaDescribes predicate="DTDname">OxChapML</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
<metaItem about="TCIgroup">
<metaItem about="TCI">
<metaDescribes predicate="TCIname">OUP TCI</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="version">20170301.0</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaItem>
<metaDescribes predicate="product">oso</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="colour-figures-for-online">Yes</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="publishing-group">oso US</metaDescribes>
<metaDescribes predicate="captured-by">Integra</metaDescribes>
</metaItem>
</metaInfo>
<titleGroup id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-titleGroup-1"><title id="C9"><p><page id="198" chapter=""/>Epilogue</p></title></titleGroup>
<textMatter id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-textMatter-1">
<div1 id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-div1-1" doi="10.1093/oso/9780198878230.003.0009.021.0001">
<p id="C9P1">Ireland&#x2019;s overall growth performance from independence until well into the European Economic Community (EEC) era was poor by international standards. The early decades of the state&#x2019;s existence had been dominated by issues of legitimacy, sovereignty, and security, leading Kieran Kennedy and his co-authors to suggest that &#x2018;it was not until 25&#x00A0;years after the achievement of independence that economic development could receive the degree of attention that might otherwise have been expected from the start&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-1"><sup>1</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C9P2">More recent research dates Ireland&#x2019;s underperformance primarily to this later period. Growth rates were low generally across Europe in the 1920s and 1930s. The Cumann na nGaedheal governments of the&#x00A0;years to 1932 had achieved some success in agricultural and infrastructural development as well as in expanding the boundaries of independence, and the industrial expansion of the time is likely to have been more substantial than has generally been supposed. De Valera was more generous than most on the losing civil war side in recognizing their achievements, reportedly remarking to his son Vivion after coming to power that &#x2018;when we got in and saw the files [.&#x00A0;.&#x00A0;.] They did a magnificent job, Viv. They did a magnificent job.&#x2019;<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-2"><sup>2</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C9P3">Though the contemporary economics community had been highly critical of Fianna F&#x00E1;il policy in the 1930s, governments of all political dispositions became more protectionist and interventionist with the onset of the Great Depression, and debt default was widespread. The land annuities dispute with Britain caused significant hardship, but the terms of the settlement were such that, in the judgement of quantitative economic historians, &#x2018;Ireland under Fianna F&#x00E1;il rule may not have lost the economic war.&#x2019;<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-3"><sup>3</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C9P4">The problem with the extensive protectionism of the time was the path dependence to which it gave rise, as the Fiscal Inquiry Committee of 1923 had warned. The large number of jobs that had been created&#x2014;and that <page id="199" chapter=""/>remained dependent on protection for their survival&#x2014;made it difficult to dismantle the tariff regime when external circumstances changed. The strategy of &#x2018;industrialization by invitation&#x2019; provided a route through the difficult interest-group politics of outward reorientation.</p>
<p id="C9P5">Comparison with the performance of other independent states may in any case entail the application of an overly taxing standard. Sidney Pollard, in his major work on the process of European industrialization, suggests that Ireland&#x2019;s problems&#x2014;rather than stemming from independence&#x2014;&#x2018;were more akin to those of the major non-industrialized regions inside advanced countries, like the Italian South, Corsica, and the French South-West&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-4"><sup>4</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Ireland was unusual among independent states in that it continued to share a common labour market with its larger and more prosperous neighbour. Economies of this type can expand more dramatically when circumstances are advantageous and decline more precipitously when they are not.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-5"><sup>5</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Even within the United Kingdom, regional policy achieved only limited success in counteracting the gravitational forces drawing economic activity towards London and the surrounding South East region.</p>
<p id="C9P6">The 1926 Banking Commission had recognised that the Free State &#x2018;is now, and will undoubtedly long continue to be, an integral part of the economic system at the head of which stands Great Britain&#x2019;.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-6"><sup>6</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The new export-oriented foreign investment strategy of the mid-1950s initiated the process of decoupling Ireland from the UK market. The latter still served as destination for 90 per cent of Irish merchandise exports in 1955. The figure had fallen to 73 per cent by 1960 and to 55 per cent by 1973. It would fall much further over subsequent decades.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-7"><sup>7</sup></xref></xrefGrp></p>
<p id="C9P7">Outward reorientation had been a major determinant of the erosion of the sectarian divide in Irish business life and of the change in mindset that led to the expansion in educational attainment. EEC membership brought dramatic changes on a number of other fronts. The adjustment of Irish agricultural prices to Western European levels saw real agricultural incomes rise by 40 per cent over the&#x00A0;years to 1978, though the prosperity of rural Ireland today compared to the position prior to EEC membership owes much to off-farm employment in local towns, regional hubs, and nearby cities. <page id="200" chapter=""/>Unimpeded access to a vastly broader market increased Ireland&#x2019;s attractiveness as an export platform for foreign multinational corporations. The <i>Investment in Education</i> report of 1965 had pointed to the waste of natural talent associated with a non-meritocratic education system: the ending of the marriage bar and the increase in female employment further expanded the pool of talent available to the economy, as well, of course, as enhancing the opportunities for individual fulfilment.</p>
<p id="C9P8">Ireland continued to underperform in comparative terms however until the confluence of circumstances that led to the dramatic growth spurt of the 1990s. EEC accession had come at a particularly difficult time. The two major oil shocks of the 1970s had thrown the industrialized world into deep recession. Prospects for convergence on broader Western European living standards were further damaged by the inappropriate Irish fiscal response of the time. The eventual resolution of the debt crisis that ensued coincided with the coming into being of the Single European Market. Ireland&#x2019;s share of European-bound US foreign direct investment (FDI) had contracted in the 1980s. It expanded dramatically over the following decade, strengthening the country&#x2019;s export concentration in cyclically resilient sectors such as pharmaceuticals, medical devices, and information technology-enabled services.</p>
<p id="C9P9">Ireland&#x2019;s aggregate trade and production statistics are today dominated by the activities of these foreign corporations. Irish-owned firms are much more labour-intensive and much less import-dependent than their foreign-owned counterparts however.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-8"><sup>8</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Their contribution to economic performance is substantially more significant than the aggregate data might suggest.</p>
<p id="C9P10">Indigenous-dominated agri-food sectors were among those in which Ireland displayed a strong revealed comparative advantage in the&#x00A0;years leading up to EEC accession. By 1992, businesses such as the Kerry Group, Avonmore Foods, Waterford Foods, Dairygold, and Goodman International had global workforces numbering in the thousands. So too did the Smurfit Group and Cement Roadstone Holdings. The former employed 15,000 in 1992, the latter almost 12,000. Most of these firms have expanded massively since then, in many cases beyond the European Union&#x2019;s borders.</p>
<p id="C9P11">Ireland had also displayed a revealed comparative advantage in textiles, clothing, and footwear, though the number of foreign-owned export-oriented firms in these sectors would have impacted on the usefulness of the index as a predictor of subsequent developments. Job numbers in these <page id="201" chapter=""/>sectors halved by 1987 and would continue to decline thereafter. Rather than being reallocated within the EEC, which might have benefited Irish industry had cost competitiveness been maintained, production and employment shifted to the developing world. The vast bulk of the job losses were in Irish-owned companies.</p>
<p id="C9P12">The revival in Irish indigenous industry from the late 1980s is an often-forgotten element in analyses of the &#x2018;Celtic Tiger&#x2019; phenomenon.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-9"><sup>9</sup></xref></xrefGrp> That it occurred alongside an increase in the export intensity of the sector is likely to have been a reflection less of the transformation of existing enterprises than of their replacement by newer ones.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-10"><sup>10</sup></xref></xrefGrp> Industrial adjustment is not frictionless.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-11"><sup>11</sup></xref></xrefGrp> In the case of indigenous industry, it may have taken a decade-and-a-half to complete.</p>
<p id="C9P13">The demise of large numbers of major employers over this period, as charted in <xrefGrp>Chapter&#x00A0;<xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-8">8</xref></xrefGrp>, tells one part of the story. The experience contrasts sharply with that of the previous half-century. All of the major employers of 1929 remained in operation at the time of EEC accession, though Bannatyne &#x0026; Co. had been acquired by Ranks in 1930. Of the major employers of 1948, though several had merged or been acquired, only two had closed. The globalized trade environment of the EEC era would prove much less forgiving. Of the approximately 70 firms employing workforces of 500 or more in 1972, half had disappeared or contracted massively by the late 1980s. The high rate of attrition of long-established firms would continue into the future.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-12"><sup>12</sup></xref></xrefGrp> The other part of the story&#x2014;the emergence of new export-oriented indigenous businesses&#x2014;is a project for the future.</p>
<p id="C9P14">Finally, to return to one of the questions raised at the outset of this research: what was the share of foreign-owned industry in manufacturing employment over the first half-century of independence? According to the data compiled by the Industrial Development Authority, the foreign share in 1972 stood at a little over one-third. Estimates for earlier periods are <page id="202" chapter=""/>reliant on educated guesswork. Guinness and Ford were the major foreign-owned industrial employers in 1922, followed in a distant third place by Furness &#x0026; Withy, the UK owners of Rushbrooke Dockyard. These three firms would have accounted for perhaps 10 per cent of manufacturing employment. Across the entirety of manufacturing (as measured by the Census of Industrial Production) the foreign share may have been in the region of 15 per cent.</p>
<p id="C9P15">By 1929, several UK tobacco firms had established substantial operations in Dublin; Williams &#x0026; Woods, the largest confectionery and jam producer, had been acquired by Crosse &#x0026; Blackwell; and employment at Ford was close to an all-time peak. Indigenous industry had expanded too, though not as rapidly, suggesting that the foreign share may have grown to a level of perhaps 20 per cent or so.</p>
<p id="C9P16">The indigenous and foreign segments appear to have kept largely abreast of each other over the next several decades. Among the sectors surveyed by the Committee on Industrial Organisation in the early 1960s, the foreign share was a little in excess of 30 per cent.<xrefGrp role="footnote"><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-13"><sup>13</sup></xref></xrefGrp> As several indigenous-dominated sectors were underrepresented, the foreign share across all of manufacturing was probably close to around one-quarter.</p>
<p id="C9P17">By 1972, the tariff factories of the protectionist era and the few externally owned firms that predated independence were complemented by the brownfield and greenfield export-oriented foreign investors that had established in Ireland since the mid-1950s. By the early 2000s, foreign-owned firms comprised close to 50 per cent of manufacturing employment. This remains the case to the present day.</p>
<noteGroup>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-1" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>1</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-1" class="book" author="Kennedy, Kieran|Giblin, Thomas|McHugh, Deirdre" date="1988" title="The Economic Development of Ireland in the Twentieth Century" vol="255" place="London" publisher="Routledge" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Kieran" mainName="Kennedy" role="partAuthor">Kieran Kennedy</nameGrp>, <nameGrp foreNames="Thomas" mainName="Giblin" role="partAuthor">Thomas Giblin</nameGrp>, and <nameGrp foreNames="Deirdre" mainName="Mchugh" role="partAuthor">Deirdre McHugh</nameGrp>, <i>The Economic Development of Ireland in the Twentieth Century</i> (London: Routledge, 1988), 255</bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-2" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>2</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-2" class="book" author="Coogan, Tim Pat" date="1995" title="De Valera: Long Fellow, Long Shadow" page="426" place="London" publisher="Arrow Books" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Tim Pat" mainName="Coogan" role="author">Tim Pat Coogan</nameGrp>, <i>De Valera: Long Fellow, Long Shadow</i> (London: Arrow Books, 1995), 426</bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-3" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>3</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-3" class="journalArticle" author="Neary, J. Peter|Gr&#x00E1;da, Cormac &#x00D3;" date="1991" journalIssue="107" title="Protection, Economic War and Structural Change: The 1930s in Ireland" journalName="Irish Historical Studies" vol="27" page="250" pageLast="266" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="J. Peter" mainName="Neary" role="author">J. Peter Neary</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Cormac &#x00D3;" mainName="Gr&#x00e1;da" role="author">Cormac &#x00D3; Gr&#x00E1;da</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Protection, Economic War and Structural Change: The 1930s in Ireland&#x2019;. <i>Irish Historical Studies</i> 27, 107 (1991): 250&#x2013;66.</bibItem> See also <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-4" class="journalArticle" author="Kevin, O&#x2019;Rourke" date="1991" journalIssue="2" title="Burn Everything British But Their Coal: The Anglo-Irish Economic War of the 1930s" journalName="Journal of Economic History" vol="51" page="357" pageLast="366" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="O&#x2019;Rourke" mainName="Kevin" role="author">Kevin O&#x2019;Rourke</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Burn Everything British But Their Coal: The Anglo-Irish Economic War of the 1930s&#x2019;. <i>Journal of Economic History</i> 51, 2 (1991): 357&#x2013;66.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-4" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>4</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-5" class="book" author="Pollard, Sidney" date="1981" title="Peaceful Conquest: The Industrialization of Europe, 1760&#x2013;1970" page="324" place="Oxford" publisher="Oxford University Press" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Sidney" mainName="Pollard" role="author">Sidney Pollard</nameGrp>, <i>Peaceful Conquest: The Industrialization of Europe, 1760&#x2013;1970</i> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1981), 324.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-5" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>5</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-6" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank" date="2002" title="The Celtic Tiger Era: Delayed Convergence or Regional Boom?" journalName="ESRI Quarterly Economic Commentary" vol="21" page="84" pageLast="91" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Celtic Tiger Era: Delayed Convergence or Regional Boom?&#x2019; <i>ESRI Quarterly Economic Commentary</i> 21 (2002): 84&#x2013;91.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-6" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>6</sup></enumerator> Banking Commission, Final Reports (Dublin: Banking Commission, 1927), s. 6.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-7" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>7</sup></enumerator> Indigenous firms, however, remain much more heavily oriented towards the United Kingdom than Ireland&#x2019;s foreign-owned industrial sector: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-7" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank" date="2021" title="From the Treaty to Brexit: The Evolution of Ireland&#x2019;s Export Dependence on the UK Market" journalName="History Ireland" page="93" pageLast="96" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, &#x2018;From the Treaty to Brexit: The Evolution of Ireland&#x2019;s Export Dependence on the UK Market&#x2019;. <i>History Ireland</i> (2021): 93&#x2013;96.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-8" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>8</sup></enumerator> <i>Per &#x20AC;1 million of merchandise exports,</i> Irish-owned companies today employ more than three times as many workers as foreign-owned firms and spend twenty times as much on Irish raw materials: <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-8" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank" date="2021" title="From the Treaty to Brexit: The Evolution of Ireland&#x2019;s Export Dependence on the UK Market" journalName="History Ireland" page="93" pageLast="96" purpose="display"><xrefGrp><xref ref="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-7">ibid</xref></xrefGrp></bibItem>.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-9" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>9</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-9" class="journalArticle" author="O&#x2019;Malley, Eoin" date="1998" title="The Revival of Irish Indigenous Industry 1987&#x2013;1997" journalName="Quarterly Economic Commentary" page="35" pageLast="57" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Eoin" mainName="O&#x2019;malley" role="author">Eoin O&#x2019;Malley</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Revival of Irish Indigenous Industry 1987&#x2013;1997&#x2019;. <i>ESRI Quarterly Economic Commentary</i> April (1998): 35&#x2013;57.</bibItem></p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-10" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>10</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-10" class="journalArticle" author="Whelan, Ciara|Walsh, Patrick P" date="2000" title="The Importance of Structural Change in Industry for Growth" journalName="Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland" vol="29" page="1" pageLast="32" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Ciara" mainName="Whelan" role="author">Ciara Whelan</nameGrp> and <nameGrp foreNames="Patrick P" mainName="Walsh" role="author">Patrick P Walsh</nameGrp>, &#x2018;The Importance of Structural Change in Industry for Growth&#x2019;. <i>Journal of the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland</i> 29 (2000): 1&#x2013;32.</bibItem> As suggested by Frances Ruane and Eoin O&#x2019;Malley in the ensuing discussion, determining the validity of this hypothesis requires the type of firm-level data employed here.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-11" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>11</sup></enumerator> Textbook analyses of the costs of trade liberalization typically focus on the disruption to employment, the costs of which are known to be borne disproportionately by older, less educated workers with long periods of tenure in their former jobs.</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-12" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>12</sup></enumerator> Directly comparable studies of this aspect of the consequences of trade liberalization are rare. In the case of the United Kingdom (which is not the ideal comparator), by far the largest share of the manufacturing firms on the list of 100 largest employers in 1972 remained on the equivalent list for 1992: Martin Fiedler and Howard Gospel, <i>The Top 100 Largest Employers in UK and Germany in the Twentieth Century. Data (ca. 1907, 1935/38, 1955/57, 1972/73, 1992/95</i>) (Cologne: University of Cologne, Department of Economic and Business History, 2010).</p></note>
<note id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-note-13" type="footnote"><p><enumerator><sup>13</sup></enumerator> <bibItem id="oso-9780198878230-chapter-9-bibItem-11" class="journalArticle" author="Barry, Frank|Barry, Linda|Menton, Aisling" date="2016" journalIssue="4" title="Tariff&#x2010;Jumping Foreign Direct Investment in Protectionist Era Ireland" journalName="Economic History Review" vol="69" page="1285" pageLast="1308" purpose="display"><nameGrp foreNames="Frank" mainName="Barry" role="author">Frank Barry</nameGrp>, <nameGrp foreNames="Linda" mainName="Barry" role="author">Linda Barry</nameGrp>, and <nameGrp foreNames="Aisling" mainName="Menton" role="author">Aisling Menton</nameGrp>, &#x2018;Tariff&#x2010;Jumping Foreign Direct Investment in Protectionist Era Ireland&#x2019;. <i>Economic History Review</i> 69, 4 (2016): 1285&#x2013;308.</bibItem></p></note>
</noteGroup>
</div1>
</textMatter>
</chapter>
</mainText>
</book>